[
  {
    "prompt": "A",
    "response": "first letter of the Roman alphabet, based on Greekalpha(seealpha). In music from c. 1600 as the name of the sixth note of the natural scale; it is the note given by a fixed-tone instrument (usually oboe or organ) to which all the instruments of an orchestra are tuned. As a blood type, 1926, denoting A agglutinogens. TheA sideof a two-sided record (by 1962, seeside(n.)) held the material chosen for promotion.A-bomb, short foratom bomb, was in newspaper headlines by Aug. 8, 1945."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "a",
    "response": "first letter of the Roman alphabet, based on Greekalpha(seealpha). In music from c. 1600 as the name of the sixth note of the natural scale; it is the note given by a fixed-tone instrument (usually oboe or organ) to which all the instruments of an orchestra are tuned. As a blood type, 1926, denoting A agglutinogens. TheA sideof a two-sided record (by 1962, seeside(n.)) held the material chosen for promotion.A-bomb, short foratom bomb, was in newspaper headlines by Aug. 8, 1945."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aardvark",
    "response": "alsoaard-vark, South African groundhog, 1833 (in German from 1824), from Afrikaans Dutchaardvark, literally \"earth-pig\" (it burrows), fromaard\"earth,\" from Proto-Germanic*ertho-(seeearth(n.)) +vark\"pig,\" from Middle Dutchvarken\"small pig,\" which is from Proto-Germanic*farhaz(source also of Old High Germanfarah, GermanFerkel\"young pig, sucking pig,\" a diminutive form; Old Englishfearh), from PIE root*porko-\"young pig.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aardwolf",
    "response": "alsoaard-wolf, \"small, insectivorous mammal native to East and Southern Africa, related to the hyena,\" 1833, from Afrikaans Dutchaardwolf, literally \"earth-wolf,\" fromaard\"earth\" (seeearth(n.)) +wolf\"wolf\" (seewolf(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aaron",
    "response": "masc. proper name, in the Old Testament the brother of Moses, from HebrewAharon, which is said to be probably of Egyptian origin. The Arabic form isHarun. Related:Aaronic.Aaron's beardas a popular name for various plants (including St. John's wort and a kind of dwarf evergreen) deemed to look hairy in some way is from 1540s.Aaron's rodis from 1834 in botany, 1849 in ornamentation; the reference is biblical (Exodus vii.19, etc.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aba",
    "response": "outer garment of coarse, woolen stuff, of a type worn in Arabia and Syria, 1811, from Arabic. Also of the cloth it is made from (often goat or camel hair)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aback",
    "response": "c. 1200, \"toward the rear,\" a contraction of Old Englishon bæc \"backward, behind, at or on the back;\" seea-(1) +back(n.). Now surviving mainly intaken aback, which originally was a nautical expression in reference to a vessel's square sails when a sudden change of wind flattens them back against the masts and stops the forward motion (1754). The figurative sense from this, \"suddenly or unexpectedly checked or disappointed,\" is by 1792."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abacus",
    "response": "late 14c., \"sand table for drawing, calculating, etc.,\" also \"art of calculating with an abacus,\" from Latinabacus, from Greekabax(genitiveabakos) \"counting table, board for drawing,\" a word of uncertain etymology. It is said to be from a Semitic source, such as Phoenician or Hebrewabaq\"sand strewn on a surface for writing,\" literally \"dust,\" from the Semitic roota-b-q\"to fly off,\" but Beekes and others find this \"semantically weak.\"Originally a drawing board covered with dust or sand on which mathematical equations or calculations could be traced and erased. In reference to the other type of abacus, a counting frame with beads or balls strung on wires or rods, it is attested from 17c. or later in English. Both types were known in antiquity across Eurasia. Related:Abacist(late 14c.)"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abaft",
    "response": "\"in or farther toward the back part (of a ship),\" as opposed toforward, 1590s, from Middle Englishon baft(late 13c.) \"back, behind, to the rear,\" from Old Englishon bæftan. For first element, seea-(1). The second component is itself a compound ofbe\"by\" (seeby) andæftan\"aft\" (seeaft). The word has been saved by the sailors (the stern being the \"after\" part of a vessel), the lubbers having left it in Middle English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abalienate",
    "response": "in civil law, \"transfer title of ownership to another,\" 1550s, from Latinabalienatus, past participle ofabalienare\"to remove, separate, alienate, make formal transfer of,\" literally \"to convey away,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +alienare\"to separate\" (fromalius\"another, other, different,\" from PIE root*al-\"beyond\"). Related:Abalienated;abalienating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abalienation",
    "response": "\"act of transferring title of ownership,\" 1650s, from Latinabalienationem(nominativeabalienatio), in law, \"transfer of property, sale,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabalienare\"to separate, transfer the ownership of,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +alienare\"to separate\" (fromalius\"another, other, different,\" from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abalone",
    "response": "type of large mollusk found on the California coast, 1850, American English, from Spanishabulon, a loan-word from Rumsen (an extinct native language in the Costanoan family),aluan, said to mean \"red abalone.\" Prized for its meat (once an important California export) and for the mother-of-pearl in its large shells (also calledear-shells)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abandon",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to give up (something) absolutely, relinquish control, give over utterly;\" also reflexively, \"surrender (oneself), yield (oneself) utterly\" (to religion, fornication, etc.), from Old French abandonner \"surrender, release; give freely, permit,\" also reflexive, \"devote (oneself)\" (12c.).The Old French word was formed from the adverbial phrase à bandon \"at will, at discretion,\" from à \"at, to\" (from Latin ad; seead-) + bandon \"power, jurisdiction,\" from Latin bannum, \"proclamation,\" which is from a Frankish or other Germanic word, from Proto-Germanic *bannan- \"proclaim, summon, outlaw\" (things all done by proclamation); seeban(v.).Meaning \"to leave, desert, forsake (someone or something) in need\" is from late 15c.  Related:Abandoned;abandoning.Etymologically, the word carries a sense of \"put (something) under someone else's control,\" and the earliest appearance of the word in English is as an adverb (mid-13c.) with the sense \"under (one's) control,\" hence also \"unrestricted.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abandoned",
    "response": "\"self-devoted\" to some practice or purpose (usually evil), late 14c., past-participle adjective fromabandon(v.) in the reflexive sense. Hence, in a general way, \"shamelessly wicked\" (1690s). Meaning \"deserted, forsaken\" is from late 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abandonment",
    "response": "1610s, \"action of relinquishing to another,\" from Frenchabandonnement(Old Frenchabandonement), fromabandonner\"to give up\" (seeabandon(v.)). Meaning \"a deserting, forsaking\" (of one's family, principles, etc.) is by 1788; from 1839 as \"condition of being forsaken.\" In law, the relinquishing of a title, privilege, or claim. In music, Italianabbandonatamenteis the instruction to play so as to make the time subordinate to the feeling."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abase",
    "response": "late 14c., \"reduce in rank, etc.,\" from Old Frenchabaissier\"diminish, make lower in value or status; lower oneself\" (12c.), literally \"bend, lean down,\" from Vulgar Latin*ad bassiare\"bring lower,\" fromad\"to, toward\" (seead-) + Late Latinbassus\"low, short\" (seebase(adj.)).The form in English was altered 16c. by influence ofbase(adj.), making the word an exception to the rule that Old French verbs with stem-iss-enter English as-ish(comprehension might have played a role; earlier forms ofabaseoften are identical with those ofabash). Literal sense of \"lower, depress\" (late 15c.) is archaic or obsolete. Related:Abased;abasing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abasement",
    "response": "early 15c., \"embarrassment, dread, fear,\" fromabase+-ment. Sense of \"action of lowering in price\" is mid-15c.; \"action of lowering in rank\" is 1560s; \"condition of being abased\" is from 1610s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abash",
    "response": "\"perplex or embarrass by suddenly exciting the conscience, discomfit, make ashamed,\" late 14c.,abaishen, earlier \"lose one's composure, be upset\" (early 14c.), from Old Frenchesbaiss-, present stem ofesbaer\"lose one's composure, be startled, be stunned.\"The first element ises\"out\" (from Latinex; seeex-). The second may beba(y)er\"to be open, gape\" (if the notion is \"gaping with astonishment\"), possibly ultimately imitative of opening the lips. Middle English Compendium also compares Old Frenchabaissier\"bow, diminish, lower oneself\" (source ofabase). Related:Abashed;abashing.Bashfulis a 16c. derivative."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abate",
    "response": "c. 1300,abaten, \"put an end to\" (transitive); early 14c., \"to grow less, diminish in power or influence\" (intransitive); from Old Frenchabatre\"beat down, cast down, strike down; fell, destroy; abolish; reduce, lower\" (Modern Frenchabattre), from Vulgar Latin*abbatere, from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +battuere\"to beat\" (seebatter(v.)). The French literal sense of \"to fell, slaughter\" is inabatisandabattoir. Related:Abated;abating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abatement",
    "response": "\"act or state of being decreased or mitigated\" in some way, mid-14c., from Old Frenchabatement\"overthrowing; reduction,\" fromabatre\"strike down; reduce\" (seeabate). Now mostly in the legal sense \"destruction or removal of a nuisance, etc.\" (1520s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abatis",
    "response": "\"barricade defense made of felled trees with the branches angled outward,\" 1766, from Frenchabatis, literally \"things thrown down,\" from Old Frenchabateiz\"a casting down; slaughter, carnage\" (12c.), fromabatre\"to beat down, throw down\" (seeabate)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abattoir",
    "response": "\"slaughterhouse for cows,\" 1820, from Frenchabattrein its literal sense \"to beat down, knock down, slaughter\" (seeabate) + suffix-oir, corresponding to Latin-orium, indicating \"place where\" (see-ory)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abaxile",
    "response": "\"not in the axis,\" 1847, from Latinab\"away from\" (seeab-) +axile\"of or belonging to an axis,\" fromaxis."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abba",
    "response": "Swedish pop music group formed 1972, the name dates from 1973 and is an acronym from the first names of the four band members: Anni-Frid Lyngstad, Björn Ulvaeus, Benny Andersson, Agnetha Fältskog."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abbess",
    "response": "c. 1300,abbese, \"female superior of a convent of nuns,\" from Old Frenchabbesse(12c.), from Late Latinabbatissa(6c.), fem. ofabbas(seeabbot). Replaced earlierabbotess, from Old Englishabbodesse."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abbey",
    "response": "mid-13c., \"monastery or convent devoted to religion and celibacy, headed by an abbot or abbess,\" from Anglo-Frenchabbeie, Old Frenchabaïe(Modern Frenchabbaye), from Late Latinabbatia, fromabbas(genitiveabbatis); seeabbot. At the dissolution of the monasteries, the name often was kept by abbey churches (as in Westminster Abbey) or estate houses that formerly were abbey residences."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abbot",
    "response": "Old Englishabbod\"abbot,\" from Latinabbatem(nominativeabbas), from Greekabbas, from Aramaic (Semitic)abba, title of honor, literally \"the father, my father,\" emphatic state ofabh\"father.\" Spelling with-tis a Middle English Latinization. Originally a title given to any monk, later limited to the head of a monastery. The use as a surname is perhaps ironic or a nickname. The Latin fem.abbatissais root ofabbess. Related:Abbacy;abbatial;abbotship."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abbreviate",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"to make shorter,\" from Latinabbreviatus, past participle ofabbreviare\"to shorten, make brief,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +breviare\"shorten,\" frombrevis\"short, low, little, shallow\" (from PIE root*mregh-u-\"short\").Specifically of words by 1580s. Also sometimes 15c.abbrevy, from Frenchabrevier(14c.), from Latinabbreviare. Related:Abbreviated;abbreviating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abbreviation",
    "response": "early 15c.,abbreviacioun, \"shortness; act of shortening; a shortened thing,\" from Old Frenchabréviation(15c.) and directly from Late Latinabbreviationem(nominativeabbreviatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofabbreviare\"shorten, make brief,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +breviare\"shorten,\" frombrevis\"short, low, little, shallow\" (from PIE root*mregh-u-\"short\").From 1580s specifically of words. Technically a part of a word, usually the initial letter or syllable, used for the whole word but with no indication of the rest of the word (asabbr.forabbreviationorabbreviate). Acontractionis made by elision of certain letters or syllables from the body of a word but still indicates its full form (asfwd.forforward;rec'd.forreceived)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abderian",
    "response": "by 1650s, \"of or pertaining toAbdera,\" in Thrace, whose citizens were proverbial as provincials who would laugh at anything or anyone they didn't understand (Abderian laughter), making their town the Hellenic equivalent ofGotham(q.v.). Especially (or alternatively) as it was the birthplace of Democritus the atomist, the \"Laughing Philosopher\" (born c. 460 B.C.E.) who observed human follies."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abdicate",
    "response": "1540s, \"to disown, disinherit (children),\" from Latinabdicatus, past participle ofabdicare\"to disown, disavow, reject\" (specificallyabdicare magistratu\"renounce office\"), literally \"proclaim as not belonging to one,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +dicare\"proclaim\" (from PIE root*deik-\"to show,\" also \"pronounce solemnly,\" and seediction). Meaning \"divest oneself of office, privilege, etc., before the term expires\" is recorded by 1610s in English (it was in classical Latin). Related:Abdicated;abdicating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abdication",
    "response": "1550s, \"a disowning,\" from Latinabdicationem(nominativeabdicatio) \"voluntary renunciation, abdication,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabdicare\"disown, disavow, reject,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +dicare\"proclaim\" (from PIE root*deik-\"to show,\" also \"pronounce solemnly,\" and seediction). Sense of \"resignation of inherent sovereignty\" is from 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abdomen",
    "response": "1540s, \"flesh or meat of the belly\" (a sense now obsolete), from Latinabdomen\"the belly,\" a word of unknown origin, Perhaps [OED, Watkins] fromabdere\"conceal\" (fromab\"off, away\" + PIE root*dhe-\"to set, put\"), with a sense of \"concealment of the viscera,\" or else \"what is concealed\" by proper dress. De Vaan, however, finds this derivation \"unfounded.\" Anatomical sense of \"part of the mammalian body between the diaphragm and the pelvis\" is from 1610s. Zoological sense of \"posterior division of the bodies of arthropods\" is by 1725."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abdominal",
    "response": "\"pertaining to the abdomen, ventral,\" 1550s, from medical Latinabdominalis, fromabdomen(genitiveabdominis); seeabdomen. As a noun, \"abdominal muscle,\" by 1961 (earlier \"abdominal vein,\" 1928);  earlier as a fish of the order including carp, salmon, and herring (1835), so called for their ventral fins. Related:Abdominally. English in 17c. hadabdominous\"big-bellied.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abduce",
    "response": "\"to draw away\" by persuasion or argument, 1530s, from Latinabductus, past participle ofabducere\"to lead away, take away,\" also in figurative senses, fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +ducere\"to lead\" (from PIE root*deuk-\"to lead\"). Related:Abduced;abducing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abducent",
    "response": "\"drawing away, pulling aside,\" 1713, from Latinabducentem(nominativeabducens), present participle ofabducere\"to lead away,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +ducere\"to lead\" (from PIE root*deuk-\"to lead\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abduct",
    "response": "\"to kidnap,\" 1834, probably a back-formation fromabduction; also compareabduce, the earlier verb, which has a more abstract sense. Related:Abducted;abducting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abduction",
    "response": "1620s, \"a leading away,\" from Latinabductionem(nominativeabductio) \"a forcible carrying off, ravishing, robbing,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabducere\"to lead away, take away, arrest\" (often by force), fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +ducere\"to lead\" (from PIE root*deuk-\"to lead\"). As \"criminal act of forcibly taking (someone)\" by 1768; before that the word also was a term in surgery and logic. In the Mercian hymns, Latinabductioneis glossed by Old Englishwiðlaednisse."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abductor",
    "response": "1610s, in physiology, a muscle that moves (a limb) away from the axis of the body, from Latinabductor, agent noun fromabducere\"to lead away,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +ducere\"to lead\" (from PIE root*deuk-\"to lead\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abeam",
    "response": "\"at right angles to the keel\" of a ship, hence in line with its beam, 1826, nautical, literally \"on beam;\" seea-(1) +beam(n.) in the nautical sense."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abecedary",
    "response": "\"primer, alphabet table,\" mid-15c., from Medieval Latinabecedarium\"an ABC book,\" neuter of adjectiveabecedarius, used as a noun, from the first four letters of the Latin alphabet.Abecedarian(adj.) is attested from 1660s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abed",
    "response": "\"in bed,\" c. 1200, contraction of Old Englishon bedde\"in bed,\" froma-(1) + dative ofbed(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abel",
    "response": "masc. proper name, in the Old Testament the second son of Adam and Eve, from HebrewHebhel, literally \"breath,\" also \"vanity;\" \"so called from his short life and sudden death\" [Thayer]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aberdeen",
    "response": "city in eastern Scotland, literally \"mouth of the (River) Don,\" which enters the North Sea there, from Gaelicaber\"(river) mouth,\" from Celtic*ad-ber-o-, from*ad-\"to\" (seead-) +*ber-\"to carry\" (from PIE root*bher-(1) \"to carry\"). CompareInverness. Related:Aberdonian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aberrant",
    "response": "\"wandering from the usual course,\" 1798, originally in natural history, \"differing somewhat from a group in which it is placed,\" from Latinaberrantem(nominativeaberrans), present participle ofaberrare\"to wander away, go astray,\" literally and figuratively, fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +errare\"to wander, stray, roam, rove\" (seeerr). Related:Aberrance;aberrancy(1660s). The verbaberrateis rare."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aberration",
    "response": "1590s, \"a wandering, act of straying,\" from Latinaberrationem(nominativeaberratio) \"a wandering,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaberrare\"to wander out of the way, lose the way, go astray,\" literally and figuratively, fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +errare\"to wander, stray, roam, rove\" (seeerr). Meaning \"deviation from the normal type\" is attested by 1735."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abet",
    "response": "late 14c., \"urge on, incite\" (implied inabetting), from Old Frenchabeter\"to bait, to harass with dogs,\" literally \"to cause to bite,\" froma-\"to\" (seead-) +beter\"to bait.\" This verb is probably from Frankish or some other Germanic source (perhaps Low Franconianbetan\"incite,\" or Old Norsebeita\"cause to bite\"); ultimately from Proto-Germanic*baitjan, from PIE root*bheid-\"to split,\" with derivatives in Germanic referring to biting. Sense of \"encourage by aid or approval\" is from 1779. Related:Abetted;abetting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abeyance",
    "response": "1520s, \"state of expectation,\" from Anglo-Frenchabeiance\"suspension,\" also \"expectation (especially in a lawsuit),\" from Old Frenchabeance\"aspiration, powerful desire,\" noun of condition fromabeer\"aspire after, gape, open wide,\" fromà\"at\" (seead-) +ba(y)er\"be open,\" from Latin*batare\"to yawn, gape\" (seeabash).Originally in French a legal term, \"condition of a person in expectation or hope of receiving property;\" it turned around in English law to mean \"condition of property temporarily without an owner\" (1650s). Hence \"state of suspended action or existence.\" The French verbbaeris also the source of Englishbay(n.2) \"recessed space,\" as inbay window."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abhor",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"to loathe, regard with repugnance, dislike intensely,\" literally \"to shrink back with horror or dread,\" from Latinabhorrere\"shrink back from, have an aversion for, shudder at,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +horrere\"tremble at, shudder,\" literally \"to bristle, be shaggy\" (from PIE*ghers-\"start out, stand out, rise to a point, bristle;\" seehorror).Formerly also \"fill (someone) with horror or loathing\" (16c.). In Latin it was less intense: \"be remote from, vary from, differ from, be out of harmony with.\" Related:Abhorred;abhorring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abhorrence",
    "response": "\"feeling of extreme aversion or detestation,\" 1650s; seeabhorrent+-ence. OED recommends this form for \"act or fact of abhorring,\"abhorrency(c. 1600) for \"quality of being abhorrent.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abhorrent",
    "response": "1610s, \"recoiling (from), strongly opposed to,\" from Latinabhorentem(nominativeabhorrens) \"incongruous, inappropriate,\" present participle ofabhorrere\"shrink back from, be remote from, be out of harmony with\" (seeabhor). Meaning \"repugnant, loathesome\" is from 1650s. Earlier wasabhorrable(late 15c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abidance",
    "response": "\"act of continuing or abiding,\" 1640s, fromabide+-ance."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abide",
    "response": "Middle Englishabiden, from Old Englishabidan,gebidan\"remain, wait, wait for, delay, remain behind,\" fromge-completive prefix (denoting onward motion; seea-(1)) +bidan\"bide, remain, wait, dwell\" (seebide).Originally intransitive (with genitive of the object:we abidon his\"we waited for him\"); the transitive senses of \"endure, sustain, stay firm under,\" also \"tolerate, bear, put up with\" (now usually with a negative) are from c. 1200. Toabide with\"stay with (someone); live with; remain in the service of\" is from c. 1300.Related:Abided;abiding. The historical conjugation wasabide,abode,abidden, but in Modern English the formation generally is weak."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abiding",
    "response": "late 14c., \"enduring, steadfast,\" present-participle adjective fromabide(v.). Related:Abidingly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abigail",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from HebrewAbhigayil, literally \"my father is rejoicing,\" fromabh\"father\" +gil\"to rejoice.\" In the Old Testament Abigail the Carmelitess was a wife of David. Used in general sense of \"lady's maid\" (1660s) from character of that name in Beaumont & Fletcher's \"The Scornful Lady.\" Her traditional male counterpart wasAndrew. The waiting maid association perhaps begins with I Samuel xxv, where David's wife often calls herself a \"handmaid.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abigail",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from HebrewAbhigayil, literally \"my father is rejoicing,\" fromabh\"father\" +gil\"to rejoice.\" In the Old Testament Abigail the Carmelitess was a wife of David. Used in general sense of \"lady's maid\" (1660s) from character of that name in Beaumont & Fletcher's \"The Scornful Lady.\" Her traditional male counterpart wasAndrew. The waiting maid association perhaps begins with I Samuel xxv, where David's wife often calls herself a \"handmaid.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ability",
    "response": "late 14c., \"state or condition of being able; capacity to do or act,\" from Old Frenchableté\"ability (to inherit),\" from Latinhabilitatem(nominativehabilitas, in Medieval Latinabilitas) \"aptitude, ability,\" noun of quality fromhabilis\"easy to manage, handy\" (seeable). One case where a Latin silent-h-failed to make a return in English (despite efforts of 16c.-17c. scholars); seeH. Also in Middle English, \"suitableness, fitness.\"Abilities\"one's talents or mental endowments\" is from 1580s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abiogenesis",
    "response": "\"spontaneous generation\" (of life, without parent organisms), 1870, coined in Modern Latin by T.H. Huxley, froma-(3) +biogenesis."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abiotic",
    "response": "\"without life,\" 1870, froma-(3) +biotic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abject",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"humble, lowly, poor; of low quality; menial,\" from Latinabiectus\"low, crouching; common, mean, contemptible; cast down, dispirited,\" past participle ofabicere\"to throw away, cast off; degrade, humble, lower,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +iacere\"to throw\" (past participleiactus; from PIE root*ye-\"to throw, impel\").The figurative sense of \"downcast, brought low, hopeless,\" is by 1510s. Also in Middle English \"cast off, rejected, expelled, outcast,\" a sense now obsolete.Abjectformerly also was a verb in English, \"to cast out, expel; to degrade, humiliate\" (15c.-17c.). As a noun, \"base or servile person,\" 1530s. Related:Abjectly;abjectness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abjection",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"humbleness, low state, meanness of spirit, abject situation, groveling humility,\" from Old Frenchabjection(14c.), from Latinabiectionem(nominativeabiectio) \"dejection, despondency,\" literally \"a throwing away, a casting off,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabicere\"to throw away, cast off; degrade, humble, lower,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +iacere\"to throw\" (past participleiactus; from PIE root*ye-\"to throw, impel\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abjuration",
    "response": "\"solemn renunciation,\" mid-15c., originally of heresy or idolatry, later of renunciations of oaths generally, from Latinabiurationem(nominativeabiuratio) \"a denying on oath,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabiurare\"deny on oath,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +iurare\"to swear,\" fromius(genitiveiuris) \"law\" (seejurist). Related:Abjuratory. Theoath of abjurationis \"the negative part of the oath of allegiance\" [Century Dictionary]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abjure",
    "response": "early 15c.,abjuren, \"renounce on oath, repudiate, forswear,\" originally especially \"renounce or recant (a heresy) on oath,\" from Old Frenchabjurerand directly from Latinabiurare\"deny on oath,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +iurare\"to swear,\" fromius(genitiveiuris) \"law\" (seejurist). Related:Abjured;abjuring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablactation",
    "response": "\"weaning of a child,\" 1650s, from Latinablactationem(nominativeablactatio) \"weaning,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofablactare\"to wean,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +lactare\"to suckle,\" fromlac(genitivelactis) \"milk\" (from PIE root*g(a)lag-\"milk\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablation",
    "response": "early 15c., \"a carrying or taking away,\" in medicine, \"mechanical removal of something harmful from the body,\" from Latinablationem(nominativeablatio), \"a taking away,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofauferre\"to carry away,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) + the irregular verbferre(past participlelatum; seeoblate(n.)) \"to bear, carry.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablative",
    "response": "\"grammatical case denoting removal or separation,\" late 14c. as an adjective; mid-15c. as a noun (short forablative case, originally in reference to Latin), from Old Frenchablatifand directly from Latin(casus) ablativus\"(case) of removal,\" expressing direction from a place or time, coined by Julius Caesar fromablatus\"taken away,\" past participle ofauferre\"to carry off or away, withdraw, remove,\" fromab\"off, away\" (seeab-) + the irregular verbferre(past participlelatum; seeoblate) \"to carry, to bear\" (from PIE root*bher-(1) \"to carry,\" also \"to bear children\"). The \"from\" case, the Latin case of adverbial relation, typically expressing removal or separation, also \"source or place of an action.\" Related:Ablatival."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablaut",
    "response": "\"systematic vowel alteration in the root of a word to indicate shades of meaning or tense,\" a characteristic of Indo-European languages, 1845, from GermanAblaut, literally \"off-sound\" (\"off\" here denoting substitution), coined by J.P. Zweigel in 1568 fromab\"off\" (from Old High Germanaba\"off, away from,\" from PIE root*apo-\"off, away\") +Laut\"sound, tone\" (from Old High Germanhlut, from Proto-Germanic*hludaz\"heard, loud,\" from suffixed form of PIE root*kleu-\"to hear\"). The word was popularized by Jakob Grimm and Franz Bopp. The process is what makes strong verbs in Germanic. An example isbind/band/bond/bound+ (German)Bund. Compareumlaut."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablaze",
    "response": "late 14c., \"on fire,\" froma\"on\" (seea-(1)) +blaze(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "able",
    "response": "\"having sufficient power or means,\" early 14c., from Old French(h)able\"capable; fitting, suitable; agile, nimble\" (14c.), from Latinhabilem,habilis\"easily handled, apt,\" verbal adjective fromhabere\"to hold\" (from PIE root*ghabh-\"to give or receive\").\"Easy to be held,\" hence \"fit for a purpose.\" The silenth-was dropped in English and resisted academic attempts to restore it 16c.-17c. (seeH), but some derivatives (such ashabiliment,habilitate) acquired it via French.Able seaman, one able to do any sort of work required on a ship, may be the origin of this:"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abloom",
    "response": "\"in blossom, in a blooming state,\" 1855, froma-(1) +bloom(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ablution",
    "response": "\"ritual washing,\" late 14c., from Latinablutionem(nominativeablutio) \"a washing, cleansing,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabluere\"to wash off, wash away, cleanse by washing,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +luere\"to wash\" (from PIE root*leue-\"to wash\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abnaki",
    "response": "seeAbenaki."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abnegate",
    "response": "\"deny (something) to oneself,\" 1650s, from Latinabnegatus, past participle ofabnegare\"to refuse, deny,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +negare\"to deny\" (from PIE root*ne-\"not\"). Related:Abnegated;abnegating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abnegation",
    "response": "late 14c., \"a negative assertion,\" c. 1500 as \"self-denial, renunciation,\" from Latinabnegationem(nominativeabnegatio) \"refusal, denial,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabnegare\"to refuse, deny,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +negare\"to deny\" (from PIE root*ne-\"not\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abner",
    "response": "masc. proper name, name of Saul's commander in the Old Testament, from HebrewAbhner, literally \"my father is light,\" fromabh\"father\" +ner\"light.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abnormal",
    "response": "\"not conformed or conforming to rule, deviating from a type or standard, contrary to system or law, irregular, unnatural,\" 1835, a refashioning ofanormal(q.v.) under influence of Latinabnormalis\"deviating from a fixed rule, irregular,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +norma\"rule\" (seenorm).The older form was from Frenchanormal(13c.), from Medieval Latinanormalus, an altered (by association withnorma) borrowing of Greekanomalos\"uneven, irregular,\" froman-\"not\" (seean-(1)) +homalos\"even,\" fromhomos\"same\" (from PIE root*sem-(1) \"one; as one, together with\"). Compareanomaly. \"Few words show such a series of pseudo-etymological perversions\" [Weekley]. Another adjective wasabnormous(1742) \"irregular, misshapen,\" from Latinabnormis. Related:Abnormally."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abnormality",
    "response": "1846, \"an instance of abnormality, irregularity, deformity;\" 1853 as \"fact or quality of being abnormal,\" fromabnormal(q.v.) +-ity. Earlier wasabnormity(1731), but according to OED the earlier word has more \"depreciatory force\" than the later one.Abnormalism\"tendency to be abnormal\" is from 1847. As a verb,abnormalize(1855) seem to be rare."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aboard",
    "response": "late 14c., \"at the side of a ship;\" mid-15c., \"onto or on a ship,\" probably in most cases from the Old French phraseà bord(compare Old Frenchaborder\"to board (a ship)\"), fromà\"on\" +bord\"board,\" from Frankish*bordor a similar Germanic source (seeboard(n.2)). The word for the \"boarding\" or sides of a vessel being extended to the ship itself. The usual Middle English expression waswithin borde. The callall aboard!as a warning to passengers (on ships or railway cars) is attested by 1829 (compare Frenchaller à bord\"go aboard\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abode",
    "response": "mid-13c., \"action of waiting,\" verbal noun fromabiden\"to abide\" (seeabide). It is formally identical with the old, strong past participle ofabide(Old Englishabad), but the modern conjugation is weak andabidedis used. The present-to-preterite vowel change is consistent with an Old English class I strong verb (ride/rode, etc.). The meaning \"habitual residence\" is attested by 1570s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aboil",
    "response": "\"boiling, on the boil,\" 1858, froma-+boil(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abolish",
    "response": "\"put an end to, do away with,\" mid-15c., from Old Frenchaboliss-, present-participle stem ofabolir\"to abolish\" (15c.), from Latinabolere\"destroy, efface, annihilate; cause to die out, retard the growth of,\" which is perhaps fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) + the second element ofadolere\"to grow, magnify\" (and formed as an opposite to that word), from PIE*ol-eye-, causative of root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish,\" and perhaps formed as an antonym toadolere.But the Latin word rather could be from a root in common with Greekolluein\"destroy, maker an end of.\" Tucker writes that there has been a confusion of forms in Latin, based on similar roots, one meaning \"to grow,\" the other \"to destroy.\" Now generally used of institutions, customs, etc.; application to persons and concrete objects has long been obsolete. Related:Abolished;abolishing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abolition",
    "response": "1520s, \"act of abolishing; state of being abolished,\" from Frenchabolitionor directly from Latinabolitionem(nominativeabolitio) \"an abolition, an annulling,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabolere\"destroy\" (seeabolish). Related:Abolitionary(\"destructive\");abolitional(\"pertaining to abolition\").Specific application to \"opposition to the trans-Atlantic African slave trade\" as a political question is first attested 1788. By 1823abolitionwas being used in regard to proposals or arguments to end American slavery itself, and after 1832 this was the usual sense of the word until the effort was accomplished by the 13th Amendment (1865). The alternative nounabolishment(1540s) seems not to have acquired a special use in reference to slavery issues."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abolitionism",
    "response": "\"belief in the principle of abolishing (something),\" 1790, in a purely anti-slavery sense (distinguished from opposition to the slave trade); fromabolition+-ism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abolitionist",
    "response": "person who favors doing away with some law, custom, or institution, 1792, originally in reference to the trans-Atlantic slave trade, fromabolition+-ist. By 1825 (in Britain) in reference to abolition of slavery as an institution. In Britain, applied 20c. to advocates of ending capital punishment. In a general sense,abolisherhas been used at least since 1742."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abominable",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"exciting disgust or loathing, morally detestable,\" from Old Frenchabominable(12c.) and directly from Late Latinabominabilis\"deserving abhorrence,\" from stem of Latinabominari\"deplore (as an evil omen),\" hence, generally, \"detest, execrate, deprecate,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +omin-, stem ofomen(seeomen).The more common Middle English form wasabhominable, which persisted into 17c.; it is a folk-etymology, as if from Latinab homine\"away from man\" (thus \"beastly\"). In early Modern English sometimes misdivided asa bominable. Related:Abominably;abominableness.Abominable snowman(1921) translates Tibetanmeetaoh kangmi."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abominate",
    "response": "\"abhor, loathe,\" 1640s, a back-formation fromabominationor else from Latinabominatus, past participle ofabominari\"shun as an ill omen.\" Related:Abominated;abominating. Middle English had noun, adjective, and adverb but seems to have lacked the verb. The Old French verb,abominer\"to loathe\" is said to have fallen out of use since 16c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abomination",
    "response": "early 14c.,abominacioun, \"abominable thing or action;\" late 14c., \"feeling of disgust, hatred, loathing,\" from Old Frenchabominacion\"abomination, horror, repugnance, disgust\" (13c.) and directly from Latinabominationem(nominativeabominatio) \"abomination,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabominari\"shun as an ill omen,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +omin-, stem ofomen(seeomen).In biblical use, often \"that which is ceremonially impure.\" The meaning was intensified by folk etymology derivation from Latinab homine\"away from man\" (thus \"beastly\"); Wycliffe and Chaucer both haveabhominacioun, andabhominablewas mocked by Shakespeare in \"Love's Labour's Lost.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aboriginal",
    "response": "1660s, \"first, earliest, existing from the beginning,\" especially in reference to inhabitants of lands colonized by Europeans, fromaborigines(seeaborigine) +-al(1). The specific Australian sense is attested from 1820. The noun meaning \"an original inhabitant, an autochthon\" is attested from 1760. Related:Aboriginally;aboriginality(1848);aboriginalism(1859)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aborigine",
    "response": "\"person, animal, or plant that has been in a country or region from earliest times,\" 1858, mistaken singular ofaborigines(1540s;aboriginalis considered the correct singular in English), from Latinaborigines\"the first inhabitants,\" especially of Latium, hence \"the first ancestors of the Romans;\" possibly a tribal name, or from or made to conform to the Latin phraseab origine, which means literally \"from the beginning.\"This is fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) + ablative oforigo\"a rise, commencement, beginning, source; descent, lineage, birth,\" from stem oforiri\"arise, rise; be born, be descended, receive life\" (seeorigin). Extended 1789 to natives of other countries which Europeans have colonized, especially \"aboriginal inhabitant of Australia.\" Australian slang shorteningAboattested from 1922 (n.), 1906 (adj.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abort",
    "response": "1570s, \"to miscarry in giving birth,\" from Latinabortus, past participle ofaboriri\"to miscarry, be aborted, fail, disappear, pass away,\" a compound word used in Latin for deaths, miscarriages, sunsets, etc., which according to OED is fromab, here as \"amiss\" (seeab-), + stem oforiri\"appear, be born, arise,\" from PIE*heri-\"to rise\" (seeorigin). [Watkins, contra de Vaan, etc., derives the second element from a suffixed form of PIE root*er-(1) \"move, set in motion.\"]The English word is attested from 1610s as \"to deliberately terminate\" anything (intransitive), but especially a pregnancy in a human or animal. Intransitive use in aeronautics and space-flight is by 1946. Transitive meaning \"to cause (a woman) to miscarry\" is recorded by 1916; with the fetus or pregnancy as the object of the action, by 1966. Related:Aborted;aborting. The Latin verb for \"produce an abortion\" wasabigo, literally \"to drive away.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abortifacient",
    "response": "1853, noun (\"that which causes miscarriage\") and adjective (\"producing abortion\"), from Latinabortus(seeabort) +facientem\"making,\" related tofacere\"to make, do\" (from PIE root*dhe-\"to set, put\"). An earlier noun for this wasabortive(1640s), also a special use of an adjective."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abortion",
    "response": "1540s, \"the expulsion of the fetus before it is viable,\" originally of deliberate as well as unintended miscarriages; from Latinabortionem(nominativeabortio) \"miscarriage; abortion, procuring of an untimely birth,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaboriri\"to miscarry, be aborted, fail, disappear, pass away,\" a compound word used in Latin for deaths, miscarriages, sunsets, etc., which according to OED is fromab, here as \"amiss\" (seeab-), + stem oforiri\"appear, be born, arise\" (seeorigin).Meaning \"product of an untimely birth\" is from 1630s; earlier in this sense wasabortive(early 14c.). Another earlier noun in English for \"miscarriage\" wasabort(early 15c.). In the Middle English translation of Guy de Chauliac's \"Grande Chirurgie\" (early 15c.) Latinaborsumis used for \"stillbirth, forced abortion.\"Abortmentis attested from c. 1600;aborsementfrom 1530s, both archaic.Aborticide(1875) is illogical. Comparemiscarriage.In 19c. some effort was made to distinguishabortion\"expulsion of the fetus between 6 weeks and 6 months\" frommiscarriage(the same within 6 weeks of conception) andpremature labor(delivery after 6 months but before due time). The deliberate miscarriage wascriminal abortion. This broke down late 19c. asabortioncame to be used principally for intentional miscarriages, probably via phrases such asprocure an abortion.Foeticide(n.) appears 1823 as a forensic medical term for deliberate premature fatal expulsion of the fetus; also compareprolicide. Another 19c. medical term for it wasembryoctony, with second element from a Latinized form of Greekkteinein\"to destroy.\"Abortionwas a taboo word for much of early 20c., disguised in print ascriminal operation(U.S.) orillegal operation(U.K.), and replaced bymiscarriagein film versions of novels.Abortium\"hospital specializing in abortions,\" is from 1934, in a Soviet Union context."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abortionist",
    "response": "\"one who produces an abortion,\" 1848, fromabortion+-ist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abortive",
    "response": "late 14c., \"born prematurely or dead,\" from Latinabortivus\"prematurely born; pertaining to miscarriage; causing abortion,\" fromabort-, past-participle stem ofaboriri\"disappear, miscarry, fail\" (seeabort). From 14c.-18c. stillborn children or domestic animals were said to beabortive. Transferred meaning \"not brought to completion or successful issue\" is from 1590s. Also seeabortion. Related:Abortiveness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abound",
    "response": "\"be in great plenty,\" early 14c., from Old Frenchabonder\"to abound, be abundant, come together in great numbers\" (12c.), from Latinabundare\"overflow, run over,\" from Latinab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +undare\"rise in a wave,\" fromunda\"a wave\" (from PIE*unda-, nasalized form of root*wed-(1) \"water; wet\"). Related:Abounded;abounding;abounder\"one who has plenty or is wealthy\" (1755).English seems to always have used in the-ou-spelling, though in Middle English an unetymologicalh-sometimes was added. The vowel in Old Frenchabonder,abondanceis a continuation of a Merovingian Latin scribal use of-o-for classical Latin-u-to attempt to identify a sound that had evolved since classical times. In French eventually this sound came to be represented by-ou-. Compare Frenchtour\"tower,\" from Old Frenchtor, from Latinturris;court(n.), from Old Frenchcort, from Latincurtus; Frenchoutrefrom Latinultra, etc. However-o-remained before a nasal (asnombrefromnumerus,mondefrommundum, etc.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abounding",
    "response": "1630s, \"affluent,\" present-participle adjective fromabound. Literal sense of \"overflowing\" is recorded by 1680s. Related:Aboundingly. Compareabundant."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "about",
    "response": "Middle Englishaboute, from Old Englishabutan(adv., prep.), earlieronbutan\"on the outside of; around the circumference of, enveloping; in the vicinity of, near; hither and thither, from place to place,\" also \"with a rotating or spinning motion,\" in late Old English \"near in time, number, degree, etc., approximately;\" a compound or contraction ofon(seeon; also seea-(1)) +be\"by\" (seeby) +utan\"outside,\" fromut(seeout(adv.)).By c. 1300 it had developed senses of \"around, in a circular course, round and round; on every side, so as to surround; in every direction;\" also \"engaged in\" (Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?), and gradually it forced out Old Englishymbe,ymbutan(from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") in the sense \"round about, in the neighborhood of.\"From mid-13c. as \"in the matter, in connection with.\" From early 14c. as \"in partial rotation, so as to face in a different direction.\" From late 14c. as \"near at hand, about one's person.\" \"In a circuitous course,\" hence \"on the move\" (late 13c.), and in Middle English \"be about to do, be busy in preparation for,\" hence its use as a future participle in(to be) about to\"in readiness, intending.\"Abouts(late 14c.), with adverbial genitive, still found inhereabouts, etc., probably is a northern dialectal form.Tobring about\"cause or affect\" and tocome about\"happen\" are from late 14c.About faceas a military command (short forright about face) is first attested 1861, American English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "above",
    "response": "Middle Englishabove,aboven(alsoabounin northern dialects,abowin southwestern dialects), from Old Englishabufan(adv., prep.), earlieronbufan\"above, in or to a higher place, on the upper side; directly over, in or to a higher place than,\" a contraction or compound ofon(also seea-(1)) +bufan\"over.\"The second element is itself a compound ofbe\"by\" (seeby) +ufan\"over/high\" (from Proto-Germanic*ufan-, source also of Old Saxon, Old High Germanoban, Germanoben; from PIE root*upo\"under,\" also \"up from under,\" hence also \"over\").From c. 1200 as \"of higher rank or position, superior in authority or power; of higher rank than, superior to.\" This sense in Middle English perhaps was reinforced by a literal use ofabovein the sense \"higher at the table than,\" thus \"in a place of greater honor than, taking precedence over\" (mid-14c.) From mid-14c. as \"in addition to;\" also \"superior to, out of reach of, not condescending to.\" From late 14c. as \"more\" (in number, linear measurement, weight, value); \"older; better than, more desirable than, superior to.\"Phraseabove all\"before other considerations\" is from late 14c. To beabove (someone's) headin the figurative sense \"out of range of his or her intellect\" is from 1914 (abovein the sense \"not to be grasped or understood by\" is from mid-14c.). In Middle English to beabove erthewas \"above ground, unburied,\" hence \"living, among the living.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aboveboard",
    "response": "\"in open sight, without trickery or disguise,\" 1610s, fromaboveandboard(n.1). \"A figurative expression borrowed from gamesters, who, when they put their hands under the table, are changing their cards.\" [Johnson]"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abracadabra",
    "response": "magical formula, 1690s, from Latin (Q. Serenus Sammonicus, 2c.), from Late GreekAbraxas, cabalistic or gnostic name for the supreme god, and thus a word of power. It was written out in a triangle shape and worn around the neck to ward off sickness, etc. Another magical word, from a mid-15c. writing, wasananizapta."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrade",
    "response": "\"\"to rub or wear away; rub or scrape off,\" 1670s, from Latinabradere\"to scrape off, shave away,\" fromab\"off\" (seeab-) +radere\"to scrape\" (seeraze(v.)).Abrase, from the stem of the Latin verb, is attested from 1590s. Related:Abraded;abrading."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Abraham",
    "response": "masc. proper name, name of the first of the Patriarchs in the Old Testament, from HebrewAbraham\"father of a multitude,\" fromabh\"father\" +*raham(cognate with Arabicruham\"multitude\"); the name he altered fromAbram\"high father,\" from second elementram\"high, exalted.\" Related:Abrahamic;Abrahamite.Abraham-manwas an old term for mendicant lunatics, or, more commonly, frauds who wandered England shamming madness so as to collect alms (1560s). According to the old explanation of the name (from at least 1640s), they originally were from Bethlehem Hospital, where in early times there was anAbrahamward or room for such persons, but the ward might have been named for the beggars."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrasion",
    "response": "1650s, \"act of abrading,\" from Medieval Latinabrasionem(nominativeabrasio) \"a scraping,\" noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinabradere\"to scrape away, shave off,\" fromab\"off\" (seeab-) +radere\"to scrape\" (seeraze(v.)). From 1740 as \"result of abrasion.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrasive",
    "response": "\"an abrasive substance,\" 1850, fromabrasive(adj.).Abradantin this sense is from 1868."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abraxas",
    "response": "Cabalistic word associated with the followers of Basilides the Gnostic, by 1680s, of uncertain origin and with many elaborate explanations. Also used in reference to a type of Gnostic amulet featuring a carved gem depicting a monstrous figure and obscure words or words connected to Hebrew or Egyptian religion (1725)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abreast",
    "response": "mid-15c., a contraction ofon brest\"side-by-side,\" froma-(1) +breast(n.); the notion is of \"with breasts in line.\" Tokeep abreastin figurative sense of \"stay up-to-date\" is from 1650s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abridge",
    "response": "c. 1300,abreggen, \"make shorter, shorten, condense,\" from Old Frenchabregier,abrigier\"abridge, diminish, shorten\" (12c., Modern Frenchabréger), from Late Latinabbreviare\"make short,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +breviare\"shorten,\" frombrevis\"short, low, little, shallow\" (from PIE root*mregh-u-\"short\").Abbreviateis the same word directly from Latin. The sound development that turned Latin-vi-to French-dg-is paralleled inassuage(fromassuavidare) anddeluge(fromdiluvium). Of writing, \"shorten by omission,\" late 14c. Related:Abridged;abridging."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abroad",
    "response": "mid-13c., \"widely apart,\" a contraction ofon brode, from Old Englishon brede, \"in width,\" literally \"at wide\" (seea-(1) +broad(adj.)). From c. 1300 as \"at a distance from each other,\" hence \"out of doors, away from home\" (late 14c.) also \"at a distance generally\" (early 15c.), and the main modern sense, \"out of one's country, overseas\" (mid-15c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrogate",
    "response": "\"abolish by authoritative act, repeal,\" 1520s, from Latinabrogatus, past participle ofabrogare\"to annul, repeal (a law),\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +rogare\"propose (a law), ask, request,\" apparently a figurative use of a PIE verb meaning literally \"to stretch out (the hand),\" from root*reg-\"move in a straight line.\" Formabrogen, from Old Frenchabroger, is recorded from early 15c. Related:Abrogated;abrogating;abrogative."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrogation",
    "response": "\"annulling of (a law) by legislative action,\" 1530s, from Latinabrogationem(nominativeabrogatio) \"a repeal (of a law),\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabrogare\"annul, repeal,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +rogare\"propose (a law), ask, request,\" apparently a figurative use of a PIE verb meaning literally \"to stretch out (the hand),\" from root*reg-\"move in a straight line.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abrupt",
    "response": "1580s, \"sudden, unceremonious, without notice,\" a figurative use from Latinabruptus\"broken off,\" also \"precipitous, steep\" (as a cliff), also \"disconnected,\" past participle ofabrumpere\"break off,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +rumpere\"to break,\" from a nasalized form of the PIE root*runp-\"to snatch\" (seecorrupt(adj.)). The literal sense \"broken off or appearing as if broken off\" is from c. 1600 in English. Of writing, \"having sudden transitions, lacking continuity,\" 1630s. Related:Abruptly;abruptness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abruption",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"a sudden breaking off,\" from Latinabruptionem(nominativeabruptio) \"a breaking off,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabrumpere\"break off,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +rumpere\"to break,\" from a nasalized form of the PIE root*runp-\"to break\" (seecorrupt(adj.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Absalom",
    "response": "masc. proper name, King David's son in the Old Testament, often used figuratively for \"favorite son,\" from HebrewAbhshalom, literally \"father of peace,\" fromabh\"father\" +shalom\"peace.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscess",
    "response": "in pathology, \"collection of pus in some part of the body,\" 1610s, from Latinabscessus\"an abscess\" (the Latin word was used in a medical sense by Celsus), literally \"a going away, departure,\" from the stem ofabscedere\"withdraw, depart, retire,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +cedere\"to go, withdraw\" (from PIE root*ked-\"to go, yield\"). The notion is that humors \"go from\" the body through the pus in the swelling."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscessed",
    "response": "1846, in pathology, adjective fromabscess(n.). If there is a verbabscessit would be a back-formation from this."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscind",
    "response": "\"to cut off,\" 1650s, from Latinabscindere\"to cut off, divide, part, separate\" (seeabscissa). Related:Abscinded;abscinding."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscise",
    "response": "\"to cut off or away,\" 1610s, from Latinabscisus, past participle ofabscidere\"to cut away,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +caedere\"to cut, cut down\" (from PIE root*kae-id-\"to strike\"). Related:Abscised;abscising."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscissa",
    "response": "1798 in Latin form, earlier Englished asabscisse(1690s), from Latinabscissa, short forabscissa (linea)\"(a line) cut off,\" or(recta ex diametro) abscissa\"(a line) cut off (from the diameter),\" fem. ofabscissus\"cut off,\" past participle ofabscindere\"to cut off, divide, part, separate,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +scindere\"to cut, rend, tear asunder, split; split up, part, divide, separate\" (from PIE*skind-, from root*skei-\"to cut, split\"). The Latin word translates Greekapolambanomene."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscission",
    "response": "\"removal or cutting away,\" early 15c., from Latinabscissionem(nominativeabscissio) \"a cutting off, a breaking off, interruption,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabscindere\"to cut off, divide, part, separate\" (seeabscissa)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abscond",
    "response": "\"depart suddenly and secretly,\" especially to escape debt or the law, 1560s, from Frenchabscondre\"to hide\" and directly from Latinabscondere\"to hide, conceal, put out of sight,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +condere\"put together, store,\" from assimilated form ofcom-\"together\" (seecom-) +-dere\"put\" (from PIE root*dhe-\"to put, place\"). Related:Absconded;absconder;absconding."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absence",
    "response": "\"state of not being present,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchabsence\"absence\" (14c.), from Latinabsentia, abstract noun fromabsentem(nominativeabsens), present participle ofabesse\"be away from, be absent,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +esse\"to be\" (from PIE root*es-\"to be\").Absence makes the heart grow fonderis a line from the song \"Isle of Beauty\" by English poet and composer Thomas Haynes Bayly (1797-1839)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absent",
    "response": "\"not present, not in a certain place\" (of persons), \"non-existent\" (of things), late 14c., from Old Frenchabsent,ausent\"absent\" and directly from Latinabsentem(nominativeabsens), present participle ofabesse\"be away from, be absent,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +esse\"to be\" (from PIE root*es-\"to be\"). Related:Absently;absentness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absentee",
    "response": "\"one who is absent,\" 1530s, fromabsent(v.) +-ee. In reference to voting, by 1892, American English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absenteeism",
    "response": "\"practice or habit of being absent,\" 1822, fromabsentee+-ism; originally in reference to landlords, especially in Ireland, who lived at a distance from their estates (the earlier word wasabsenteeship(1778) and Johnson's dictionary hasabsenteein the landlord sense). In reference to pupils or workers from 1922."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absinthe",
    "response": "alsoabsinth(though properly that means \"wormwood\"), \"bitter, pale-green alcoholic liqueur distilled from wine mixed with wormwood\" (Artemisia Absinthium), 1842, from Frenchabsinthe, \"essence of wormwood\" (short forextrait d'absinthe) from Latinabsinthum\"wormwood,\" from Greekapsinthion, which is perhaps from Persian (compare Persianaspand, of the same meaning). The wormwood plant itself is figurative of \"bitter\" sorrow; it was known asabsinthin English from c. 1500; Old English used the word in the Latin form. The drink itself attained popularity from its heavy use by French soldiers in Algiers. Related:Absinthal;absinthic;absinthism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolute",
    "response": "late 14c., \"unrestricted, free from limitation; complete, perfect, free from imperfection;\" also \"not relative to something else\" (mid-15c.), from Latinabsolutus, past participle ofabsolvere\"to set free, acquit; complete, bring to an end; make separate,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +solvere\"to loosen, untie, release, detach,\" from PIE*se-lu-, from reflexive pronoun*s(w)e-(seeidiom) + root*leu-\"to loosen, divide, cut apart.\"Sense evolution probably was from \"detached, disengaged\" to \"perfect, pure.\" Meaning \"despotic\" (1610s) is from notion of \"absolute in position;\"absolute monarchyis recorded from 1735 (absolute kingis recorded from 1610s). Grammatical sense is from late 14c.Absolute magnitude(1902) is the brightness a star would have at a distance of 10 parsecs (or 32.6 light years); scientificabsolute valueis from 1907. As a noun in metaphysics,the absolute\"that which is unconditional or free from restriction; the non-relative\" is from 1809."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolutely",
    "response": "late 14c., \"unconditionally, completely,\" fromabsolute(adj.) +-ly(2). From mid-15c. as \"without reference to anything else, not relatively;\" the meaning \"to the utmost degree\" emerged by mid-16c. As a colloquial emphatic, by 1867, American English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absoluteness",
    "response": "1560s, \"perfection,\" a sense now obsolete, fromabsolute(adj.) +-ness. Meaning \"unlimited rule\" is from 1610s; that of \"unconditional quality\" is from 1650s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolution",
    "response": "\"remission, forgiveness,\" c. 1200, from Old Frenchabsolucion, earlierassolucion, from Latinabsolutionem(nominativeabsolutio) \"completion, acquittal,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabsolvere\"set free, loosen, acquit,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +solvere\"to loosen, dissolve; untie, release; dismiss,\" from PIE*se-lu-, from reflexive pronoun*s(w)e-(seeidiom) + root*leu-\"to loosen, divide, cut apart.\" Originally of sins; in general use from c. 1400."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolutism",
    "response": "1753 in theology, of God's actions; 1830 in political science, \"system of government where the power of the sovereign is unrestricted,\" in which sense it seems to have been introduced by British reformer and parliamentarian Maj. Gen. Thomas Perronet Thompson. Seeabsoluteand-ism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolutist",
    "response": "1830 in political science, \"advocate of despotism\" (Thompson), fromabsolute+-iston model of Frenchabsolutiste(by 1820). From 1835 as an adjective. Compareabsolutism. Used in a different sense in metaphysics by the followers of Fichte, Schelling and Hegel."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absolve",
    "response": "early 15c., \"release\" (from an oath or obligation), from Latinabsolvere\"set free,\" especially judicially, \"acquit\" (source also of Old Frenchassoldre(11c.), Modern Frenchabsoudre), fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +solvere\"to loosen, untie, release, remove,\" from PIE*se-lu-, from reflexive pronoun*s(w)e-(seeidiom) + root*leu-\"to loosen, divide, cut apart.\" In modern use, \"set free from consequences or penalties of actions.\" Related:Absolved;absolving."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorb",
    "response": "\"to drink in, suck up, take in by absorption,\" early 15c., from Old Frenchabsorbir,assorbir(13c., Modern Frenchabsorber), from Latinabsorbere\"to swallow up, devour,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +sorbere\"suck in,\" from PIE root*srebh-\"to suck, absorb\" (source also of Armenianarbi\"I drank,\" Greekrhopheo\"to sup greedily up, gulp down,\" Lithuaniansrebiu, srėbti\"to drink greedily\"). Figurative meaning \"to completely grip (one's) attention\" is from 1763."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorbed",
    "response": "\"engrossed mentally,\" 1760, past-participle adjective in a figurative sense fromabsorb(v.). Related:Absorbedly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorbency",
    "response": "\"quality of absorbing,\" 1781, fromabsorbent+ abstract noun suffix-cy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorbent",
    "response": "\"absorbing or capable of absorbing,\" 1718, from Latinabsorbentem(nominativeabsorbens) \"a drinking,\" present participle ofabsorbere\"swallow up\" (seeabsorb). Also from 1718 as a noun, \"anything which absorbs.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorbing",
    "response": "1670s, \"soaking up, swallowing,\" present-participle adjective in a figurative sense fromabsorb(v.). Originally in medicine. Figurative sense of \"engrossing\" is by 1826. Related:Absorbingly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absorption",
    "response": "1590s, \"a swallowing up\" (now obsolete), from Latinabsorptionem(nominativeabsorptio) \"a swallowing,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofabsorbere\"swallow up\" (seeabsorb). From 1714 specifically of \"disappearance by assimilation into something else.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absquatulate",
    "response": "\"run away, make off,\" 1840, earlierabsquotilate(1837), \"Facetious U.S. coinage\" [Weekley], perhaps based on a mock-Latin negation ofsquat(v.) \"to settle.\" Said to have been used on the London stage in in the lines of rough, bragging, comical American character \"Nimrod Wildfire\" in the play \"The Kentuckian\" as re-written by British author William B. Bernard, perhaps it was in James K. Paulding's American original, \"The Lion of the West.\" Civil War slang establishedskedaddlein its place. Related:Absquatulated;absquatulating;absquatulation."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstain",
    "response": "late 14c., \"avoid (something); refrain (oneself) from; keep free from sin or vice; live austerely, practice abstinence or asceticism; be sexually continent,\" from Old Frenchabstiner,abstenir(14c.), earlierastenir(13c.) \"hold (oneself) back, refrain voluntarily, abstain (from what satisfies the passions), practice abstinence,\" from Latinabstinere\"withhold, keep back, keep off,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +tenere\"to hold\" (from PIE root*ten-\"to stretch\"). Specifically of liquor from late 14c. Meaning \"refrain from voting\" is from 1796. Related:Abstained;abstaining."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstainer",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"one who practices self-denial,\" agent noun fromabstain. Modern use in the temperance movement and specifically with reference to alcoholic drink is from 1862. French usedabstèmein this sense, from Latinabstemius."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstemious",
    "response": "\"sparing or moderate in eating or drinking,\" c. 1600, from Latinabstemius\"sober, temperate, abstaining from wine,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) + stem oftemetum\"strong drink,\" which is related totemulentus\"drunken.\" Etymologically it refers only to abstaining from alcoholic drink, but it was extended in Latin to temperance in living generally. Related:Abstemiously;abstemiousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstention",
    "response": "1520s, \"a holding off, refusal to do something,\" from Frenchabstention(Old Frenchastencion), from Late Latinabstentionem(nominativeabstentio) \"the act of retaining,\" noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinabstinere/abstenere\"withhold, keep back, keep off,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +tenere\"to hold\" (from PIE root*ten-\"to stretch\"). As \"a refraining from voting\" by 1859."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstinence",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"forbearance in indulgence of the appetites,\" from Old Frenchabstinance(earlierastenance), from Latinabstinentia\"abstinence, starvation; self-restraint, integrity,\" abstract noun fromabstinentem(nominativeabstinens), present participle ofabstinere/abstenere\"withhold, keep back, keep off,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +tenere\"to hold\" (from PIE root*ten-\"to stretch\"). Especially of sexual appetites but also in Middle English of food, fighting, luxury."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstinent",
    "response": "late 14c., \"refraining from undue indulgence,\" especially in reference to food and drink, from Old Frenchabstinent(earlierastenant) \"moderate, abstemious, modest,\" from Latinabstinentem(nominativeabstinens) \"temperate, moderate,\" present participle ofabstinere,abstenere\"withhold, keep back, keep off,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +tenere\"to hold\" (from PIE root*ten-\"to stretch\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstract",
    "response": "late 14c., originally in grammar (in reference to nouns that do not name concrete things), from Latinabstractus\"drawn away,\" past participle ofabstrahere\"to drag away, detach, pull away, divert,\" also used figuratively; from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +trahere\"to draw\" (from PIE root*tragh-\"to draw, drag, move;\" seetract(n.1)).The meaning in philosophy, \"withdrawn or separated from material objects or practical matters\" (opposed toconcrete) is from mid-15c. That of \"difficult to understand, abstruse\" is from c. 1400.In the fine arts, \"characterized by lack of representational qualities\" by 1914; it had been a term at least since 1847 for music without accompanying lyrics.Abstract expressionismas an American-based uninhibited approach to art exemplified by Jackson Pollock is from 1952, but the term itself had been used in the 1920s of Kandinsky and others."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstracted",
    "response": "\"absent in mind, distracted from present reality by intellectual activity,\" 1640s, past-participle adjective fromabstract(v.). Related:Abstractedly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstraction",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"a withdrawal from worldly affairs, asceticism,\" from Old Frenchabstraction(14c.), from Late Latinabstractionem(nominativeabstractio), noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinabstrahere\"to drag away, detach, pull away, divert;\" also figuratively, from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +trahere\"to draw\" (from PIE root*tragh-\"to draw, drag, move;\" seetract(n.1)). Meaning \"idea of something that has no actual existence\" is from 1640s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstractly",
    "response": "late 14c., \"by itself, absolutely, unconnected with anything else,\" fromabstract(adj.) +-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abstruse",
    "response": "1590s, \"remote from comprehension,\" from Frenchabstrus(16c.) or directly from Latinabstrusus\"hidden, concealed, secret,\" past participle ofabstrudere\"conceal, hide,\" literally \"to thrust away,\" from assimilated form ofab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +trudere\"to thrust, push\" (from PIE root*treud-\"to press, push, squeeze;\" seethreat). Related:Abstrusely;abstruseness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absurd",
    "response": "\"plainly illogical,\" 1550s, from Frenchabsurde(16c.), from Latinabsurdus\"out of tune, discordant;\" figuratively \"incongruous, foolish, silly, senseless,\" fromab-\"off, away from,\" here perhaps an intensive prefix, +surdus\"dull, deaf, mute,\" which is possibly from an imitative PIE root meaning \"to buzz, whisper\" (seesusurration). Thus the basic sense is perhaps \"out of tune,\" but de Vaan writes, \"Since 'deaf' often has two semantic sides, viz. 'who cannot hear' and 'who is not heard,'ab-surduscan be explained as 'which is unheard of' ...\" The modern English sense is the Latin figurative one, perhaps \"out of harmony with reason or propriety.\" Related:Absurdly;absurdness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "absurdity",
    "response": "late 15c.,absurdite, \"that which is absurd,\" from Late Latinabsurditatem(nominativeabsurditas) \"dissonance, incongruity,\" noun of state from Latinabsurdus\"out of tune;\" figuratively \"incongruous, silly, senseless\" (seeabsurd)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abundance",
    "response": "\"copious quantity or supply,\" mid-14c., from Old Frenchabondanceand directly from Latinabundantia\"fullness, plenty,\" abstract noun fromabundant-, stem ofabundans\"overflowing, full,\" present participle ofabundare\"to overflow\" (seeabound)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abundant",
    "response": "\"present in great quantity, plentiful,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchabundantand directly from Latinabundantem(nominativeabundans) \"overflowing, full; rich, abounding,\" present participle ofabundare\"to overflow, flow in profusion, have in excess\" (seeabound). Related:Abundantly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abuse",
    "response": "early 15c., \"to misuse, misapply\" (power, money, etc.), from Old Frenchabuser\"deceive, abuse, misuse\" (14c.), from Vulgar Latin*abusare, from Latinabusus\"an abusing; a using up,\" past participle ofabuti\"use up, consume,\" also \"to misuse, abuse, misapply, outrage,\" fromab\"off, away from\" (seeab-) +uti\"use\" (seeuse).Also in reference to forbidden sexual situations from early 15c., but originally meaning incest, masturbation (self-abuse), homosexuality, prostitution, etc. From 1550s specifically as \"to misuse sexually, ravish,\" but OED 2nd ed. marks this obsolete and the modern use \"subject (someone) to unwanted sexual activity\" is likely a fresh coinage from late 20c. Specifically of drugs, from 1968. Meaning \"attack with harsh language, revile\" is from c. 1600. Related:Abused;abusing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abuser",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"one who uses (something) improperly,\" agent noun fromabuse(v.). From c. 1600 as \"a ravisher;\" 1836 as \"one who abuses in speech or words.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abusive",
    "response": "1530s (implied inabusively) \"improper,\" from Frenchabusif, from Latinabusivus\"misapplied, improper,\" fromabus-, past-participle stem ofabuti\"misuse,\" literally \"use up\" (seeabuse(v.)). Meaning \"full of abuse\" is from 1580s. Shakespeare hasabusious(\"Taming of the Shrew,\" 1594).Abuseful\"abounding in reproaches\" was in use 17c.-19c. Related:Abusively; abusiveness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abut",
    "response": "mid-13c., \"to end at, to border on, touch at the end,\" from Old Frenchaboter,abuter\"join end to end, touch with an end\" (13c.), andabouter\"join end to end,\" fromà\"to\" (seead-) +boter,bouter\"to strike, push,\" from a Germanic source (ultimately from PIE root*bhau-\"to strike\"). Comparebutt(v.). Related:Abutted;abutting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abutment",
    "response": "1640s, \"that which borders on something else, the part abutting on or against,\" fromabut(v.) +-ment. Originally any junction; the architectural usage, \"solid structure where one arch of a bridge, etc., meets another\" is attested from 1793 (the notion is of the meeting-place of the arches)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abuzz",
    "response": "\"filled with buzzing sound,\" by 1838, froma-(1) +buzz(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abysm",
    "response": "\"bottomless gulf, greatest depths,\" c. 1300, from Old Frenchabisme\"chasm, abyss, depths of ocean, Hell\" (12c., Modern Frenchabîme), from Vulgar Latin*abyssimus(source also of Spanish and Portugueseabismo), which represents perhaps a superlative of Latinabyssusor a formation on analogy of Greek-derived words in-ismus; seeabyss. It survived only as a poetic variant ofabyss; as late as early 17c. it was pronounced to rhyme withtime."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abysmal",
    "response": "1650s, \"pertaining to an abyss,\" formed in English fromabysm+-al(1). Perhaps only a dictionary word before 19c. The weakened sense of \"extremely bad\" is attested by 1904, perhaps fromabysmal ignorance(suggestive of its \"depth\"), an expression attested from 1847. Related:Abysmally."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abyss",
    "response": "late 14c. in Latin formabyssus, \"depths of the earth or sea; primordial chaos;\" early 14c. asabime\"depths of the earth or sea; bottomless pit, Hell\" (via Old French; seeabysm). Both are from Late Latinabyssus\"bottomless pit,\" from Greekabyssos (limnē)\"bottomless (pool),\" fromabyssos\"bottomless, unfathomed,\" hence, generally, \"enormous, unfathomable,\" also as a noun,he abyssos\"the great depth, the underworld, the bottomless pit.\" This is a compound ofa-\"without\" (seea-(3)) +byssos\"bottom,\" a word of uncertain origin possibly related tobathos\"depth\" [Liddell & Scott]. Watkins suggests a connection with the root ofbottom(n.); Beekes suggests it is pre-Greek.The current form in English is a 16c. partial re-Latinization. Greekabyssoswas used in Septuagint to translate Hebrewtehom\"original chaos\" and was used in the New Testament for \"Hell.\" OED notes, \"the word has had five variants,abime,abysm,abysmus,abyssus,abyss; of whichabyssremains as the ordinary form, andabysmas archaic or poetic.\" In reference to a seemingly bottomless gulf from 1630s. Old English glossed Latinabyssumwithdeagenesse, which is related todeagol\"secret, hidden; dark, obscure.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "abyssal",
    "response": "1690s, \"unfathomable, unsearchably deep, like an abyss,\" fromabyss+-al(1). Since 19c. mainly \"inhabiting or belonging to the depths of the ocean\" (used especially of the zone of ocean water below 300 fathoms), though in 19c.abysmalwas more common in oceanography."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Acacia",
    "response": "1540s, type of shrub or tree fund in warm climates of Africa and Australia, from Latinacacia, from Greekakakia\"thorny Egyptian tree,\" a word of uncertain origin. Perhaps it is related to Greekakē\"point, thorn\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\"), or perhaps it is a Hellenization of some Egyptian word. Beekes suggests it is probably a word from a pre-Greek Mediterranean language and finds \"no reason for an Oriental origin.\" Greekkaktosalso has been compared. From late 14c. in English as the name of a type of gum used as an astringent, etc. Extended 17c. to North American trees."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "academe",
    "response": "\"The Academy,\" as a place where arts and sciences were taught, 1580s, from phrasegroves of Academe(translating Horace'ssilvas Academi), the name of the public gymnasium and gardens near Athens where Plato taught, from Greekhe Akadēmeia(seeacademy).Latinacademiaalso was used in reference to Plato's doctrines.Academein a modern, general sense of \"the world of universities and scholarship\" is attested in English from 1849. (academiain the sense of \"academic community\" is from 1956.)"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Academic",
    "response": "1580s, \"relating to an academy,\" also \"collegiate, scholarly,\" from Latinacademicus\"of the (classical Athenian) Academy,\" fromAcademia, name of the place where Plato taught (seeacademy).It is attested by 1610s in English in the sense \"belonging to the classical Academy in Athens.\" The meaning \"theoretical, not practical, not leading to a decision\" (such as university debates or classroom legal exercises) is by 1886. In the arts, \"rigidly conforming to academic style,\" 1889.Academic freedom\"liberty of a teacher to state opinions openly without fear of retribution,\" is attested from 1901. Related:Academical;academically;academicalism(1874); Johnson hasacademial.As a noun, \"student in college or university life,\" 1580s (Latinacademicus, Greekakadēmikoimeant \"Academic philosopher\"). Alsoacademian(1590s);academician(1746) mostly was confined to members of the old societies for the promotion of sciences and arts."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "academic",
    "response": "1580s, \"relating to an academy,\" also \"collegiate, scholarly,\" from Latinacademicus\"of the (classical Athenian) Academy,\" fromAcademia, name of the place where Plato taught (seeacademy).It is attested by 1610s in English in the sense \"belonging to the classical Academy in Athens.\" The meaning \"theoretical, not practical, not leading to a decision\" (such as university debates or classroom legal exercises) is by 1886. In the arts, \"rigidly conforming to academic style,\" 1889.Academic freedom\"liberty of a teacher to state opinions openly without fear of retribution,\" is attested from 1901. Related:Academical;academically;academicalism(1874); Johnson hasacademial.As a noun, \"student in college or university life,\" 1580s (Latinacademicus, Greekakadēmikoimeant \"Academic philosopher\"). Alsoacademian(1590s);academician(1746) mostly was confined to members of the old societies for the promotion of sciences and arts."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "academy",
    "response": "mid-15c.,Achademie, \"the classical Academy,\" properly the name of the public garden where Plato taught his school, from Old French (Modern FrenchAcadémie) and directly from LatinAcademia, from GreekAkadēmeia\"The Academy; the grove ofAkadēmos,\" a legendary Athenian of the Trojan War tales (his name, Latinized asAcademus, apparently means \"of a silent district\"), who was original estate-holder of the site.Comparelyceum. By 1540s the word in English was being used for any school or training place for arts and sciences or higher learning. \"In the 18th century it was frequently adopted by schools run by dissenters, and the name is often found attached to the public schools in Scotland and Northern Ireland\" [Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1941]; hence, in the U.S., a school ranking between an elementary school and a university. \"In England the word has been abused, and is now in discredit in this sense\" [OED]. By 1560s it was used for \"a place of training\" in any sense (riding schools, army colleges).The word also was used of associations of adepts for the cultivation and promotion of some science or art, whether founded by governments, royalty, or private individuals. HenceAcademy award(1939), so called for their distributor, the U.S.-basedAcademy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences(founded 1927)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Acadian",
    "response": "\"native or inhabitant of the French colony of Acadia\" in what is now the Canadian Maritimes, 1705, fromAcadia, Latinized form ofAcadie, French name of Nova Scotia, probably fromArchadia, the name given to the region by Verrazano in 1520s, from GreekArkadia, then emblematic in pastoral poetry of a place of rural peace (seeArcadian); the name may have been suggested to Europeans by the native Micmac (Algonquian) wordakadie\"fertile land.\" The Acadians, expelled by the English in 1755, settled in large numbers in Louisiana, and were known there asAcadiansby 1803 (seeCajun, which is a corruption ofAcadian)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acajou",
    "response": "\"cashew,\" the full form of the word, from Frenchacajou, from older Portugueseacajúfrom Tupi (Brazil)acajuba, name of the tree that produces the nut."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acanthocephalous",
    "response": "in zoology, \"having a spiny head,\" 1847, fromacantho-(seeacanthus) + Latinized adjectival form of Greekkephalē\"head\" (seecephalo-) +-ous."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acanthus",
    "response": "type of tall herb or shrub native to the Mediterranean regions, 1660s, from Latinacanthus, name of the plant, from Greekakanthos, fromakē\"point, thorn\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +anthos\"flower\" (seeanther). So called for its large spiny leaves. A conventionalized form of the leaf is used in Corinthian capitals. Related:Acanthaceous."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acapulco",
    "response": "in full,Acapulco de Juarez, resort town in western Mexico, from Nahuatl (Aztecan)acapulco\"place of the large canes,\" fromaca(tl)\"cane (plant)\" +-pul\"large\" +-co\"place.\"Acapulco goldas the name of a local grade of potent marijuana is attested from 1965."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acatholic",
    "response": "\"non-Catholic,\" 1809, froma-(3) +Catholic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accede",
    "response": "\"come to or arrive at\" (a state, position, office, etc.), early 15c., from Latinaccedere\"approach, go to, come near, enter upon,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +cedere\"go, move, withdraw\" (from PIE root*ked-\"to go, yield\"). Latinad-usually becameac-before \"k\" sounds. Related:Acceded;acceding."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accelerando",
    "response": "musical instruction indicating a passage to be played with gradually increasing speed, 1842, from Italianaccelerando, present participle ofaccelerare, from Latinaccelerare\"to hasten, quicken\" (seeaccelerate)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accelerant",
    "response": "\"that which hastens,\" especially combustion, 1854, from Latinaccelerantem(nominativeaccelerans), present participle ofaccelerare\"to hasten, quicken\" (seeaccelerate). As an adjective from 1890."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accelerate",
    "response": "1520s, \"hasten the occurrence of;\" 1590s, \"make quicker\" (implied inaccelerating), from Latinacceleratus, past participle ofaccelerare\"to hasten, quicken\" (trans.), \"make haste\" (intrans.), fromad\"to\" (seead-) +celerare\"hasten,\" fromceler\"swift,\" which is perhaps from PIE*keli-\"speeding\" (seecelerity). The intransitive sense of \"go faster, become faster\" in English is from 1640s. Related:Accelerated;accelerative."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acceleration",
    "response": "\"act or condition of going faster,\" 1530s, from Latinaccelerationem(nominativeacceleratio) \"a hastening,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccelerare\"to hasten, quicken,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +celerare\"hasten,\" fromceler\"swift,\" which is perhaps from PIE*keli-\"speeding\" (seecelerity)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accelerator",
    "response": "1610s, \"a hastener,\" from Latinaccelerator, agent noun fromaccelerare\"to hasten; make haste\" (seeaccelerate). Motor vehicle sense of \"pedal which operates the throttle and thus modulates engine speed\" is from 1900; particle physics sense is from 1931."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accent",
    "response": "late 14c., \"particular mode of pronunciation,\" from Old Frenchacent\"accent\" (13c.), from Latinaccentus\"song added to speech,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +cantus\"a singing,\" past participle ofcanere\"to sing\" (from PIE root*kan-\"to sing\").The Latin word was a loan-translation of Greekprosōidia, frompros-\"to\" +ōidē\"song,\" which apparently described the pitch scheme in Greek verse.The meaning \"effort in utterance making one syllable stronger than another in pitch or stress\" is attested from 1580s; as \"mark or character used in writing to indicate accent,\" it is recorded by 1590s. The decorative-arts sense of \"something that emphasizes or highlights\" is from 1972."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accentual",
    "response": "\"pertaining to accent,\" c. 1600, from Latinaccentus(seeaccent(n.)) +-al(1). Related:Accentually;accentuality."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accentuate",
    "response": "1731, \"pronounce with an accent,\" from Medieval Latinaccentuatus,past participle ofaccentuare\"to accent,\" from Latinaccentus\"song added to speech,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +cantus\"a singing,\" past participle ofcanere\"to sing\" (from PIE root*kan-\"to sing\"). Figurative meaning \"emphasize, place an accent or emphasis on\" is recorded from 1865.Related:Accentuated;accentuating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accentuation",
    "response": "1690s, from Medieval Latinaccentuationem(nominativeaccentuatio) \"intoning, chanting,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccentuare\"to accent,\" from Latinaccentus\"song added to speech,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +cantus\"a singing,\" past participle ofcanere\"to sing\" (from PIE root*kan-\"to sing\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accept",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to take what is offered; admit and agree to (a proposal, etc.),\" from Old Frenchaccepter(14c.) or directly from Latinacceptare\"take or receive willingly,\" frequentative ofaccipere\"receive, get without effort,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +capere\"to take\" (from PIE root*kap-\"to grasp\"). Related:Accepted;accepting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acceptability",
    "response": "1660s, from Late Latinacceptabilitas, from Latinacceptabilis\"worthy of acceptance,\" fromacceptare\"take or receive willingly\" (seeaccept).Acceptableness(1610s) is older."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acceptable",
    "response": "late 14c., from Old Frenchacceptable\"pleasant, agreeable,\" from Latinacceptabilis\"worthy of acceptance,\" fromacceptare\"take or receive willingly\" (seeaccept). Related:Acceptably."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acceptance",
    "response": "1570s, from Frenchacceptance, fromaccepter(seeaccept). The earlier word wasacception(late 14c.,accepcioun), from Latinacceptionem; it was common until c. 1700.Acceptationis from early 15c. as \"action of taking or receiving what is offered,\" 1590s as \"state of being accepted.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "access",
    "response": "early 14c., \"an attack of fever,\" from Old Frenchacces\"onslaught, attack; onset (of an illness),\" from Latinaccessus\"a coming to, an approach; way of approach, entrance,\" noun use of past participle ofaccedere\"to approach,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +cedere\"go, move, withdraw\" (from PIE root*ked-\"to go, yield\"). The English sense of \"an entrance\" (c. 1600) is directly from Latin. The meaning \"habit or power of getting into the presence of (someone or something)\" is from late 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accessibility",
    "response": "1758, from Frenchaccessibilité(from Late Latinaccessibilitas), or else a native formation fromaccessible+-ity."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accessible",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"affording access, capable of being approached or reached,\" from Old Frenchaccessibleand directly from Late Latinaccessibilis, verbal adjective from Latinaccessus\"a coming near, an approach; an entrance,\" fromaccedere\"approach, go to, come near, enter upon\" (seeaccede). The meaning \"easy to reach\" is from 1640s; of art or writing, \"able to be readily understood,\" by 1961 (a word not needed before writing or art often deliberately was made not so). Related:Accessibility."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accession",
    "response": "1580s, \"that which is added,\" also \"act of acceding\" (by assent, to an agreement, etc.), from Latinaccessionem(nominativeaccessio) \"a going to, approach; a joining; increase, enlargement,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccedere\"approach, enter upon\" (seeaccede). From 1640s as \"act of coming to a position or into possession,\" especially in reference to a throne. Related:Accessional."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accessory",
    "response": "alsoaccessary, early 15c., \"that which is subordinate to something else,\" also as a legal term, \"one aiding in a felony without committing the offense\" (as by advising, inciting, concealing), from Late Latinaccessorius, from Latinaccessor, agent noun ofaccedere\"to approach\" (seeaccede).Especially in the visual arts, \"object introduced to balance composition or enhance artistic effect\" (1540s). Attested from 1896 as \"woman's smaller articles of dress;\" henceaccessorize. Related:Accessorial."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accidence",
    "response": "late 14c., in philosophy, \"non-essential or incidental characteristic,\" also \"part of grammar dealing with inflection\" (mid-15c.), in some cases a misspelling ofaccidents, or else directly from Latinaccidentia(used as a term in grammar by Quintilian), neuter plural ofaccidens, present participle ofaccidere\"to happen, fall out; fall upon\" (seeaccident). The grammar sense is because they are qualities which change in accordance with use (as gender, number, tense, case) but are not essential to the primary signification."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accident",
    "response": "late 14c., \"an occurrence, incident, event; what comes by chance,\" from Old Frenchaccident(12c.), from Latinaccidentem(nominativeaccidens) \"an occurrence; chance; misfortune,\" noun use of present participle ofaccidere\"happen, fall out, fall upon,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) + combining form ofcadere\"to fall\" (from PIE root*kad-\"to fall\").The sense has had a tendency since Latin to extend from \"something that happens, an event\" to \"a mishap, an undesirable event.\" Latinsi quid cui accidat, \"if anything should happen to one,\" was a euphemism for \"if one should die.\" In Middle English the word is met usually in theology (in reference to the material qualities in the sacramental bread and wine), medicine (\"something out of the ordinary, disease, injury\"), or philosophy (\"non-essential characteristic of a thing\").From late 15c. as \"the operations of chance.\" Meaning \"an unplanned child\" is attested by 1932.Accident-proneis from 1926."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accidental",
    "response": "late 14c., \"non-essential,\" from Old Frenchaccidentelor directly from Medieval Latinaccidentalis, from Latinaccidentem\"an accident, chance\" (seeaccident). Meaning \"outside the normal course of nature\" is from early 15c.; that of \"coming by chance, unintentional\" is from 1570s.Accidential(1811) sometimes serves now in the sense \"characterized by non-essential qualities\" and goes withaccidence."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accidentally",
    "response": "late 14c., \"non-essentially,\" also \"unnaturally,\" fromaccidental(adj.) +-ly(2). Meaning \"unintentionally\" is recorded from 1580s; phraseaccidentally on purposeis recorded from 1799."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Accipiter",
    "response": "raptorial bird, 1708, from Latinaccipiter, a generic name for birds of prey, especially the common hawk. According to de Vaan, \"generally assumed\" to be from a Proto-Italic*aku-petri-\"having pointed (that is, 'swift') wings\" (seeacro-+ptero-) and compares Greekokypteros\"with swift wings,\" Sanskritasu-patvan-\"flying swiftly,\" \"all of which are used as epithets to birds of prey.\" Under this theory the initialacc-is by influence of the verbaccipere\"to take\" (whence also Latinacceptor\"falcon;\" seeaccept). Or the sense could be literal, \"with pointed wings.\" The proper plural would beaccipitres. Related:Accipitral;accipitrine(1809)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclaim",
    "response": "early 14c., \"to lay claim to,\" from Latinacclamare\"to cry out at\" (in Medieval Latin \"to claim\"), fromad\"to, toward\" (seead-) +clamare\"cry out\" (from PIE root*kele-(2) \"to shout\"). The meaning \"to applaud\" is recorded by 1630s. The spelling has been conformed toclaim. Related:Acclaimed;acclaiming;acclamatory."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclamation",
    "response": "1540s, \"act of shouting or applauding in approval,\" from Latinacclamationem(nominativeacclamatio) \"a calling, exclamation, shout of approval,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofacclamare\"to call to, cry out at, shout approval or disapproval of,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to, toward\" (seead-) +clamare\"cry out\" (from PIE root*kele-(2) \"to shout\"). As a method of spontaneous approval of resolutions, etc., by unanimous voice vote, by 1801, probably from the French Revolution."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclimate",
    "response": "1792, \"habituate (something) to a new climate,\" from Frenchacclimater, verb formed fromà\"to\" (seead-) +climat(seeclimate). Intransitive sense \"adapt to a new climate\" is from 1861. Related:Acclimated;acclimating. The extended formacclimatizeis now more common in the older sense of this word (generally in reference to plants or animals), leaving to this word the intransitive sense, which more often refers to humans."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclimation",
    "response": "1826, noun of action fromacclimate, \"by form-assoc. with words likenarrate,narration, in which-ateis a vbl. ending: inacclimateit is part of the stem\" [OED]. The word is attested earlier in German and French. Coleridge hasacclimatement(1823), which also is found earlier in French."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclimatization",
    "response": "\"modification of a living thing to allow it to endure in a foreign climate,\" 1830, noun of action fromacclimate. There is or was a tendency to use this word in reference to animals and plants andacclimationof humans."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclimatize",
    "response": "1824, \"modify a living thing to suit a foreign climate\" (transitive); seeacclimate+-ize. A more recent formation thanacclimateand generally replacing it in this sense. Related:Acclimatized;acclimatizing. Simpleclimatizeis attested from 1826 as \"inure (a living thing) to a climate.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclinal",
    "response": "in geology, \"leaning against,\" as one stratum of rock against another, both turned up at an angle, 1837, from Latinacclinis\"leaning on or against,\" related toacclinare\"to lean on or against,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to, upon\" (seead-) +clinare\"to bend\" (from PIE*klein-, suffixed form of root*klei-\"to lean\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acclivity",
    "response": "\"upward slope of ground,\" 1610s, from Latinacclivitatem(nominativeacclivitas) \"an ascending direction, rising grade, upward steepness,\" fromacclivis\"mounting upwards, ascending,\" fromad\"to, up to\" (seead-) +clivus\"hill, a slope\" (from PIE*klei-wo-, suffixed form of root*klei-\"to lean\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accolade",
    "response": "1620s, \"an embrace about the neck then the tapping of a sword on the shoulders to confer knighthood,\" from Frenchaccolade\"an embrace, a kiss\" (16c.), from Provençalacoladaor Italianaccollata, ultimately from noun use of a fem. past participle of Vulgar Latin*accollare\"to embrace around the neck,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +collum\"neck\" (comparecollar(n.)), from PIE root*kwel-(1) \"revolve, move round.\" Also see-ade.The extended meaning \"praise, award\" is by 1851. The earlier form of the word in English wasaccoll(mid-14c.), from Old Frenchacolee\"an embrace, kiss, especially that given to a new-made knight,\" a noun use of the past participle of the verbacoler. The French noun in the 16c. was altered toaccolade, with the foreign suffix, and English followed suit."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accommodate",
    "response": "1530s, \"fit one thing to another,\" from Latinaccomodatus\"suitable, fit, appropriate to,\" past participle ofaccomodare\"make fit, make fit for, adapt, fit one thing to another,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +commodare\"make fit,\" fromcommodus\"\"proper, fit, appropriate, convenient, satisfactory,\" fromcom-, here as an intensive prefix (seecom-), +modus\"measure, manner\" (from PIE root*med-\"take appropriate measures\").From late 16c. as \"make suitable,\" also \"furnish (someone) with what is wanted,\" especially \"furnish with suitable room and comfort\" (1712). Related:Accommodated;accommodating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accommodating",
    "response": "\"obliging, disposed to yield to the desires of others,\" 1771, present-participle adjective fromaccommodate. Related:Accomodatingly.Accomodableis from c. 1600 as \"suitable.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accommodation",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"that which supplies a want or need,\" from Frenchaccommodation, from Latinaccommodationem(nominativeaccommodatio) \"an adjustment,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccommodare\"make fit; make fit for\" (seeaccommodate).Meaning \"appliance, anything which affords aid\" is from 1610s; that of \"act of accommodating\" is from 1640s. Meaning \"arrangement of a dispute\" is from 1640s. Anaccommodation train(1838) was one making all stops (as opposed to anexpresss); it was used earlier of stages (1811)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accompaniment",
    "response": "\"something that attends another as a circumstance,\" 1731 as a term in heraldry, from Frenchaccompagnement(13c.), fromaccompagner(seeaccompany). In music, \"the subordinate part or parts added to a solo or concerted composition,\" by 1744."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accompanist",
    "response": "\"performer who takes the accompanying part in music,\" 1779, fromaccompany+-ist. Fowler prefersaccompanyist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accompany",
    "response": "early 15c., \"to be in company with,\" from Old Frenchacompaignier\"take as a companion\" (12c., Modern Frenchaccompagner), fromà\"to\" (seead-) +compaignier, fromcompaign(seecompanion). The musical meaning \"play or sing along with\" is by 1570s. Related:Accompanied;accompanying."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accomplice",
    "response": "\"associate in crime,\" 1580s, an unetymological extension of earliercomplice\"an associate or confederate\" (early 15c.), from Old Frenchcomplice\"a confederate, partner\" (not in a criminal sense), from Late Latincomplicem(nominativecomplex) \"partner, confederate,\" from Latincomplicare\"to involve,\" literally \"fold together,\" fromcom\"with, together\" (seecom-) +plicare\"to fold, weave\" (from PIE root*plek-\"to plait\"). Altered perhaps on model ofaccomplish, etc., or by assimilation of the indefinite article ina complice."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accomplish",
    "response": "late 14c., \"fulfill, perform, carry out an undertaking,\" from Old Frenchacompliss-, present-participle stem ofacomplir\"to fulfill, fill up, complete\" (12c., Modern Frenchaccomplir), from Vulgar Latin*accomplere, from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +complere\"to fill up,\" transferred to \"fulfill, finish (a task),\" fromcom-, here probably as an intensive prefix (seecom-), +plere\"to fill\" (from PIE root*pele-(1) \"to fill\"). Related:Accomplished;accomplishing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accomplishable",
    "response": "\"capable of being accomplished,\" 1792 (Tom Paine), fromaccomplish+-able. Related:Accomplishability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accomplished",
    "response": "late 14c., \"completed, finished,\" past-participle adjective fromaccomplish(v.). From late 15c. as \"perfect in acquirements as a result of training,\" fromaccomplishin an archaic sense \"make complete by providing education in what is wanting,\" especially mental accomplishments and social graces."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accomplishment",
    "response": "early 15c., \"performance of a task; state of completion,\" from Old Frenchacomplissement\"completion, action of accomplishing,\" fromacomplir\"to fulfill, carry out, complete\" (seeaccomplish). Meaning \"thing completed\" and that of \"something that completes\" someone and fits him or her for cultivated or fashionable society are from c. 1600."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accord",
    "response": "early 12c., \"come into agreement,\" also \"agree, be in harmony,\" from Old Frenchacorder\"agree, be in harmony\" (12c.), from Vulgar Latin*accordare\"make agree,\" literally \"be of one heart, bring heart to heart,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +cor(genitivecordis) \"heart\" (used figuratively for \"soul, mind\"), from PIE root*kerd-\"heart.\" Compareconcord,discord. Related:Accorded;according."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accordance",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"compliance;\" early 14c., \"agreement, concurrence, state of being in accord,\" from Old Frenchacordance\"agreeing, reconciliation, harmony,\" noun of action fromacorder\"reconcile, agree, be in harmony\" (seeaccord(v.)).Of things, \"conformity, compatibility, harmony,\" late 14c. The meaning \"formal adjustment of a difference, peace treaty\" is from late 13c. Phrasein accordance withis attested by 1793 (in Middle English,in accordance ofwas the usual form)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accordant",
    "response": "\"corresponding, conformable,\" early 14c., from Old Frenchacordant\"agreeing with,\" from Medieval Latinaccordantem(nominativeaccordans), present participle ofaccordare\"agree,\" from Vulgar Latin (seeaccord(v.)). Related:Accordantly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "according",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"matching, similar, corresponding\" (a sense now obsolete), present-participle adjective and adverb fromaccord(v.). Meanings \"conforming (to), compliant, in agreement; consistent, harmonious; suitable, appropriate\" are from late 14c.According to\"referring to,\" literally \"in a manner agreeing with\" is from late 14c. As an adverb, \"often applied to persons, but referring elliptically to their statements or opinions\" [Century Dictionary]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accordingly",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"in agreement with\" (now obsolete), fromaccording+-ly(2). From mid-15c. as \"properly, adequately;\" meaning \"agreeably with logic or expectation\" is from 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accordion",
    "response": "\"small, keyed, bellows-like wind instrument,\" 1830, from GermanAkkordion, fromAkkord\"musical chord, concord of sounds,\" from a verb similar to Old Frenchacorder\"agree, be in harmony,\" from Vulgar Latin*accordare(compare Italianaccordare\"to attune a musical instrument;\" seeaccord(v.)), with suffix on analogy ofclarion, etc. Invented 1829 by piano-maker Cyrill Demian of Vienna. The type with a keyboard instead of buttons is apiano accordion. Related:Accordionist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accost",
    "response": "1570s, \"come side-by-side or face-to-face with,\" for any reason, from Frenchaccoster\"move up to, come alongside\" (Old Frenchacoster), from Late Latinaccostare\"come up to the side,\" from assimilated form of Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +costa\"a rib, side\" (seecoast(n.)). Now usually in the sense \"approach and speak to\" (1610s). Also picked up as the verb for a prostitute's solicitation of a customer (1812). Related:Accosted;accosting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accouchement",
    "response": "\"parturition, delivery in childbed,\" 1803, from Frenchaccouchement, noun of action fromaccoucher\"go to childbed\" (seeaccoucheur). The verbaccouche(1867) is a back-formation, or else from Frenchaccoucher."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accoucheur",
    "response": "1759, \"midwife\" (properly, \"man-midwife,\" but in English used without regard to gender), \"medical practitioner who attends women in childbirth,\" from Frenchaccoucheur(Jules Clément, later 17c.), agent noun fromaccoucher\"to go to childbed, be delivered,\" from Old Frenchacouchier\"deliver\" (transitive), \"be delivered, give birth\" (intransitive), originally simply \"to lie down\" in one's bed, \"go to bed\" (12c.), froma-\"to\" (from Latinad; seead-) + Old Frenchculcher\"to lie,\" from Latincollocare, fromcom-\"with\" (seecom-) +locare\"to place,\" fromlocus\"a place\" (seelocus). The fem. form,accoucheuse, is attested in English from 1842."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "account",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"counting,\" especially \"reckoning of money received and paid, detailed statement of funds owed or spent or property held,\" from Old Frenchacont\"(financial) account, reckoning, terminal payment,\" froma\"to\" (seead-) +cont\"counting, reckoning of money to be paid,\" from Late Latincomputus\"a calculation,\" from Latincomputare\"to count, sum up, reckon together,\" fromcom\"with, together\" (seecom-) +putare\"to reckon\" (originally \"to prune,\" from PIE root*pau-(2) \"to cut, strike, stamp\").From the first it was often in plural form; sometimes in late Middle English it wasaccompt(seeaccount(v.)). The meaning \"course of business dealings requiring records\" is from 1640s; hence \"arrangement to keep money in a business, bank, etc.\" (1833), also \"customer or client having an account\" (1937).Money of account(1690s), that used in reckoning but not circulating as coin or paper, preserves the \"counting\" sense of the word.From the notion of \"rendering an account\" comes the sense \"statement answering for conduct\" (mid-14c.) and the general sense \"narration, recital of facts,\" attested by 1610s. From the notion of \"statement of reasons\" comeson no account\"under no circumstances\" (1704). Also from c. 1300 in reference to answering for one's conduct, especially at the Last Judgment. The meaning \"estimation, consideration,\" especially in the eyes of others, is from late 14c.On accountin the financial sense \"as an item to be accounted for at the final settlement\" is from 1610s, henceon account ofin the general sense \"for the sake of, in regard to, in consideration of\" (1640s, originallyupon account of). Alsoon (my, your, etc.) account\"on (one's) behalf.\" Togive accounts\"prepare or present a statement of funds and property\" is from mid-15c; the older term wascast accounts(mid-14c.); totake account oforiginally was to make an inventory;take into account\"take account of\" is from 1680s. The phraseby all accountsis attested from 1798."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accountability",
    "response": "\"state of being answerable,\" 1770, fromaccountable+-ity. Earlier wasaccountableness(1660s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accountable",
    "response": "\"answerable,\" literally \"liable to be called to account,\" c. 1400 (mid-14c. in Anglo-French), from Old Frenchacontable; seeaccount(v.) +-able. Related:Accountably."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accountancy",
    "response": "\"the art of the accountant,\" 1848, fromaccountant+ abstract noun suffix-cy.Accountantshipis attested by 1818."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accountant",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"accounting officer, one who renders accounts,\" from Old Frenchacontant(Modern Frenchaccomptant), from present participle ofaconter\"to count, enumerate\" (seeaccount(v.)). The sense of \"professional maker of accounts\" is recorded from 1530s. The word also was an adjective in Middle English, \"accountable; liable to render accounts\" (early 15c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accounting",
    "response": "\"reckoning of numbers,\" late 14c., verbal noun fromaccount(v.). From 1855 as \"management of financial affairs.\" Phraseno accounting for tastes(1823) translates Latinde gustibus non est disputandum, fromaccount(v.) in the \"give an explanation\" sense."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accouter",
    "response": "alsoaccoutre, \"to dress or equip\" (especially in military clothing and gear), 1590s, from Frenchacoutrer, earlieracostrer(13c.) \"arrange, dispose, put on (clothing),\" probably originally \"sew up,\" from Vulgar Latin*accosturare\"to sew together, sew up,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +*consutura\"a sewing together,\" from Latinconsutus, past participle ofconsuere\"to sew together,\" fromcon-(seecom-) +suere\"to sew\" (from PIE root*syu-\"to bind, sew\"). The English spelling reflects the 16c. French pronunciation. Related:Accoutered;accoutred;accoutering;accoutring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accredit",
    "response": "1610s, \"vouch for, bring into credit,\" from Frenchaccréditer, earlieracrediter, fromà\"to\" (seead-) +créditer\"to credit\" (someone with a sum), fromcrédit\"credit\" (seecredit(n.)). Falsely Latinized in French. The word was rare in English in the original sense but became common in the meaning \"confer credit or authority on\" (1794). Related:Accredited;accrediting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accreditation",
    "response": "\"act of accrediting; state of being accredited,\" 1806, noun of action fromaccredit."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accredited",
    "response": "\"furnished with credentials,\" 1630s, past-participle adjective fromaccredit(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accretion",
    "response": "1610s, \"act of growing by organic enlargement;\" 1650s as \"that which is formed by continued growth from without,\" from Latinaccretionem(nominativeaccretio) \"an increasing, a growing larger\" (as of the waxing moon), noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccrescere\"grow progressively, increase, become greater,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +crescere\"grow\" (from PIE root*ker-(2) \"to grow\"). It goes with the verbaccrue. Related:Accretional;accretionary."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accrual",
    "response": "\"act or process of accruing,\" 1782, fromaccrue+-al(2). Compareaccretion. Another older noun wasaccruement(c. 1600)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accrue",
    "response": "formerly alsoaccrew, mid-15c.,acreuen, in reference to property, etc., \"to fall to someone as an addition or increment,\" from Old Frenchacreue\"growth, increase, what has grown,\" fem. ofacreu, past participle ofacreistre(Modern Frenchaccroître) \"to increase,\" from Latinaccrescere\"grow progressively, increase, become greater,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +crescere\"grow\" (from PIE root*ker-(2) \"to grow\"). Related:Accrued;accruing.Apparently an English verb from a French noun because there is no English noun to go with it until much later (the earliest seems to be now-obsoleteaccrue, 1570s), unless the record is defective. From late 15c. as \"happen or result as a natural growth;\" from 1881 as \"gain by increment, accumulate.\" Alternative verbaccrete\"grow by adhesion\" (1784) is rare, as isaccresce(1630s), from Latinaccrescere."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acculturate",
    "response": "\"adopt and assimilate an alien culture,\" 1925 (implied inacculturated), a back-formation fromacculturation(q.v.).Acculturizewas used from 1895. Related:Acculturating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acculturation",
    "response": "\"the adoption and assimilation of an alien culture\" [OED], 1880, from assimilated form ofad-\"to\" +culture(n.) + noun ending-ation."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accumulate",
    "response": "1520s, \"to heap up\" (transitive), from Latinaccumulatus, past participle ofaccumulare\"to heap up, amass,\" fromad\"to,\" here perhaps emphatic (seead-), +cumulare\"heap up,\" fromcumulus\"heap\" (from suffixed form of PIE root*keue-\"to swell\"). From 1759 in intransitive sense of \"grow in size or number.\" Related:Accumulated;accumulating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accumulation",
    "response": "late 15c., \"that which is heaped up, an accumulated mass,\" from Latinaccumulationem(nominativeaccumulatio) \"a heaping up,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccumulare\"to heap up, amass,\" fromad\"to,\" here perhaps emphatic (seead-), +cumulare\"heap up,\" fromcumulus\"heap\" (from suffixed form of PIE root*keue-\"to swell\"). Meaning \"act of heaping up\" is from c. 1600."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accumulative",
    "response": "\"tending to accumulation; cumulative,\" 1650s, from Latin stemaccumulat-(seeaccumulate) +-ive. Related:Accumulatively;accumulativeness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accuracy",
    "response": "\"state of being extremely precise or exact; conformity to truth,\" 1660s, fromaccurate+ abstract noun suffix-cy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accurate",
    "response": "1610s, \"done with care,\" from Latinaccuratus\"prepared with care, exact, elaborate,\" past participle ofaccurare\"take care of,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +curare\"take care of\" (seecure(n.1)). The notion of doing something carefully led to that of being precise (1650s). A stronger word thancorrect(adj.), weaker thanexact(adj.). Related:Accurately;accurateness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accursed",
    "response": "alsoaccurst, early 13c.,acursede\"being under a curse,\" past-participle adjective from obsolete verbacursen\"pronounce a curse upon, excommunicate\" (late 12c.), froma-intensive prefix (seea-(1)) +cursein\"to curse\" (seecurse(v.)). The unetymological-c-is 15c., a mistaken Latinism in imitation of words inacc-. The weakened sense of \"worthy of a curse, damnable\" is from 1590s. Related:Accursedly;accursedness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accusation",
    "response": "late 14c.,accusacioun, \"charge of wrongdoing,\" from Old Frenchacusacion\"charge, indictment\" (Modern Frenchaccusation) or directly from Latinaccusationem(nominativeaccusatio) \"formal complaint, indictment,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaccusare\"call to account, make complaint against,\" fromad causa, fromad\"with regard to\" (seead-) +causa\"a cause; a lawsuit\" (seecause(n.)). The meaning \"that which is charged (against someone)\" is from early 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accusative",
    "response": "grammatical case whose primary function is to express destination or goal of motion, mid-15c., from Anglo-Frenchaccusatif, Old Frenchacusatif, or directly from Latin(casus) accusativus\"(case) of accusing,\" fromaccusatus, past participle ofaccusare\"to call to account, make complaint against\" (seeaccuse).The Latin word was chosen somewhat inaccurately to translate Greek(ptōsis) aitiatikē\"(case) of that which is caused\" based on the similarity of the Greek word to the Greek verbaitiasthai\"to accuse.\" Greekaitiais the root of both, and means \"cause\" as well as \"accusation,\" hence the confusion of the Romans. A more correct translation would have beencasus causativus.Typically it is the case of the direct object, but also sometimes denoting \"motion towards.\" Nouns and adjectives in French, Spanish, and Italian, languages from which English has borrowed heavily, generally were formed from the accusative case of a Latin word. Related:Accusatival;accusatively."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accusatory",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"containing an accusation,\" from Latinaccusatorius\"of a prosecutor, relating to prosecution; making a complaint,\" fromaccusare\"call to account, make complaint against\" (seeaccuse). Related:Accusatorial(1801);accusatorially."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accuse",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"charge (with an offense, fault, error, etc.), impugn, blame,\" from Old Frenchacuser\"to accuse, indict, reproach, blame\" (13c., Modern Frenchaccuser), earlier \"announce, report, disclose\" (12c.), or directly from Latinaccusare\"to call to account, make complaint against, reproach, blame; bring to trial, prosecute, arraign indict,\" from the phrasead causa, fromad\"with regard to\" (seead-) +causa\"a cause; a lawsuit\" (seecause(n.)). \"Accusecommonly, though not invariably, expresses something more formal and grave thancharge\" [Century Dictionary, 1902]. Related:Accused;accusing;accusingly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accused",
    "response": "\"person charged with a crime,\" 1590s, from past participle ofaccuse(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accuser",
    "response": "\"one who accuses or blames,\" especially \"person who formally accuses another of an offense before a magistrate,\" mid-14c.,accusour, from Anglo-Frenchaccusour, Old Frenchaccusor, from Latinaccusator, agent-noun from past-participle stem ofaccusare(seeaccuse)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accustom",
    "response": "\"familiarize by custom or use,\" early 15c.,accustomen, from Old Frenchacostumer\"become accustomed; accustom, bring into use\" (12c., Modern Frenchaccoutumer), fromà\"to\" (seead-) + verb fromcostume\"habit, practice\" (seecustom(n.)). Related:Accustomed;accustoming."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "accustomed",
    "response": "late 15c., \"made customary, habitual, often practiced or used,\" past-participle adjective fromaccustom(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ace",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"one at dice,\" from Old Frenchas\"one at dice\" (12c.), from Latinas\"a unit, one, a whole, unity;\" also the name of a small Roman coin (originally a rectangular bronze plaque weighing one pound, it eventually was reduced by depreciation to half an ounce; in imperial times it became a round coin). The Latin word also is the source of Spanishas, Italianasso, Germanass, Dutchaas, Danishes. It is perhaps originally Etruscan and related to Greekheis\"one\" (from PIE root*sem-(1) \"one, as one\"), or it might have been taken directly into Latin from the Greek word.In English, it meant the side of the die with only one mark before it meant the playing card with one pip (1530s). Because this was the lowest roll at dice,acewas used metaphorically in Middle English for \"bad luck\" or \"something of no value;\" but as the ace often is the highest playing card, the extended senses based on \"excellence, good quality\" arose 18c. as card-playing became popular.Ace in the holein the figurative sense of \"concealed advantage\" is attested from 1904, from crooked stud-poker deals.The meaning \"outstanding pilot\" dates from 1917 (technically, in World War I aviators' jargon, one who has brought down 10 enemy planes, though originally in reference to 5 shot down), from Frenchl'ace(1915), which, according to Bruce Robertson (ed.) \"Air Aces of the 1914-1918 War\" was used in prewar French sporting publications for \"top of the deck\" boxers, cyclists, etc. The sports meaning \"point scored\" (1819) led to sense of \"unreturnable serve\" (by 1889)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aceldama",
    "response": "late 14c., name of the potter's field near Jerusalem that was purchased with the money Judas Iscariot took to betray Jesus, literally \"place of bloodshed,\" from GreekAkeldama, rendering an Aramaic (Semitic) name akin to Syriachaqal dema\"the field of blood.\" So called for being purchased with the blood-money."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acentric",
    "response": "\"having no center,\" 1852; seea-(3) \"not\" +-centric."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acephalous",
    "response": "\"headless,\" 1731, from Frenchacéphale+-ousor directly from Late Latinacephalus, from Greekakephalos. Seea-(3) \"not\" +cephalo-\"head.\"Principally in botany and zoology, but also \"without a leader\" (1751).Acephalias the name of a fabulous race of men with no heads, said by ancient writers to inhabit part of Africa, is attested from c. 1600, from Late Latin plural ofacephalus, from Greekakephalos; the name also appears in Church history in reference to sects that refused to have priests or bishops (1620s). Related:Acephalian(1580s);acephalic(1650s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Acer",
    "response": "maple tree genus name, from Latinacer, a word of uncertain origin, perhaps from PIE*ak-\"be sharp\" (seeacro-) and so called for its pointed leaves.There seem to have been two roots for \"maple\" in Indo-European; cognates of this one are said to include Old High Germanahorn\"maple,\" and there is a similar form in Greekakastos\"maple,\" perhaps also Hittitehiqqar-\"maple.\" De Vaan writes, \"This may well be a non-PIE tree name which was borrowed into Greek and Latin.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acerbic",
    "response": "1865, originally, and usually, figurative: \"sour, harsh, severe\" (of speech, manners, etc.), from Latinacerbus\"harsh to the taste, sharp, bitter, sour,\" especially of unripe fruits, etc., also figuratively, of character, conduct, etc. (seeacerbity) +-ic. The earlier adjective was simplyacerb(1650s), from Frenchacerbe, from Latinacerbus."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acerbity",
    "response": "\"sourness, with roughness or astringency of taste,\" 1570s, from Frenchacerbité, from Latinacerbitatem(nominativeacerbitas) \"harshness, sharpness, bitterness, sourness,\" literal and figurative (as invirus acerbitatis\"the poison of malice\"), fromacerbus\"bitter to taste, sharp, sour, tart,\" from Proto-Italic*akro-po-\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\").The earliest use in English is figurative, of \"sharp and bitter\" persons. Of tastes, from 1610s. Latinacerbusis related toacer\"sharp\" assuperbus\"haughty\" tosuper\"above.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acervate",
    "response": "\"to heap up,\" 1610s, from Latinacervatus, past participle ofacervare\"to heap up,\" fromacervus\"heap,\" which is akin toacer\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point\"). Related:Acervated;acervating;acerval;acervative;acervuline\"occurring in clusters; clustered\" (by 1859)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acervulus",
    "response": "\"brain-sand\" (anatomical), 1806, medical Latin, literally \"little heap,\" diminutive of Latinacervus\"heap,\" which is akin toacer\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point\"). Compareacervate."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acescent",
    "response": "\"becoming sour,\" 1670s, from Frenchacescent, from Latinacescentem(nominativeacescens), present participle ofacescere\"become sour,\" fromacer\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acetate",
    "response": "by 1790 in a translation of Fourcroy, \"salt formed by combining acetic acid with a base,\" from Latinacetum\"vinegar\" (seeacetic) + chemical suffix-ate(3). As a type of synthetic material, it is attested from 1920, short foracetate silk(1912), etc."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acetic",
    "response": "1808 (inacetic acid), from Frenchacétique\"pertaining to vinegar, sour, having the properties of vinegar,\" from Latinacetum\"vinegar\" (properlyvinum acetum\"wine turned sour;\" seevinegar), originally the past participle ofacere\"be sharp; be sour\" (related toacer\"sharp,\" from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acetification",
    "response": "\"process of turning to vinegar,\" 1753, from Latinacetum\"vinegar\" (seeacetic) +-fication, word-forming element indicating \"making or causing.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acetone",
    "response": "colorless volatile liquid, 1839, literally \"a derivative of acetic acid,\" from Latinacetum\"vinegar\" (seeacetic) + Greek-based chemical suffix-one, which owes its use in chemistry to this word."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acetylene",
    "response": "gaseous hydrocarbon, 1860, from Frenchacétylène, coined by French chemist Pierre Eugène Marcellin Berthelot from chemical ending-ene+acetyl, which was coined fromacetic+-ylin 1839 by German chemist Justus von Liebig. Liebig's coinage was in reference to a different radical;acetylwas transferred to its current sense in 1850s, but Berthelot's coinage was based on the original use ofacetyl."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ach",
    "response": "aspirated form ofah; in English often used in representations of German or Celtic speech."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Achaean",
    "response": "in Homeric language, \"a Greek,\" generally; later restricted to natives or inhabitants ofAchaea, a region in the Peloponnesus. TheAchaean Leagueafter c. 280 B.C.E. was a model for later federal republics. In Latin,Achaicusmeant \"a Greek.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Achates",
    "response": "name of the armor-bearer and faithful friend of Aeneas in the \"Aeneid;\" The phrasefidus Achateswas proverbial for \"faithful friend, loyal and devoted companion.\" The name is from Greekakhatēs\"agate\" (seeagate)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ache",
    "response": "Middle Englishaken, from Old Englishacan\"suffer continued pain,\" from Proto-Germanic*akanan, which is perhaps from a PIE root*ag-es-\"fault, guilt,\" with apparent cognates in Sanskrit and Greek, which itself is perhaps imitative of groaning.Originally the verb was pronounced \"ake,\" the noun \"ache\" (as inspeak/speech). The noun changed its pronunciation to conform to the verb, but the spelling of both was changed toachec. 1700 on a false assumption of a Greek origin (specifically Greekakhos\"pain, distress,\" which rather is a distant relation ofawe(n.)). Related:Ached;aching."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "achievable",
    "response": "\"capable of being gained or performed,\" 1620s; seeachieve(v.) +-able. Related:Achievably;achievableness;achievability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "achieve",
    "response": "early 14c.,acheven, \"to perform, execute, accomplish;\" late 14c., \"gain as a result of effort,\" from Old Frenchachever(12c.) \"to finish, accomplish, complete,\" from phraseà chef (venir)\"at an end, finished,\" or Vulgar Latin*accapare, from Late Latinad caput (venire); both the French and Late Latin phrases meaning literally \"to come to a head,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) + stem of Latincaput\"head\" (from PIE root*kaput-\"head\").Related:Achieved;achieving."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "achievement",
    "response": "late 15c., \"act of completing\" (something), from Frenchachèvement\"a finishing,\" noun of action from Old Frenchachever\"to finish, accomplish\" (seeachieve). Meaning \"thing achieved\" is recorded from 1590s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "achromatic",
    "response": "\"destitute of color; transmitting light without decomposing it into constituent colors,\" 1766, froma-(3) \"not, without\" +chromatic. Related:Achromatically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "achy",
    "response": "\"full of aches, sore, aching,\" 1875, first recorded in George Eliot's letters, fromache(n.) +-y(2). Middle English hadakeful\"painful\" (early 15c.). Related:Achily;achiness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acicular",
    "response": "\"resembling or in the form of small needles,\" 1794, from Latinacicula\"needle, small pin,\" diminutive ofacus\"pin\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acid",
    "response": "1620s, \"of the taste of vinegar,\" from Frenchacide(16c.) or directly from Latinacidus\"sour, sharp, tart\" (also figurative, \"disagreeable,\" etc.), adjective of state fromacere\"to be sour, be sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\").Figurative use in English (\"sour, sharp, biting\") is from 1775; the word was applied to intense colors by 1916; anacid dye(1888) involves an acid bath.Acid rain\"highly acidity in rain caused by atmospheric pollution\" is recorded by 1859 in reference to England.Acid dropas a kind of hard sugar candy flavored with tartaric acid is by 1835, withdrop(n.) in the \"lozenge\" sense.Acid testis American English, 1881, in literal use a quick way to distinguish gold from similar metals by application of nitric acid. Fowler wrote (1920) that it was then in vogue in the figurative sense and \"became familiar through a conspicuous use of it during the war by President Wilson.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acidic",
    "response": "\"containing a large amount of the acid element,\" 1877, originally in geology; seeacid(n.) +-ic. The geological use was chemical, in reference to the acid element (silicon, etc.) in certain salts, and was opposed tobasic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acidify",
    "response": "\"make acid; become acid; render sour,\" literally or figuratively, 1784 (implied inacidifying); seeacid(adj.) +-ify. Related:Acidified."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acidity",
    "response": "\"quality of being acid or sour; tartness,\" 1610s, from Frenchacidité(16c.) or directly from Latinaciditatem(nominativeaciditas) \"sourness,\" noun of quality from Latinacidus\"sour, tart\" (seeacid(adj.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acidulate",
    "response": "\"make somewhat sour, flavor with an acid,\" 1704 (implied inacidulated), from Latinacidulus\"slightly sour\" (seeacidulous) +-ate(2). Related:Acidulating;acidulent."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acidulous",
    "response": "\"sub-acidic, slightly sour\" (of cream of tartar, oranges, etc.), 1766, also used figuratively for \"sour-tempered;\" from Latinacidulus\"slightly sour,\" a diminutive ofacidus(seeacid(adj.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acknowledge",
    "response": "late 15c., \"admit or show one's knowledge,\" a blend of Middle Englishaknow\"admit or show one's knowledge\" and Middle Englishknowlechen\"admit, acknowledge\" (c. 1200; seeknowledge). Middle Englishaknowis from Old Englishoncnawan\"understand, come to recognize,\" fromon(seeon(prep.)) +cnawan\"recognize;\" seeknow).\"By 16th c. the earlier vbs.knowledgeanda(c)know... were obs., andacknowledgetook their place\" [OED]. In the merger, an unetymological-c-slipped in; perhaps the explanation is that when Englishkn-became a simple \"n\" sound, the-c-stepped up to preserve, in this word, the ancient \"kn-\" sound. Related:Acknowledged;acknowledging."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acme",
    "response": "\"highest point,\" 1560s, from Greekakmē\"(highest) point, edge; peak of anything,\" hence \"prime (of life, etc.), the best time\" (from PIE*ak-ma-, suffixed form of root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\"). In English it was written in Greek letters until c. 1620. The U.S. grocery store chain was founded 1891 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acne",
    "response": "skin eruption common during puberty, 1813, from Modern Latin, fromaknas, a 6c. Latin clerical misreading of Greekakmas, accusative plural ofakmē\"point\" (seeacme), from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce.\" The \"pointed\" pimples are the source of the medical use."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acold",
    "response": "\"cold,\" early 14c.; seea-(1), here perhaps intensive +cold(adj.). Or it might be literally \"a-cooled,\" from the past participle of the verbacool\"to take cold\" (late Old English); \"to make cold\" (15c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acolyte",
    "response": "early 14c., \"inferior officer in the church,\" from Old Frenchacoliteor directly from Medieval Latinacolytus(Late Latinacoluthus), from Greekakolouthos\"following, attending on,\" as a noun, \"a follower, attendant,\" literally \"having one way,\" froma-\"together with,\" copulative prefix (seea-(3)), +keleuthos\"a way, road, path, course, journey,\" which is of unknown etymology. The word was in late Old English asacolitus, a Latin form; in early modern English a corrected formacolythewas used."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acomia",
    "response": "\"baldness, want or deficiency of hair,\" a medical term, by 1860, a coinage in Modern Latin from  abstract noun suffix-ia(see-ia) + Latinized form of Greekakomos\"hairless, bald,\" froma-\"not, without\" (seea-(3)) +komē\"hair\" (seecomet)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aconite",
    "response": "poisonous plant (also known asmonkshoodandwolfsbane), 1570s, from Frenchaconit(16c.), from Latinaconitum, from Greekakoniton, which is of unknown origin.The highly poisonous alkaloid in it, once isolated, was namedaconitine(1826). The ancient folk-etymology of the name is Derived by the ancients from Greekakoniti\"without dust,\" hence \"without struggle or fight,\" hence \"invincible\" in its deadly effect. But Beekes finds this \"hardly possible\" and proposes a substrate origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acorn",
    "response": "Middle Englishakorn, from Old Englishæcern\"nut, mast of trees, acorn,\" a common Germanic word (cognates: Old Norseakarn, Dutchaker, Low Germanecker\"acorn,\" GermanEcker, Gothicakran\"fruit\"), originally the mast of any forest tree. It is by most sources said to be related to Proto-Germanic*akraz, the source of Old Englishæcer\"open land,\" Gothicakrs\"field,\" Old Frenchaigrun\"fruits and vegetables\" (from Frankish or some other Germanic source), perhaps on the notion of  \"fruit of the open or unenclosed land;\" seeacre.The sense was gradually restricted in Low German, Scandinavian, and English to the most important of the forest produce for feeding swine: the mast of the oak tree. The regular modern form would be*akern; the current spelling emerged 15c.-16c. by folk etymology association withoak(Old Englishac) andcorn(n.1), neither of which has anything to do with it.Acorn squashis attested by 1937."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acoustic",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"pertaining to hearing or sound,\" from Frenchacoustique, from Latinized form of Greekakoustikos\"pertaining to hearing,\" fromakoustos\"heard, audible,\" verbal adjective fromakouein\"to hear,\" which probably is from copulative prefixa-(seea-(3)) +koein\"to mark, perceive, hear\" (from PIE root*kous-\"to hear,\" which is also the presumed source of Englishhear).In reference to material meant to deaden sound, 1924. Of sound reproduced mechanically (rather than electrically) from 1932 in reference to gramophone players;acoustic guitar(as distinguished fromelectric) is attested by 1958. Related:Acoustical;acoustically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acoustics",
    "response": "1680s, \"the science of sound,\" fromacoustic; also see-ics. The meaning \"acoustic properties\" of a building, etc., is attested from 1885."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquaint",
    "response": "early 13c., \"make oneself known\" (reflexive, now obsolete); early 14c., \"to gain for oneself personal knowledge of,\" from Old Frenchacointer\"make known; make or seek acquaintance of,\" from Vulgar Latin *accognitare\"to make known,\" from Latinaccognitus\"acquainted with,\" past participle ofaccognoscere\"know well,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +cognitus, past participle ofcognoscere\"come to know\" (seecognizance).Meaning \"to inform (someone of something), furnish with knowledge or information\" is from 1550s. Related:Acquainted;acquainting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquaintance",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"state of being acquainted;\" late 14c., \"person with whom one is acquainted;\" also \"personal knowledge;\" from Old Frenchacointance\"acquaintance, friendship, familiarity,\" noun of action fromacointer\"make known\" (seeacquaint).Acquaintant(17c.), would have been better in the \"person known\" sense but is now obsolete. Fowler regardsacquaintanceship(1792) as a \"needless variant.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquainted",
    "response": "early 13c., \"personally known;\" past-participle adjective fromacquaint(v.). Of skills, situations, etc., from late 15c.Acquaintalso was used as an adjective (late 13c.) \"acquainted.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquiesce",
    "response": "1610s, \"remain at rest\" (a sense now obsolete); 1650s as \"agree tacitly, concur,\" from Frenchacquiescer\"to yield or agree to; be at rest,\" (14c.), from Latinacquiescere/adquiescere\"become quiet, remain at rest, rest, repose,\" thus \"be satisfied with, be content,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +quiescere\"become quiet,\" fromquies(genitivequietis) \"rest, quiet\" (from PIE root*kweie-\"to rest, be quiet\"). Related:Acquiesced;acquiescing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquiescence",
    "response": "1630s, \"rest, quiet, satisfaction,\" from Frenchacquiescence, noun of action fromacquiescer\"to yield or agree to; be at rest\" (seeacquiesce). Meaning \"silent consent, passive assent\" is recorded from 1640s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquiescent",
    "response": "\"disposed to yield, submissive,\" 1690s (implied inacquiescently), from Latinacquiescentem(nominativeacquiescens), present participle ofacquiescere\"become quiet, remain at rest\" (seeacquiesce)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquire",
    "response": "\"to get or gain, obtain,\" mid-15c.,acqueren, from Old Frenchaquerre\"acquire, gain, earn, procure\" (12c., Modern Frenchacquérir), from Vulgar Latin*acquaerere, corresponding to Latinacquirere/adquirere\"to get in addition to, accumulate, gain,\" fromad\"to,\" here perhaps emphatic (seead-), +quaerere\"to seek to obtain\" (seequery(v.)). Reborrowed in current form from Latin c. 1600. Related:Acquired;acquiring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquired",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"gained by effort,\" past-participle adjective fromacquire. Of diseases, \"occurring after birth, thus not dependent on heredity,\" 1842 (opposed tocongenital);acquired immune deficiencyis attested by 1980;acquired immune deficiency syndromeby 1982.Acquired tasteis attested from 1734."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquirement",
    "response": "\"act of acquiring; that which is acquired,\" 1620s, fromacquire+-ment. Perhaps modeled on Frenchacquerement(16c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquisition",
    "response": "late 14c.,adquisicioun, \"act of obtaining,\" from Old Frenchacquisicion\"purchase, acquirement\" (13c., Modern Frenchacquisition) or directly from Latinacquisitionem(nominativeacquisitio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofacquirere\"get in addition, accumulate,\" fromad\"to,\" here perhaps emphatic (seead-), +quaerere\"to seek to obtain\" (seequery(v.)).The meaning \"thing obtained\" is from late 15c. The vowel change of-ae-to-i-in Latin is due to a phonetic rule in that language involving unaccented syllables in compounds."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquisitive",
    "response": "1630s, \"owned through acquisition\" (now obsolete, this sense going withacquired), from Latinacquisit-, past-participle stem ofacquirere\"accumulate, gain\" (seeacquire) +-ive. Meaning \"given to acquisition, avaricious\" is by 1824. Related:Acquisitively(1590s);acquisitiveness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquit",
    "response": "mid-13c.,aquiten, \"repay, reciprocate, reward or retaliate for\" (a good or bad deed); c. 1300 as \"satisfy a debt; redeem (a pledge),\" from Old Frenchaquiter,acquiter\"pay, pay up, settle a claim\" (12c., Modern Frenchacquitter), froma-\"to\" (seead-) +quite\"free, clear,\" from Medieval Latinquitus,quittus, from Latinquietus\"free\" (in Medieval Latin \"free from war, debts, etc.\"), also \"calm, resting\" (from PIE root*kweie-\"to rest, be quiet\"). Also in part from Medieval Latinacquitare.From mid-14c. as \"relieve (someone) of an obligation, release from a pledge,\" hence the meanings \"set (an accused person) free from charges, pronounce not guilty,\" and \"discharge one's duty; behave or conduct oneself\" (for better or worse), all of which date to late 14c. The notion in the word is \"to release or discharge,\" from an obligation or from accusation, guilt, censure, or suspicion. Related:Acquitted;acquitting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquittal",
    "response": "early 15c.,aquitaille, \"payment of debt or retribution;\" seeacquit+-al(2). Sense of \"a release from debt or obligation\" is from mid-15c.; that of \"freeing from charge or offense\" (by legal process) is from 1530s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acquittance",
    "response": "\"legal settlement\" of a debt, obligation, etc., early 14c.,aquitaunce, from Old Frenchaquitanceand Medieval Latinacquietantia; seeacquit+-ance."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acre",
    "response": "Old Englishæcer\"tilled field, open land,\" from Proto-Germanic*akraz\"field, pasture\" (source also of Old Norseakr, Old Saxonakkar, Old Frisianekker, Middle Dutchacker, Dutchakker, Old High Germanachar, Germanacker, Gothicakrs\"field\"), from PIE root*agro-\"field.\"\"[O]riginally 'open country, untenanted land, forest'; ... then, with advance in the agricultural state, pasture land, tilled land, an enclosed or defined piece of land\" [OED]. In English at first without reference to dimension; in late Old English the amount of land a yoke of oxen could plow in a day, afterward defined by statute 13c. and later as a piece 40 poles by 4, or an equivalent shape [OED cites 5 Edw. I, 31 Edw. III, 24 Hen. VIII]. The older sense is retained inGod's acre\"churchyard.\"The Germanic word was adopted early in Old French and Medieval Latin, hence the Modern English spelling, which by normal development would be*aker(comparebakerfrom Old Englishbæcere)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acreage",
    "response": "\"number of acres in a tract of land,\" 1795, fromacre+-age."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrid",
    "response": "1712, \"sharp and bitter to the taste,\" formed irregularly (perhaps by influence ofacrimonious) from Latinacer(fem.acris) \"sharp to the senses, pungent, bitter; eager, fierce,\" also figuratively, of qualities, \"active, ardent, spirited,\" also \"hasty, quick, passionate;\" of mind \"violent, vehement; subtle, penetrating,\" from PIE*akri-\"sharp,\" from root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce.\" Of feelings, temper, etc., in English from 1781. The-idsuffix probably is in imitation ofacid.Acrious(1670s) is a correct formation, but seldom seen. Related:Acridly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acridity",
    "response": "\"quality of being acrid,\" 1799, fromacrid+-ity.Acridness(1759) is older."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrimonious",
    "response": "1610s, \"acrid,\" from Frenchacrimonieux, from Medieval Latinacrimoniosus, from Latinacrimonia\"sharpness\" (seeacrimony). Now usually figurative, of dispositions, debates, etc., \"bitter, irritating in manner\" (1775). Related:Acrimoniously;acrimoniousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrimony",
    "response": "1540s, \"quality of being sharp or pungent in taste,\" from Frenchacrimonieor directly from Latinacrimonia\"sharpness, pungency of taste,\" figuratively \"acrimony, severity, energy,\" abstract noun fromacer\"sharp\" (fem.acris), from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +-moniasuffix of action, state, condition (see-mony). Figurative extension to personal sharpness or bitterness is by 1610s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrobat",
    "response": "1845, from Frenchacrobate\"tightrope-walker\" (14c.) and directly from a Latinized form of Greekakrobatēs\"rope dancer, gymnastic performer,\" which is related toakrobatos\"going on tip-toe, climbing up high,\" fromakros\"topmost, at the point end\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") + Greek agential element-batēs\"one that goes, one that treads (in some manner), one that is based,\" from-batos, verbal adjective from stem ofbainein\"to go, walk, step\" (from PIE root*gwa-\"to go, come\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrobatic",
    "response": "\"of or pertaining to an acrobat or an acrobat's performances,\" 1848; seeacrobat+-ic, probably modeled on Frenchacrobatique. Related:Acrobatically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrobatics",
    "response": "1859, \"acrobatic performances or feats,\" fromacrobatic; also see-ics. Alsoacrobatism(1864).Acrobacy(1918, from Frenchacrobatie) sometimes was used. Figurative use is attested by 1915."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acromegaly",
    "response": "\"gigantism due to activity of pituitary after normal growth has ceased,\" 1886, from Frenchacromégalie, from medical Latinacromegalia, from Greekakron\"extremity, highest point, mountain peak, headland,\" neuter ofakros\"at the furthest point\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +megas\"great\" (fem.megale; from PIE root*meg-\"great\"). Said in contemporary literature to have been coined 1885 by French physician Dr. Pierre Marie."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acronym",
    "response": "word formed from the first letters of a series of words, 1943, American English coinage fromacro-+-onym\"name\" (abstracted fromhomonym; ultimately from PIE root*no-men-\"name\"). With the exception of cabalistic esoterica and acrostic poetry, this way of forming words wasexceedingly uncommon before 20c.For distinction of usage (regretfully ignored on this site), seeinitialism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrophobia",
    "response": "\"morbid fear of heights,\" 1887, medical Latin, from Greekakros\"at the end, topmost\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +-phobia\"fear.\" Coined by Italian physician Dr. Andrea Verga in a paper describing the condition, from which Verga himself suffered."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acropolis",
    "response": "\"elevated part of a Greek city,\" often the site of original settlement and usually a citadel, 1660s, from Latinized form of Greekakropolis\"citadel\" (especially, with capitalA-, that of Athens), fromakros\"highest, upper\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +polis\"city\" (seepolis). The plural would beacropoles."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "across",
    "response": "c. 1200,o cros, \"in the shape of a cross;\" c. 1300,a-croiz, \"in a crossed position;\" early 14c.,acros, \"from one side to another;\" a contraction of Anglo-Frenchan cros, literally \"on cross;\" seea-(1) +cross(n.)).Meaning \"on the other side (as a result of crossing)\" is from 1750. In crossword puzzle clues from 1924. Spellingacrost, representing a dialectal or vulgar pronunciation, is attested by 1759. Phraseacross the board\"embracing all categories\" (1945) is said to be originally from horse-racing, in reference to a bet of the same amount of money on a horse to win, place, or show. Toget (something) across\"make (something) understood or appreciated\" is by 1913, probably from earlier theater expressionget (something) across the footlights, perform it so as to be received by the audience (1894)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrostic",
    "response": "short poem in which the initial letters of the lines, taken in order, spell a word or phrase, 1580s, from Medieval Latinacrostichis, from Greekakrostikhis, fromakros\"at the end, outermost\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +stikhos\"line of verse,\" literally \"row, line\" (from PIE root*steigh-\"to stride, step, rise;\" seestair). The second element is properly-stich, but it has been assimilated to words in-ic. As an adjective from 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acrylic",
    "response": "1843, \"of or containingacryl,\" the name of a radical derived fromacrolein(1843), the name of a liquid in onions and garlic that makes eyes tear, from Latinacer\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +olere\"to smell\" (seeodor) +-in(see-ine(2)). With adjectival suffix-ic. Modern senses often short foracrylic fiber,acrylic resin, etc."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "act",
    "response": "late 14c., \"a thing done,\" from Latinactus\"a doing; a driving, impulse, a setting in motion; a part in a play,\" andactum\"a thing done\" (originally a legal term), both fromagere\"to set in motion, drive, drive forward,\" hence \"to do, perform,\" figuratively \"incite to action; keep in movement, stir up\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").The verbagerehad a broad range of meaning in Latin, including \"act on stage, play the part of; plead a cause at law; chase; carry off, steal.\" The theatrical (\"part of a play,\" 1510s) and legislative (early 15c.) senses of the noun also were in Latin.The meaning \"one of a series of performances in a variety show\" is from 1890. The meaning \"display of exaggerated behavior\" is from 1928, extended from the theatrical sense.In the act\"in the process\" is from 1590s, perhaps originally from a late 16c. sense ofthe actas \"sexual intercourse.\"Act of God\"uncontrollable natural force\" is recorded by 1726.Toget into the act\"participate\" is from 1947; toget (one's) act together\"organize one's (disorderly) life\" is by 1976, perhaps euphemistic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Actaeon",
    "response": "in Greek mythology, the name of the hunter who discovered Artemis bathing and was changed by her to a stag and torn to death by his hounds. The name is of unknown origin. Sometimes used figuratively in 17c. for \"a cuckold\" (because of his \"horns\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acting",
    "response": "1590s, \"putting forth activity, active,\" present-participle adjective fromact(v.). Meaning \"performing temporary duties\" is from 1797."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actinium",
    "response": "radioactive element discovered in 1899; seeactino-\"pertaining to rays\" + chemical suffix-ium. It emits beta rays. The name was given earlier to a supposed new element (1881)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "action",
    "response": "mid-14c.,accioun, \"cause or grounds for a lawsuit,\" from Anglo-Frenchaccioun, Old Frenchaccion,action(12c.) \"action; lawsuit, case,\" from Latinactionem(nominativeactio) \"a putting in motion; a performing, a doing; public acts, official conduct; lawsuit, legal action\" (source also of Spanishaccion, Italianazione), noun of action from past-participle stem ofagere\"to do\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").Spelling with the restored Latin-t-begins in 15c. The meaning \"active exertion, activity\" is from late 14c. The sense of \"something done, an act, deed\" is late 14c. The meaning \"military fighting\" is from 1590s. The meaning \"way in which (a firearm, etc.) acts\" is from 1845. As a film director's command, it is attested from 1923.The meaning \"noteworthy or important activity\" in a modern sense by 1933, as in the figurative phrasea piece of the action(by 1965), perhaps from a sense ofactionin card-playing jargon attested by 1914.But there are uses ofactionas far back as c. 1600 that seem to mean \"noteworthy activity.\" The meaning \"excitement\" is recorded from 1968.In action\"in a condition of effective operation\" is from 1650s. Phraseactions speak louder than wordsis attested from 1731.Action-packedis attested from 1953, originally of movies."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actionable",
    "response": "\"furnishing sufficient grounds for a (legal) action,\" 1590s; fromaction+-able. Related:Actionably."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activate",
    "response": "1620s, \"make active, intensify;\" seeactive+-ate(2). Meaning \"put into action\" is from 1902, originally in chemistry. Related:Activated;activating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activation",
    "response": "\"action or process of making or being operative,\" 1906, noun of action fromactivate(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "active",
    "response": "mid-14c.,actif,active, \"given to worldly activity\" (opposed tocontemplativeormonastic), from Old Frenchactif(12c.) and directly from Latinactivus, fromactus\"a doing\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").As \"capable of acting\" (opposed topassive), from late 14c. Meaning \"energetic, lively\" is from 1590s; that of \"working, effective, in operation\" (opposed toinactive) is from 1640s. The grammaticalactive voiceis recorded from 1765; grammatical use ofactive, signifying performance and not endurance of an action, dates from mid-15c. (opposed topassiveorreflexive)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actively",
    "response": "c. 1400,actifli,activeli, \"secularly,\" fromactive+-ly(2). Meaning \"vigorously\" is early 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activeness",
    "response": "\"quality of being active, activity,\" c. 1600, fromactive+-ness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activism",
    "response": "1920 in the political sense of \"advocating energetic action;\" seeactive+-ism. Earlier (1907) it was used in reference to a philosophical theory. Compareactivist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activist",
    "response": "\"one who advocates a doctrine of direct action\" in any sense, 1915; fromactive+-ist. Originally in reference to a political movement in Sweden advocating abandonment of neutrality in World War I and active support for the Central Powers. The word was used earlier in philosophy (1907)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "activity",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"active or secular life,\" from Old Frenchactivité, from Medieval Latinactivitatem(nominativeactivitas), a word in Scholastic philosophy, from Latinactivus\"active\" (seeactive). The meaning \"state of being active, briskness, liveliness\" is recorded from 1520s; that of \"capacity for acting on matter\" is from 1540s. As \"an educational exercise,\" by 1923."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actor",
    "response": "late 14c., \"an overseer, guardian, steward,\" from Latinactor\"an agent or doer; a driver (of sheep, etc.),\" in law, \"accuser, plaintiff,\" also \"theatrical player, orator,\" from past-participle stem ofagere\"to set in motion, drive, drive forward,\" hence \"to do, perform,\" also \"act on stage, play the part of; plead a cause at law\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). In English from mid-15c. as \"a doer, maker,\" also \"a plaintiff at law.\" The sense of \"one who performs in plays\" is by 1580s, originally applied to both men and women. Related:Actorish;actorly;actory."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actress",
    "response": "1580s, \"female who does something;\" seeactor+-ess; stage sense is from 1700. Sometimes Frenchactricewas used. Related:Actressy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Acts",
    "response": "1530s, short forActs of the Apostlesin the New Testament."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actual",
    "response": "early 14c., \"pertaining to acts or an action;\" late 14c. in the broader sense of \"real, existing\" (as opposed topotential,ideal, etc.); from Old Frenchactuel\"now existing, up to date\" (13c.), from Late Latinactualis\"active, pertaining to action,\" adjectival form of Latinactus\"a doing\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actuality",
    "response": "late 14c., \"power, efficacy,\" from Medieval Latinactualitatem(nominativeactualitas), from Late Latinactualis\"pertaining to action,\" from Latinactus\"a doing\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). A Latin loan-translation of Greekenergeia\"activity, action, operation\" (seeenergy). Meaning \"state of being real\" is from 1670s (actualities\"existing conditions\" is from 1660s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actualization",
    "response": "\"a making real,\" 1824, noun of action fromactualize. Related:Actualisation."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actualize",
    "response": "\"to make actual,\" 1810, first attested in Coleridge, fromactual+-ize. Related:Actualized;actualizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actually",
    "response": "early 15c., \"in fact, in reality\" (as opposed to \"in possibility\"), fromactual+-ly(2). The meaning \"actively, vigorously\" is from mid-15c.; that of \"at this time, at present\" is from 1660s. As an intensive added to a statement and suggesting \"as a matter of fact, really, in truth\" it is attested from 1762, often used as an expression of mild wonder or surprise."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actuarial",
    "response": "\"of the business of an actuary,\" 1853, fromactuary+-al(1). Related:Actuarially."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actuary",
    "response": "1550s, \"registrar, clerk,\" from Medieval Latinactuarius\"copyist, account-keeper, short-hand writer,\" from Latinactusin the specialized sense \"public business\" (literally \"a doing;\" from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). Meaning \"person skilled in the calculation of chances and costs,\" especially as employed by an insurer, is from 1849."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "actuation",
    "response": "\"a putting in motion, communication of force,\" 1620s, noun of action fromactuate(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acuity",
    "response": "\"sharpness, acuteness,\" early 15c.,acuite, from Old Frenchacuite(14c.) or directly from Medieval Latinacuitatem(nominativeacuitas) \"sharpness,\" noun of state from Latinacuere\"to sharpen,\" literal and figurative (of intellect, emotion, etc.), related toacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aculeate",
    "response": "c. 1600, figurative, \"pointed, stinging,\" of writing, from Latinaculeatus\"having a sting; thorny, prickly,\" also figurative, fromaculeus\"a sting, prickle,\" diminutive ofacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\"). From 1660s in a literal sense, in zoology, \"furnished with a sting;\" by 1870 in botany."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acumen",
    "response": "\"quickness of perception, keen insight,\" 1530s, from Latinacumen\"a point, sting,\" hence, figuratively, \"mental sharpness, shrewdness,\" fromacuere\"to sharpen,\" literal and figurative (of intellect, emotion, etc.), related toacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\"). Related:Acuminous."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acuminate",
    "response": "1640s, \"having a long, tapering end\" (of certain feathers, leaves, etc.), from Latinacuminatus, past participle ofacuminare\"to sharpen,\" fromacumen\"a point\" (seeacumen). Related:Acuminated;acumination."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acupressure",
    "response": "1859, name of a method (developed by J.Y. Simpson) of stopping surgical bleeding by pinning or wiring the artery shut, from Latinacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +pressure(n.). From 1958 in reference to the oriental body therapy also known asshiatsu(said to mean literally \"finger-pressure\" in Japanese)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acupuncture",
    "response": "1680s, \"pricking with a needle\" as a surgical operation to ease pain, from Latinacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\") +puncture. The verb is recorded by 1972."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "acute",
    "response": "late 14c., originally of fevers and diseases, \"coming quickly to a crisis\" (opposed tochronic), from Latinacutus\"sharp, pointed,\" figuratively \"shrill, penetrating; intelligent, cunning,\" past participle ofacuere\"to sharpen\" (literal and figurative), from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce.\"It was also used of humors (early 15c.). The meaning \"ending in a sharp point\" is from 1560s; the sense of \"sharp or penetrating in intellect\" is from 1580s. Of feelings, pains, etc., \"intense,\" 1727. As a noun, early 15c. of fevers; c. 1600 as \"an acute accent.\" Related:Acutely;acuteness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ad",
    "response": "abbreviation ofadvertisement, attested by 1841. Long resisted by those in the trade, and according to Mencken (1945) denounced by William C. D'Arcy (president of Associated Advertising Clubs of the World) as \"the language of bootblacks, ... beneath the dignity of men of the advertising profession.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ada",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from HebrewAdha, literally \"ornament.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adage",
    "response": "\"brief, familiar proverb,\" 1540s, Frenchadage(16c.), from Latinadagium\"adage, proverb,\" apparently a collateral form ofadagio, fromad\"to\" (seead-) +*agi-, root ofaio\"I say,\" which is perhaps cognate with Armenianar-ac\"proverb,\"asem\"to say.\" But some find this unlikely and suggest the second element might be related toagein\"set in motion, drive, urge\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). Related:Adagial."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adagio",
    "response": "c. 1746, in music, \"slowly, leisurely and gracefully,\" Italian, a contraction ofad agio, fromad\"to, at\" (seead-) +agio\"leisure,\" from Vulgar Latin *adiacens, present participle ofadiacere\"to lie at, to lie near\" (compareadjacent). In noun sense of \"a slow movement,\" first attested 1784."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adam",
    "response": "masc. proper name, the biblical name of the first man, progenitor of the human race, from Hebrewadam\"man,\" literally \"(the one formed from the) ground\" (Hebrewadamah\"ground\"); compare Latinhomo\"man,\"humanus\"human,\"humus\"earth, ground, soil.\" Comparehomunculus.The name also was used to signify the evil inherent in human nature (as a consequence of Adam's fall), and other qualities (e.g. nakedness, gardening) associated with the biblical Adam.Adam's alefor \"water\" is colloquial from 1640s. Tonot know(someone)from Adam\"not know him at all\" is recorded by 1784 (with later elaborations up tofrom Adam's off ox, 1880). The pet form of the name in Middle English wasAddy, henceAddison; other old pet forms (Adkin,Adcock) also survive in surnames."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adamant",
    "response": "late 14c., \"hard, unbreakable,\" fromadamant(n.). The figurative sense of \"unshakeable\" (in belief, etc.) is by 1670s. Related:Adamantly;adamance."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adamantine",
    "response": "c. 1200, \"made of adamant; having the qualities of adamant\" (hard, unyielding, unbreakable, inflexible), from Latinadamantinus\"hard as steel, inflexible,\" from Greekadamantinos\"hard as adamant,\" fromadamas(genitiveadamantos) \"unbreakable, inflexible,\" as a noun, \"hardest material\" (seeadamant(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adamite",
    "response": "by 1630s as \"human being, descendant of Adam\" the Biblical first man, fromAdam+-ite(1). The term was used from 1620s in reference to Christian perfectionist sects or groups that practice nudism (or, as a 1657 poem has it, \"Cast off their petticoats and breeches\"), recalling the state of Adam before the Fall. They existed in 2c. North Africa, 14c.-15c. central Europe, and 1840s America. Related:Adamic;Adamitic;Adamitism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adamite",
    "response": "by 1630s as \"human being, descendant of Adam\" the Biblical first man, fromAdam+-ite(1). The term was used from 1620s in reference to Christian perfectionist sects or groups that practice nudism (or, as a 1657 poem has it, \"Cast off their petticoats and breeches\"), recalling the state of Adam before the Fall. They existed in 2c. North Africa, 14c.-15c. central Europe, and 1840s America. Related:Adamic;Adamitic;Adamitism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adapt",
    "response": "early 15c. (implied inadapted) \"to fit (something, for some purpose),\" from Old Frenchadapter(14c.), from Latinadaptare\"adjust, fit to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +aptare\"to join,\" fromaptus\"fitted\" (seeapt). Intransitive meaning \"to undergo modification so as to fit new circumstances\" is from 1956. Related:Adapting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adaptability",
    "response": "\"quality that renders adaptable,\" 1660s, fromadapt+-ability. In modern use especially in evolutionary biology, \"variability in respect to, or under the influence of, external conditions.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adaptable",
    "response": "1680s, \"capable of being made to fit by alteration,\" fromadapt+-able."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adaptation",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"action of adapting (something to something else),\" from Frenchadaptation, from Late Latinadaptationem(nominativeadaptatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofadaptare\"to adjust,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +aptare\"to join,\" fromaptus\"fitted\" (seeapt).The meaning \"condition of being adapted, state of being fitted to circumstances or relations\" is from 1670s. The sense of \"modification of a thing to suit new conditions\" is from 1790. The biological sense of \"variations in a living thing to suit changed conditions\" is by 1859, in Darwin's writings."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adapter",
    "response": "1801, \"one who adapts (something to something else),\" agent noun fromadapt. From 1808 as \"mechanical means of adapting objects so they fit or work together\" (originally of chemistry apparatus); electrical engineering sense is by 1907."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adaptive",
    "response": "\"of, pertaining to, or characterized by adaptation,\" 1795, fromadapt+-ive. The classically proper formation isadaptative(1831)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adays",
    "response": "late 14c., \"by day; on or in the day or time,\" with adverbial genitive-sfrom earlieraday(mid-13c.), prepositional phrase used as an adverb, froma-(1) \"on, on each\" +day(n.). The genitive ending now is regarded as an accusative plural."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "add",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to join or unite (something to something else),\" from Latinaddere\"add to, join, attach, place upon,\" literal and figurative, fromad\"to\" (seead-) +-dere, combining form meaning \"to put, place,\" fromdare\"to give\" (from PIE root*do-\"to give\").The intransitive meaning \"to do sums, do addition\" also is from late 14c. Related:Added;adding. Toadd upis from 1754; in the figurative meaning \"make sense,\" by 1942.Adding machine\"machine to cast up large sums\" is from 1822."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "added",
    "response": "\"additional,\" c. 1600, past-participle adjective fromadd(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addendum",
    "response": "1794, \"an appendix to a work; a thing to be added,\" from Latinaddendum, neuter ofaddendus\"that which is to be added,\" gerundive ofaddere\"add to, join, attach\" (seeadd(v.)). The classical plural form isaddenda."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adder",
    "response": "Middle Englishnaddre, from Old English (West Saxon)næddre(Merciannedre, Northumbriannedra), \"a snake; the Serpent in the Garden of Eden,\" from Proto-Germanic*naethro\"a snake\" (source also of Old Norsenaðra, Middle Dutchnadre, Old High Germannatra, GermanNatter, Gothicnadrs), from PIE root*nētr-\"snake\" (source also of Latinnatrix\"water snake\" (the sense is probably by folk-association withnare\"to swim\"); Old Irishnathir, Welshneidr\"snake, serpent\").The modern form represents a faulty separation 14c.-16c. ofa nadderintoan adder, for which see alsoapron,auger,nickname,orange,humble pie,aitchbone,umpire.Nedderis still a northern English dialect form.Since Middle English the word has been restricted to use as the common name of the viper, the only poisonous British reptile (though not generally fatal to humans), then by extension it was applied to venomous or similar snakes elsewhere (puff-adder, etc.). Folklore connection with deafness is via Psalms lviii.1-5. The adder is said to stop up its ears to avoid hearing the snake charmer called in to drive it away."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addict",
    "response": "1530s (implied inaddicted) \"to devote or give up (oneself) to a habit or occupation,\" from Latinaddictus, past participle ofaddicere\"to deliver, award, yield; make over, sell,\" properly \"give one's assent to,\" but figuratively \"to devote, consecrate; sacrifice, sell out, betray, abandon.\" This is fromad\"to\" (seead-) +dicere, which was usually \"to say, declare\" (from PIE root*deik-\"to show,\" also \"pronounce solemnly\"), but also could be \"adjudge, allot.\"\"It is a yielding to impulse, and generally a bad one\" [Century Dictionary]. Old English glossed Latinaddictusliterally withforscrifen. Related:Addicted;addicting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addicted",
    "response": "1530s, \"delivered over\" by judicial sentence (as a debtor to his creditors, a sense from Roman law); past-participle adjective fromaddict(v.). The sense of \"dependent\" (1560s) is reflexive, \"self-addicted,\" from the notion of \"give over or award (oneself) to someone or some practice;\" specialization to narcotics dependency is from c. 1910. An earlier English adjective was simplyaddict\"delivered, devoted\" (1520s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addiction",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"tendency, inclination, penchant\" (a less severe sense now obsolete); 1640s as \"state of being (self)-addicted\" to a habit, pursuit, etc., from Latinaddictionem(nominativeaddictio) \"an awarding, a delivering up,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaddicere\"to deliver, award; devote, consecrate, sacrifice\" (seeaddict(v.)).The sense of \"compulsion and need to take a drug as a result of prior use of it\" is by 1906, in reference to opium (there is an isolated instance from 1779 with reference to tobacco)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "additament",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"anything added, an increase or increment,\" from Latinadditamentum\"an increase,\" from past-participle stem ofaddere\"to add\" (seeadd)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addition",
    "response": "late 14c., \"action of adding numbers;\" c. 1400, \"that which is added,\" from Old Frenchadition\"increase, augmentation\" (13c.), from Latinadditionem(nominativeadditio) \"an adding to, addition,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaddere\"add to, join, attach\" (seeadd). Phrasein addition to\"also\" is from 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "additional",
    "response": "1640s, \"added, supplementary,\" fromaddition+-al(1). Related:Additionally."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "additive",
    "response": "1690s, \"tending to be added,\" from Late Latinadditivus\"added, annexed,\" past-participle adjective from Latinaddere\"add to, join, attach\" (seeaddition). Alternativeaddititious\"additive, additional\" (1748) is from Latinadditicius\"additional.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addle",
    "response": "\"become putrid,\" hence \"be spoiled, be made worthless or ineffective,\" 1640s (implied inaddled), from archaicaddle(n.) \"urine, liquid filth,\" from Old Englishadela\"mud, mire, liquid manure\" (cognate with East Frisianadel\"dung,\" Old Swedishadel\"urine,\" Middle Low Germanadel\"mud,\" Dutchaal\"puddle\").Popularly used in the noun phraseaddle egg(mid-13c.) \"egg that does not hatch, rotten egg,\" a loan-translation of Latinovum urinum, literally \"urine egg,\" which is itself an erroneous loan-translation of Greekourion ōon\"putrid egg,\" literally \"wind egg,\" fromourios\"of the wind\" (confused by Roman writers withourios\"of urine,\" fromouron\"urine\").From this phrase, since c. 1600 the noun in English was mistaken as an adjective meaning \"putrid,\" and thence given a figurative extension to \"empty, vain, idle,\" also \"confused, muddled, unsound\" (1706), then back-formed into a verb in that sense. Related:Addling.Popular in forming derogatory compounds 17c. and after, such asaddle-headed\"stupid, muddled\" (1660s);addle-pated(1630s);addle-pate\"stupid bungler\" (c. 1600);addle-plot\"spoil-sport, person who spoils any amusement\" (1690s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "address",
    "response": "early 14c., \"to guide, aim, or direct,\" from Old Frenchadrecier\"go straight toward; straighten, set right; point, direct\" (13c.), from Vulgar Latin*addirectiare\"make straight\" (source also of Spanishaderezar, Italianaddirizzare), fromad\"to\" (seead-) +*directiare\"make straight,\" from Latindirectus\"straight, direct\" past participle ofdirigere\"set straight,\" fromdis-\"apart\" (seedis-) +regere\"to direct, to guide, keep straight\" (from PIE root*reg-\"move in a straight line\"). Comparedress(v.)).The oldest sense in English is preserved in the terminology of golf (toaddressa ball). The meaning \"direct for transmission, write as a destination on a message\" is from mid-15c. The meaning \"direct spoken words (to someone)\" is from late 15c. From late 14c. as \"to set in order, repair, correct.\" The attempt (falsely) re-Latinize the spelling toadd-began in France 15c. but failed there (the Modern French verb isadresser); it stuck in English. Related:Addressed;addressing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "addressee",
    "response": "\"one to whom anything is addressed,\" 1810; seeaddress(v.) +-ee."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adduce",
    "response": "\"to bring forward, present, or offer, cite as authority or evidence,\" early 15c.,adducen, from Latinadducere\"lead to, bring to, bring along,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ducere\"to lead\" (from PIE root*deuk-\"to lead\"). Related:Adduced;adducing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adduction",
    "response": "\"the act of drawing toward a common center or median line,\" 1650s, from Frenchadduction(16c.), from Medieval Latinadductionem(nominativeadductio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofadducere\"lead to, bring to\" (seeadduce). Related:Adduct;adductor;adductive."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adelaide",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from FrenchAdélaide, from a Germanic source similar to Old High GermanAdalhaid, fromadal\"noble family\" (seeatheling) + Germanheit\"state, rank,\" which is related to Old English-had\"person, degree, state, nature\" (see-hood). The first element of it affixed to French fem. ending-inegaveAdeline."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adeline",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from French, of Germanic origin, literally \"noblewoman,\" fromadal\"noble family\" (seeatheling) + French fem. suffix-ine(see-ine(1))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adelphi",
    "response": "district of London, so called because it was laid out c. 1768 and built by four brothers of a family named Adam; from Greekadelphos\"brother,\" literally \"from the same womb, co-uterine,\" from copulative prefixa-\"together with\" (seea-(3)) +delphys\"womb,\" which is perhaps related todolphin(q.v.). The district was the site of the popularAdelphitheater c. 1882-1900, which for a time gave its name to a style of performance."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adenine",
    "response": "crystalline base, 1885, coined by German physiologist/chemist Albrecht Kossel from Greekadēn\"gland\" (seeadeno-) + chemical suffix-ine(2). So called because it was derived from the pancreas of an ox."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adenoid",
    "response": "1839, \"gland-like,\" from medical Latinadenoideus, from Greekadenoeides, fromadēn(genitiveadēnos) \"gland\" (seeadeno-) +eidos\"form\" (see-oid).Adenoids(n.) \"adenoid growths\" is attested by 1856."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adenoidal",
    "response": "1852, \"gland-like, resembling a gland,\" fromadenoid+-al(1). From 1919 as \"having the appearance of one with adenoids.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adept",
    "response": "1690s, \"completely skilled, well-versed,\" from Latinadeptus\"having reached or attained,\" past participle ofadipisci\"to come up with, arrive at,\" figuratively \"to attain to, acquire,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +apisci\"to grasp, attain\" (related toaptus\"fitted,\" from PIE root*ap-(1) \"to take, reach,\" for which seeapt). Related:Adeptly;adeptness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adequacy",
    "response": "\"condition of being proportionate or sufficient; a sufficiency for a particular purpose,\" 1794; seeadequate+ abstract noun suffix-cy.Adequatenessis from 1670s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adequate",
    "response": "1610s, \"equal to what is needed or desired, sufficient,\" from Latinadaequatus\"equalized,\" past participle ofadaequare\"to make equal to, to level with,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +aequare\"make level,\" fromaequus\"equal, even\" (seeequal(adj.)).The sense is of being \"equal to what is required.\" It shares duty withenough, depending on the subject. Somewhat disparaging use, \"mediocre, just good enough,\" is by 1900. Related:Adequateness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adequately",
    "response": "1620s; seeadequate+-ly(2); originally a term in logic in reference to correspondence of ideas and objects and probably based on Latin use. Meaning \"suitably\" is recorded from 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adhere",
    "response": "1590s, from Frenchadhérer\"to stick, adhere\" (15c., corrected from earlieraderer, 14c.) or directly from Latinadhaerare\"to stick, cling to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +haerere\"to stick\" (seehesitation). Originally often of persons, \"to cleave to a leader, cause, party, etc.\" (compareadherent(n.), which still often retains this sense). Related:Adhered;adhering."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adherence",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"steady attachment of the mind or feelings to a person, cause, belief, etc.,\" from Old Frenchadhérence, from Medieval Latinadhaerentia, abstract noun from Latinadhaerent-, present participle stem ofadhaerare\"stick to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +haerere\"to stick\" (seehesitation). Rare in a physical sense,adhesionbeing the usual word for that."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adherent",
    "response": "late 14c., \"sticking, clinging to, adhesive,\" from Old Frenchadherentor directly from Latinadhaerentem(nominativeadhaerens), present participle ofadhaerere\"stick to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +haerere\"to stick\" (seehesitation)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adhesion",
    "response": "1620s, \"act or state of sticking or being stuck, a being united or attached,\" from Frenchadhésionor directly from Latinadhaesionem(nominativeadhaesio) \"a sticking to,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadhaerare\"to stick to, cling to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +haerere\"to stick\" (seehesitation). The earliest English use is of persons (\"faith is adhesion unto God\"), but by 18c.adhesionwas \"generally used in the material, andadherencein the metaphysical sense.\" [Johnson]"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adhesive",
    "response": "\"sticky, cleaving or clinging,\" 1660s, from Frenchadhésif, formed in French from Latinadhaes-, past-participle stem ofadhaerere\"stick to\" (seeadherent(adj.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adiabatic",
    "response": "\"without transference, impossible (to heat),\" 1838, with-ic+ Greekadiabatos\"not to be passed\" (of rivers, etc.), froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +diabatos\"to be crossed or passed, fordable,\" fromdia\"through\" (seedia-) +batos\"passable,\" frombainein\"to go, walk, step\" (from PIE root*gwa-\"to go, come\"). In thermodynamics, of a change in volume without change in heat."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adiaphorous",
    "response": "\"indifferent, non-essential, morally neither right nor wrong,\" 1630s, from Greekadiaphoros\"not different; indifferent,\" froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +diaphoros\"different.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adieu",
    "response": "late 14c.,adewe, from Old Frencha Dieu,a Deu, shortened from phrases such asa dieu (vous) commant\"I commend (you) to God,\" froma\"to\" (seead-) +dieu\"God,\" from Latindeum, accusative ofdeus\"god\" (from PIE*deiwos\"god\" (from root*dyeu-\"to shine\").Originally it was said to the party left (farewellwas to the party setting forth), but in English it came to be used as a general parting salutation. As a noun, \"expression of kind wishes upon departure,\" late 14c. Compare the native parting salutationgood-bye, a contraction ofGod be with ye."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adipose",
    "response": "\"pertaining to fat, fatty,\" 1743, from Modern Latinadiposus\"fatty,\" from Latinadipem(nominativeadeps, genitiveadipis) \"soft fat of animals, fat, lard,\" which is said to be from Greekaleipha\"unguent, fat, anything used for smearing,\" a word related tolipos\"grease, fat,\" from PIE root*leip-\"to stick, adhere,\" also used to form words for \"fat.\" With change of-l-to-d-\"prob. due to Umbrian influence\" [Klein]. But it could as well be a native Italic formation from the same roots."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adirondack",
    "response": "1906 in reference to a type of lawn or deck chair said to have been designed in 1903 by a Thomas Lee, owner of the Westport Mountain Spring, a resort in the Adirondack region of New York State. Commercial manufacture is said to have begin the following year but it was at first calledWestport chairafter the town where it was made.AdirondackMountainsis a back-formation fromAdirondacks, which was treated as a plural noun but really it is from Mohawk (Iroquoian)adiro:daks\"tree-eaters,\" a name they applied to neighboring Algonquian tribes. The-sis an imperfective affix."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adit",
    "response": "\"entrance,\" especially \"horizontal mine excavation,\" c. 1600, from Latinaditus\"an approach, an entrance; a going to or drawing near,\" from past participle stem ofadire\"to approach,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ire(past participleitus) \"to go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjacent",
    "response": "early 15c., \"contiguous, bordering; close, nearby,\" from Latinadiacentem(nominativeadiacens) \"lying at,\" present participle ofadiacere\"lie at, border upon, lie near,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iacēre\"to lie, rest,\" related toiacere\"to throw; to lay\" (from PIE root*ye-\"to throw, impel\"). Only of things, never of persons or animals.Adjacent, properly, is near but not necessarily in contact;adjoiningis so as to touch. Latinadiacentiameant \"the neighborhood.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjectival",
    "response": "\"of or like an adjective,\" 1797, fromadjective+-al(1). Related:Adjectivally(1773)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjective",
    "response": "\"word used to qualify, limit, or define a noun or noun-like part of speech,\" late 14c., short fornoun adjective, from Old Frenchadjectif(14c.), from Latinadjectivum\"that is added to (the noun),\" neuter ofadjectivus\"added,\" past participle ofadicere\"throw to, fling at, throw or place (a thing) near,\" especially \"add in addition, add by way of increase,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) + combining form ofiacere\"to throw\" (from PIE root*ye-\"to throw, impel\"). In Britain from at least 1851 the word often was a euphemism for the taboo adjectivebloody."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjoin",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"unite (something to something else), ally\" (a sense now obsolete); late 14c. as \"be contiguous with, be adjacent to,\" from Old Frenchajoin-stem ofajoindre\"join together, unite,\" from Latinadiungere\"fasten on, harness, join to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iungere\"to bind together\" (from a nasalized form of PIE root*yeug-\"to join\"). The meaning \"be contiguous with, be in contact with\" is from late 14c. The French word was Latinized 16c. to Modern Frenchadjoindre. Related:Adjoined;adjoining."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjourn",
    "response": "mid-14c.,ajournen, \"assign a day, fix a day\" (for convening or reconvening of an organized body), from Old Frenchajorner(12c.) \"meet\" (at an appointed time), from the phraseà jorn\"to another day, to a (stated) day,\" fromà\"to\" (seead-) +journ\"day,\" from Latindiurnus\"daily,\" fromdies\"day\" (from PIE root*dyeu-\"to shine\").The notion is of setting a date for re-meeting. The meaning \"close a meeting\" (with or without intention to reconvene) is from early 15c. The sense of \"go in a body to another place\" (1640s) is colloquial.The English word has had the-d-since 16c., but the spelling is unetymological, as the compound apparently is not from Latin; Middle French also occasionally hasadjourner, but this was rejected in Modern French. Related:Adjourned;adjourning."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjournment",
    "response": "mid-15c.,ajournement, \"act of postponing or deferring (a court, assembly, etc.),\" from Old Frenchajornement\"daybreak, dawn; summons (to appear in court),\" fromajorner(seeadjourn), with unetymological-d-added in English on the mistaken expectation of a Latin origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjudge",
    "response": "late 14c.,ajuge, \"to make a judicial decision, decide by judicial opinion,\" from Old Frenchajugier\"to judge, pass judgment on\" (Modern Frenchadjuger; the-d-was restored 14c. and English followed suit by 16c.), from Latinadiudicare\"grant or award as a judge,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iudicare\"to judge,\" which is related toiudicem\"a judge\" (seejudge(n.)). The sense of \"have an opinion\" is from c. 1400. Related:Adjudged;adjudging."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjudicate",
    "response": "\"pronounce judgement upon, reward judicially,\" 1700, a back-formation fromadjudication, or else from Latinadiudicatus, past participle ofadiudicare\"grant or award as a judge\" (seeadjudge). Related:Adjudicated;adjudicating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjudication",
    "response": "1690s, \"action of adjudging,\" from Frenchadjudicationor directly from Late Latinadiudicationem(nominativeadiudicatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofadiudicare\"grant or award as a judge\" (seeadjudge). By 1782 as \"a judicial settlement.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjudicative",
    "response": "\"involving or pertaining to adjudication,\" 1809; seeadjudicate+-ive. Perhaps modeled on Frenchadjudicatif. Especially in law, \"useful in determining the outcome of a case.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjudicator",
    "response": "\"one who adjudicates,\" 1804, agent noun in Latin form fromadjudicate."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjunct",
    "response": "1580s, \"something added to but not an essential part of (something else),\" from Latinadiunctus\"closely connected, joined, united\" (as a noun, \"a characteristic, essential attribute\"), past participle ofadiungere\"join to\" (seeadjoin)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjuration",
    "response": "late 14c., \"exorcism,\" from Late Latinadiurationem(nominativeadiuratio) \"a swearing to,\" noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinadiurare\"to put (someone) to an oath,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iurare\"swear,\" fromius(genitiveiuris) \"law,\" from PIE root*yewes-\"law\" (seejurist). Originally a term in exorcism (withconjuration); the general sense of \"a solemn oath, a charging under the penalty of a curse\" is from 17c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjure",
    "response": "late 14c.,adjuren, \"to bind by oath; to question under oath;\" c. 1400 as \"to charge with an oath or under penalty of a curse,\" from Latinadiurare\"confirm by oath, add an oath, to swear to in addition; call to witness,\" in Late Latin \"to put (someone) to an oath,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iurare\"swear,\" fromius(genitiveiuris) \"law\" (seejurist). Related:Adjured;adjuring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjust",
    "response": "late 14c.,ajusten, \"to correct, remedy,\" from Old Frenchajuster,ajoster\"add; assemble; calibrate, gauge, regulate,\" from Late Latinadiuxtare\"to bring near,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) + Latiniuxta\"next, close by\" (from suffixed form of PIE root*yeug-\"to join\").In 16c. French corrected toadjuster, but the pedantic effort was rejected and Modern French hasajouter. Influenced in form and sense by folk-etymology, as if fromad-+iustus\"just, equitable, fair.\"English reborrowed the word by c. 1600 in sense \"arrange, settle, compose,\" from Frenchadjuster\"fit (things together) properly, put things in order.\" The meaning \"arrange (something) so as to conform with (a standard or another thing)\" is from 1660s. The insurance sense is from 1755 (seeadjuster). Toadjust to\"get used to\" is attested by 1924. Related:Adjusted;adjusting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjustable",
    "response": "\"capable of being adjusted,\" 1775, fromadjust+-able. Related:Adjustably;adjustability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjuster",
    "response": "1670s, agent noun in English form fromadjust. The insurance sense of \"one who settles the amount to be paid for a claim under a policy, after making proper allowances and deductions,\" is from 1830."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjustment",
    "response": "\"a making fit or conformable; the act of adapting to a given purpose; orderly regulation or arrangement,\" 1640s, from Frenchajustement(Old Frenchajostement) or else a native formation fromadjust(v.) +-ment."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adjutant",
    "response": "\"military officer who assists superior officers,\" c. 1600, from Latinadiutantem(nominativeadiutans), present participle ofadiutare\"to give help to, help zealously, serve,\" frequentative ofadiuvare(past participleadiutus) \"help, assist, aid, support,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iuvare\"to help, give strength, support,\" which is perhaps from the same root asiuvenis\"young man\" (seeyoung(adj.)).Frenchadjudant, earlierajudant(early 18c.) is from Spanish cognateayudante. Related:Adjutancy. Theadjutant birdis the name given by the English in Bengal to a large type of Indian stork, so called for its \"stiff martinet air\" [Century Dictionary]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "administer",
    "response": "late 14c.,aministren, lateradministren, \"to manage as a steward, control or regulate on behalf of others,\" from Old Frenchaministrer\"help, aid, be of service to\" (12c., Modern Frenchadministrer), and directly from Latinadministrare\"to help, assist; manage, control, guide, superintend; rule, direct,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ministrare\"to serve, attend, wait upon,\" fromminister\"inferior, servant, priest's assistant\" (seeminister(n.)).The-d-was restored 14c.-16c. in French and after 15c. in English. In reference to punishment, justice, etc., \"to dispense, bring into operation\" (especially as an officer), from mid-15c. In reference to medicines, medical treatment, etc., \"to give,\" from 1540s. Related:Administered;administering."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "administrate",
    "response": "\"manage or direct affairs,\" 1630s, from Latinadministratus, past participle ofadministrare\"manage, control, superintend\" (seeadminister) or else a back-formation fromadministrator,administration. Related:Administrated;administrating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "administration",
    "response": "mid-14c.,administracioun, \"act of giving or dispensing;\" late 14c., \"management (of a business, property, etc.), act of administering,\" from Latinadministrationem(nominativeadministratio) \"aid, help, cooperation; direction, management,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadministrare\"to help, assist; manage, control, guide, superintend; rule, direct,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ministrare\"to serve, attend, wait upon,\" fromminister\"inferior, servant, priest's assistant\" (seeminister(n.)).It is attested by early 15c. as \"management of a deceased person's estate under a commission from authority.\" The sense of \"management of public affairs\" is from 1680s; hence, \"executive power in a government\" (1731), though in Britain latergovernmentwas used in this sense. The meaning \"a U.S. president's period in office\" is recorded by 1796 in the writings of George Washington."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "administrative",
    "response": "\"pertaining to administration, having to do with the managing of public affairs,\" 1731, from Latinadministrativus, fromadministrat-, past-participle stem ofadministrare\"to manage, control, superintend\" (seeadminister). Related:Administratively."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "administrator",
    "response": "\"one who has been given authority to manage,\" mid-15c.,administratour, from Old Frenchadministrateuror directly from Latinadministrator\"a manager, conductor,\" agent noun from past-participle stem ofadministrare\"to manage, control, superintend\" (seeadminister). The estate sense is earliest. For ending, see-er."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admirable",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"worthy of admiration,\" from Latinadmirabilis\"admirable, wonderful,\" fromadmirari\"to admire\" (seeadmire). In early years it also carried a stronger sense of \"awe-inspiring, marvelous.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admirably",
    "response": "\"in a manner to excite approbation and esteem,\" 1590s, fromadmirable+-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admiral",
    "response": "c. 1200,amiral,admirail, \"Saracen commander or chieftain,\" from Old Frenchamirail(12c.) \"Saracen military commander; any military commander,\" ultimately from medieval Arabicamir\"military commander,\" probably via Medieval Latin use of the word for \"Muslim military leader.\"Amiral de la mer\"commander of a fleet of ships\" is in late 13c. Anglo-French documents. Meaning \"highest-ranking naval officer\" in English is from early 15c. The extension of the word's meaning from \"commander on land\" to \"commander at sea\" likely began in 12c. Sicily with Medieval Latinamiratusand then spread to the continent, but the word also continued to mean \"Muslim military commander\" in Europe in the Middle Ages. The Arabic word was later Englished asemir.Also in Old French and Middle English the word was further conformed to familiar patterns asamirauld,amiraunt. The unetymological-d-probably is from influence of Latinad-mirabilis(seeadmire). Italian formalmiraglio, Spanishalmiranteare from confusion with Arabic words inal-. As the name of a type of butterfly from 1720, according to OED possibly a corruption ofadmirable."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admiralship",
    "response": "\"office or position of an admiral,\" 1610s, fromadmiral+-ship."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admiralty",
    "response": "\"naval branch of the English executive,\" early 15c.,admiralte, from Old Frenchamiralte, fromamirail(seeadmiral)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admiration",
    "response": "early 15c., \"wonder,\" from Old Frenchadmiration\"astonishment, surprise\" (14c., corrected from earlieramiracion), or directly from Latinadmirationem(nominativeadmiratio) \"a wondering at, admiration,\" noun of state from past-participle stem ofadmirari\"regard with wonder, be astonished,\" fromad\"to; with regard to\" (seead-) +mirari\"to wonder,\" frommirus\"wonderful\" (seemiracle). The sense has gradually weakened since 16c. toward \"high regard, esteem.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admire",
    "response": "early 15c. (implied inadmired), \"regard with wonder, marvel at,\" from Old Frenchadmirer\"look upon, contemplate\" (correcting earlieramirer, 14c.), or directly from Latinadmirari\"regard with wonder, be astonished,\" fromad\"to, with regard to\" (seead-) +mirari\"to wonder,\" frommirus\"wonderful\" (seesmile(v.)). The sense has gradually weakened toward \"regard with pleasure and esteem,\" but for a time they overlapped.Related:Admiring;admiringly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admirer",
    "response": "\"one who admires,\" c. 1600, agent noun fromadmire(v.). From 1704 in the colloquial sense of \"one who pays court to (a woman), a lover.\" The Latin agent noun wasadmirator."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admissibility",
    "response": "\"quality of being admissible,\" 1763, fromadmissible+-ity. Perhaps modeled on Frenchadmissibilité(by 1670s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admissible",
    "response": "1610s, \"allowable,\" from Frenchadmissible, from past-participle stem of Latinadmittere\"allow to enter, admit, give entrance,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +mittere\"let go, send\" (seemission). The meaning \"capable of being allowed entrance\" is from 1775; the specific sense of \"capable of being used in a legal decision or judicial investigation\" is by 1849."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admission",
    "response": "early 15c., \"acceptance, reception, approval,\" from Latinadmissionem(nominativeadmissio) \"a letting in,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadmittere\"admit, give entrance; grant an audience,\" of acts, \"let be done, allow, permit,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +mittere\"let go, send\" (seemission).The meaning \"an acknowledging\" is from 1530s. The literal sense of \"act of allowing to enter, admittance,\" is from 1620s. As short foradmission price, by 1792."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admit",
    "response": "late 14c.,admitten, \"let in,\" from Latinadmittere\"admit, give entrance, allow to enter; grant an audience,\" of acts, \"let be done, allow, permit,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +mittere\"let go, send\" (seemission).The sense of \"concede in argument as valid or true\" is recorded by early 15c. In Middle English the word sometimes also wasamit, after Old Frenchamettre, which was refashioned 15c. Related:Admitted;Admitting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admittance",
    "response": "1580s, \"the action of admitting,\" formed in English fromadmit+-ance(if from Latin, it would have been*admittence; French usesaccèsin this sense). Used formerly in figurative senses whereadmissionnow prevails.Admissurewas used in this sense from mid-15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admitted",
    "response": "1550s, \"received,\" past-participle adjective fromadmit(v.). As \"received as true or valid\" from 1780 (implied inadmittedly)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admix",
    "response": "\"mingle\" (something, with something else), 1530s, a back-formed verb; seeadmixture. Related:Admixing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admixture",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"act of mingling,\" with-ure+admix(1530s), a back-formed verb fromadmixt\"mingled\" (early 15c.), a past-participle adjective from Latinadmixtus\"mixed with,\" past participle ofadmiscere\"to add to by mingling, mix with,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +miscere\"to mix\" (from PIE root*meik-\"to mix\"). In Middle Englishadmixtwas mistaken as the past participle of a (then) non-existent*admix. The earlier noun wasadmixtion(late 14c., from Latinadmixionem)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admonish",
    "response": "mid-14c.,amonesten\"remind, urge, exhort, warn, give warning,\" from Old Frenchamonester\"urge, encourage, warn\" (12c.), from Vulgar Latin*admonestare, from Latinadmonere\"bring to mind, remind (of a debt);\" also \"warn, advise, urge,\" fromad\"to,\" here probably with frequentative force (seead-) +monere\"to admonish, warn, advise,\" from PIE*moneie-\"to make think of, remind,\" suffixed (causative) form of root*men-(1) \"to think.\"The-d-was restored, on the Latin model, in English as in French (Modern Frenchadmonester). The ending was influenced by words in-ish(such asastonish,abolish). Related:Admonished;admonishing. Latin also hadcommonere\"to remind,\"promonere\"to warn openly,\"submonere\"to advise privately\" (source ofsummon)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admonition",
    "response": "late 14c.,amonicioun\"reminding, instruction,\" from Old Frenchamonicion\"admonition, exhortation,\" from Latinadmonitionem(nominativeadmonitio) \"a suggestion, a reminding; an admonition,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadmonere\"to advise, warn\" (seeadmonish).The-d-was restored in French, then (17c.) in English. The meaning \"caution or warning about future conduct based on past failures\" is by early 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "admonitory",
    "response": "\"containing an admonition,\" 1590s, from Late Latinadmonitorius, from Latinadmonit-, past-participle stem ofadmonere\"to advise; to warn\" (seeadmonish). Related:Admonitorily;admonitorial."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ado",
    "response": "late 14c., \"conflict, fighting; difficulty, trouble,\" a contraction ofatdo, literally \"to do,\" a dialectal formation in the Norse-influenced areas of northern England: some Scandinavian languages usedatwith the infinitive of a verb where Modern English usesto.From use of the infinitive inmuch ado(\"much to do\") and similar phrases,adocame to be regarded as a noun. Compare the sense evolution into-doandaffair(from French infinitive phraseà faire\"to do\"). The weakened meaning \"fuss\" is from early 15c. Also used in Middle English for \"dealings, traffic,\" and \"sexual intercourse\" (both c. 1400)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adobe",
    "response": "\"mudbrick,\" 1739, American English, from Spanishadobe\"unburnt brick dried in the sun,\" which is said by 19c. Dutch Arabist Reinhart Dozy to be from oral form of Arabical-tob\"the brick,\" from Coptictube\"brick,\" a word found in hieroglyphics. Other sources point to a Spanishadobar\"daub, plaster,\" from the source of Englishdaub(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adolescence",
    "response": "\"the age following childhood, the age of growing\" (roughly the period from the 15th to the 21st year; or age 14 to 25 in males, 12 to 21 in females), early 15c., from Old Frenchadolescence(13c.), from Latinadolescentia/adulescentia\"youth, youthful people collectively,\" abstract noun fromadulescentem\"growing, youthful\" (seeadolescent(n.)).Adolescency(late 14c.) is slightly earlier."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adolescent",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"youth, young person, one who is growing up,\" from Frenchadolescent(15c.) or directly from Latinadolescentem/adulescentem(nominativeadolescens/adulescens) \"young man or woman, a youth,\" noun use of an adjective meaning \"growing, near maturity, youthful.\" The adjective is the present participle ofadolescere\"grow up, come to maturity, ripen,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +alescere\"be nourished,\" hence, \"increase, grow up\" (inchoative ofalere\"to nourish,\" from a suffixed form of PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\").Adolescewas a back-formed verb used early 20c. (OED quotes H.G. Wells, G.B. Shaw, Louis MacNeice), but it seems not to have grown."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adolph",
    "response": "alsoAdolf, masc. proper name, German, from Old High GermanAthalwolf, etymologically \"noble wolf,\" fromathal\"noble\" (seeatheling) +wolf(seewolf(n.)). The-phis from the Latinized form of the name,Adolphus."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adonai",
    "response": "Old Testament word for \"God,\" used as a substitute for the ineffable name, late 14c., from Medieval Latin, from Hebrew, literally \"my lord,\" fromadon(seeAdonis) + suffix of the first person."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adonis",
    "response": "\"beautiful young man,\" 1620s, probably via FrenchAdonis(15c.), from GreekAdōnis, name of the youth beloved by Aphrodite, from Phoenicianadon\"lord,\" probably originally \"ruler,\" from basea-d-n\"to judge, rule.\"Adonaiis the Hebrew cognate."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adopt",
    "response": "\"take to one's self, make one's own by selection,\" c. 1500, a back-formation fromadoptionor else from Old Frenchadopter(14c.) or directly from Latinadoptare\"chose for oneself, take by choice, select, adopt,\" especially \"to take into a family, adopt as a child,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +optare\"choose, wish, desire\" (seeoption(n.)).Originally in English of friends, fathers, citizens, etc., as well as children. The specific sense of \"to legally take as one's own child\" and that of \"to embrace, espouse\" a practice, method, etc. are from c. 1600. Related:Adopted;adopting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adoptee",
    "response": "\"one who is adopted,\" 1849; seeadopt(v.) +-ee."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adopter",
    "response": "\"one who adopts\" in any sense, 1570s, agent noun fromadopt(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adoption",
    "response": "mid-14c.,adopcioun, \"action of taking (a child) as one's own; condition of being adopted,\" from Old Frenchadopcionor directly from Late Latinadoptionem(nominativeadoptio) \"a taking as one's child,\" shorter form ofadoptatio, noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinadoptare\"chose for oneself, take by choice, select, adopt,\" especially \"to take into a family, adopt as a child,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +optare\"choose, wish, desire\" (from PIE root*op-(2) \"to choose;\" seeoption(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adoptive",
    "response": "early 15c.,adpotif, \"by adoption,\" from Old Frenchadoptifand directly from Latinadoptivus\"pertaining to adoption,\" from stem ofadoptere\"to choose, adopt\" (seeadopt)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adorable",
    "response": "1610s, \"worthy of worship,\" from Frenchadorable, from Latinadorabilis\"worthy of worship,\" fromadorare\"to worship\" (seeadore). The weakened sense of \"delightful, charming\" is recorded from 1710. Related:Adorably;adorableness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adoration",
    "response": "1540s, \"act of paying divine honors,\" from Frenchadoration, from Late Latinadorationem(nominativeadoratio) \"worship, adoration,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadorare\"to worship.\" Seeadore, the original sense of which is preserved in this word."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adore",
    "response": "late 14c.,aouren, \"to worship, pay divine honors to, bow down before,\" from Old Frenchaorer\"to adore, worship, praise\" (10c., lateradorer), from Latinadorare\"speak to formally, beseech, entreat, ask in prayer,\" in Late Latin \"to worship,\" literally \"to call to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ōrare\"speak formally, pray\" (seeorator).The meaning \"to honor very highly\" is attested from 1590s; the weakened sense of \"to be very fond of\" emerged by 1880s. Related:Adored;adoring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adorn",
    "response": "late 14c.,aournen, lateradornen, \"to decorate, embellish,\" also \"be an ornament to,\" from Old Frenchaorner\"to order, arrange, dispose, equip; adorn,\" from Latinadornare\"equip, provide, furnish;\" also \"decorate, embellish,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ornare\"prepare, furnish, adorn, fit out,\" from stem ofordo\"row, rank, series, arrangement\" (seeorder(n.)). The-d-was reinserted by French scribes 14c. and spread to English from late 15c. Related:Adorned;adorning."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adornment",
    "response": "late 14c.,adornement, \"act of adorning;\" also \"a thing which adorns;\" from Old Frenchaornement\"ornament, decoration,\" fromaorner(seeadorn)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adown",
    "response": "\"to a lower place,\" Old Englishadune(adv.), originally a prepositional phrase,of dune\"down, downward;\" seea-(1) +down(adv.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adrenal",
    "response": "\"of or near the kidneys,\" 1866, Modern Latin, fromad-\"to, near\" +renalis\"of the kidneys,\" from Latinrenes\"kidneys\" (seerenal).Adrenal glandis from 1875."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adrenaline",
    "response": "alsoAdrenalin(trademark name), coined 1901 by Japanese chemist Jokichi Takamine (1853-1922), who discovered it, from Modern Latinadrenal(seeadrenal) + chemical suffix-ine(2).Adrenaline rushwas in use c. 1970."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adrian",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from LatinAdrianus, properlyHadrianus, literally \"of the Adriatic\" (seeAdriatic). A name taken by several popes, including the only English pontiff, Nicholas Brakespear (died 1159). The proper nameAdrienne, etc., when not a fem. form of this, is a transposition ofAriadne:Adrianeis the usual form ofAriadnein Chaucer (\"House of Fame,\" etc.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adriatic",
    "response": "sea east of Italy, from LatinAdriaticus, properlyHadriaticus, from town ofAtria/Hatria(modernAdria) in Picenum, near Venice, once a seaport but now more than 12 miles inland. The name is perhaps fromatra, neuter ofatrum\"black,\" hence \"the black city;\" or else it represents Illyrianadur\"water, sea.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adrift",
    "response": "\"floating at random, at the mercy of currents,\" 1620s, froma-(1) \"on\" +drift(n.). Figurative use by 1680s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adroit",
    "response": "1650s, \"dexterous,\" originally \"rightly,\" from Frenchadroit, which by Old French had senses \"upright (physically and morally); able, clever, skillful; well-formed, handsome; on the right-hand side; veritable,\" from adverbial phraseà droit\"according to right.\"This is from Old Frenchà\"to\" (seead-) +droit,dreit\"right,\" from Medieval Latindirectum(contracteddrictum) \"right, justice, law,\" neuter or accusative of Latindirectus\"straight,\" past participle ofdirigere\"set straight,\" fromdis-\"apart\" (seedis-) +regere\"to direct, to guide, keep straight\" (from PIE root*reg-\"move in a straight line,\" with derivatives meaning \"to direct in a straight line,\" thus \"to lead, rule\"). It expresses prominently the idea of a trained hand. Related:Adroitly;adroitness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adsorb",
    "response": "1882, transitive (intransitive use attested from 1919), back-formation fromadsorption\"condensation of gases on the surfaces of solids\" (1882), coined in German fromad-+-sorption, abstracted fromabsorptionand representing Latinsorbere\"to suck\" (seeabsorb). Related:Adsorbent;adsorption."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulate",
    "response": "\"flatter slavishly,\" 1777, a back-formation fromadulation. Related:Adulated;adulating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulation",
    "response": "\"servile or insincere praise,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchadulacion, from Latinadulationem(nominativeadulatio) \"a fawning; flattery, cringing courtesy,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadulari\"to flatter, fawn upon.\"This is usually said to be fromad\"to\" (seead-) + a stem meaning \"tail,\" from a PIE*ul-\"the tail\" (source also of Sanskritvalah\"tail-hair,\" and Lithuanianvalai\"horse's tail\"). The original notion would be \"to wag the tail\" like a fawning dog (compare Greeksainein\"to wag the tail,\" also \"to flatter;\" also seewheedle).But de Vaan finds phonetic problems with these and concludes the etymology is uncertain, though he proposes a connection withavidus\"eager,\" via*adulo-\"who is eager toward something,\" hence \"a flatterer.\" Adulation may proceed from true blind worship or be insincere, from hope of advantage."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adult",
    "response": "1530s (but not common until mid-17c.) \"grown, mature,\" from Latinadultus\"grown up, mature, adult, ripe,\" past participle ofadolescere\"grow up, come to maturity, ripen,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +alescere\"be nourished,\" hence, \"increase, grow up,\" inchoative ofalere\"to nourish,\" from a suffixed form of PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish.\"The meaning \"mature in attitude or outlook\" is from 1929. As a euphemism for \"pornographic,\" it dates to 1958 and does no honor to the word. In the old British film-rating system,Aindicated \"suitable for exhibit to adult audiences,\" and thus, implicitly, unsuitable for children (1914)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulterant",
    "response": "\"that which adulterates,\" 1735, from Latinadulterantem(nominativeadulterans), present participle ofadulterare(seeadulteration)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulterate",
    "response": "\"debase by mixing with foreign or inferior material, make corrupt,\" 1530s, back-formation fromadulteration, or else from Latinadulteratus, past participle ofadulterare\"to falsify, corrupt,\" also \"to commit adultery.\" An earlier verb wasadulter(late 14c. in the sense \"make impure\"), directly from the Latin verb, but this English verb also carried the meaning \"commit adultery.\" Related:Adulterated;adulterating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulteration",
    "response": "c. 1500, \"act of adulterating; state of being debased by mixture with something else,\" generally of inferior quality, from Latinadulterationem(nominativeadulteratio) \"an adulteration, sophistication,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadulterare\"corrupt, falsify; debauch; commit adultery,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +alterare\"to alter\" (seealter), though Watkins explains it asad alterum\"(approaching) another (unlawfully).\" Meaning \"a result of adulterating\" is from 1650s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulterer",
    "response": "early 15c., agent noun from obsolete verbadulter\"commit adultery; adulterate, make impure, pollute\" (late 14c.), from Latinadulterare\"to corrupt\" (seeadulteration). The earlier form in Middle English wasavouter(c. 1300),avoutrer(late 14c.), \"person (usually a man) guilty of adultery,\" from Old Frenchavoutrier, from the Latin verb, or from Latinadulter\"adulterer, seducer,\" noun use of an adjective."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulteress",
    "response": "alsoadultress, \"woman guilty of adultery,\" an early 17c. substitution for earlieravoutresse(late 14c.), agent noun in fem. form from obsolete verbadulter\"commit adultery\" (seeadulterer), with fem. ending-ess."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulterous",
    "response": "\"pertaining to or given to adultery; illicit,\" c. 1600, a classical correction (replacing earlieravoutrious\"addicted to adultery,\" c. 1400), from obsolete verbadulter(seeadulterer) +-ous. Related:Adulterously.Adulterine(1640s, from Latinadulterinus) was used in the sense \"pertaining to adultery, born of adultery.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adultery",
    "response": "\"voluntary violation of the marriage bed,\" c. 1300,avoutrie, from Old Frenchavouterie(12c., lateradulterie, Modern Frenchadultĕre), noun of condition fromavoutre, from Latinadulterare\"commit adultery; corrupt,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +alterare\"to alter\" (seealter). Compareadulteration. The spelling was corrected toward Latin from early 15c. in English, following French (seead-).In Middle English, also \"sex between husband and wife for recreational purposes; idolatry, perversion, heresy.\" As a crime, formerly classified assingle adultery(with an unmarried person) anddouble adultery(with a married person). The Old English word wasæwbryce\"breach of law(ful marriage)\" (similar formation in GermanEhebruch). In translations of the 7th Commandment it is understood to mean \"lewdness or unchastity\" of any kind, in act or thought."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adulthood",
    "response": "\"state or condition of being an adult,\" 1850, fromadult(adj.) +-hood.Adultnessis attested from 1731."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adumbrate",
    "response": "1580s, \"to outline, to sketch,\" from Latinadumbratus\"sketched, shadowed in outline,\" also \"feigned, unreal, sham, fictitious,\" past participle ofadumbrare\"cast a shadow over;\" in painting, \"to represent (a thing) in outline,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +umbrare\"to cast in shadow\" (from PIE root*andho-\"blind; dark;\" seeumbrage). The meaning \"overshadow\" is from 1660s in English. Related:Adumbrated;adumbrating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adumbration",
    "response": "1550s, \"faint sketch, imperfect representation,\" from Latinadumbrationem(nominativeadumbratio) \"a sketch in shadow, sketch, outline,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadumbrare\"to cast a shadow, overshadow,\" in painting, \"represent (a thing) in outline,\" fromad-\"to\" (seead-) +umbrare\"to cast in shadow\" (from PIE root*andho-\"blind; dark;\" seeumbrage)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advance",
    "response": "mid-13c.,avauncen(transitive), \"improve (something), further the development of,\" from Old Frenchavancir,avancier\"move forward, go forward, set forward\" (12c., Modern Frenchavancer), from Vulgar Latin*abanteare(source of Italianavanzare, Spanishavanzar). This is from Late Latinabante\"from before,\" composed ofab\"from\" (seeab-) +ante\"before, in front of, against\" (from PIE root*ant-\"front, forehead\").Compare Frenchavant\"before\" (as inavant-garde), which is from the same Late Latin word. The unetymological-d-in English was inserted 16c. on the mistaken notion that initial syllable was from Latinad-.It is attested from c. 1300 as \"to promote, raise to a higher rank.\" The intransitive sense of \"move forward, move further in front\" is by mid-14c.; the transitive meaning \"bring forward in place, move (something) forward\" is from c. 1500. The meaning \"give (money, etc.) before it is legally due\" is attested by 1670s. Related:Advanced;advancing. The adjective (inadvance warning, etc.) is recorded from 1843."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advanced",
    "response": "1530s, \"far ahead in the course of actions or ideas; being beyond others in attainment, degree, etc.,\" past-participle adjective fromadvance(v.). Of studies, from 1790. Of age, by 1713. In late 19c. used especially in reference to views on women's equality."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advancement",
    "response": "c. 1300,avauncement, \"a raising to a higher rank,\" also \"promotion, assistance,\" from Old Frenchavancement\"advancement; profit, advance payment,\" fromavancir\"move forward\" (seeadvance(v.)). The unetymological-d-is from 16c. The meaning \"act of helping to move something forward\" is from 1550s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advantage",
    "response": "early 14c.,avantage, \"position of being in advance of another,\" from Old Frenchavantage\"advantage, profit; superiority\" (12c.), fromavant\"before,\" probably via an unrecorded Late or Medieval Latin*abantaticum, from Latinabante\"from before,\" composed ofab\"from\" (seeab-) +ante\"before, in front of, against\" (from PIE root*ant-\"front, forehead\"). Compareadvance(v.).The unetymological-d-is a 16c. intrusion on the analogy of the many Latinad-words in English. The meaning \"any condition favorable to success, a favoring circumstance\" (the opposite of adisadvantage) is from late 15c. The tennis score sense is from 1640s (in the writings of John Milton). Phrasetake advantage ofis from late 14c. as \"avail oneself of,\" also \"impose upon.\" Tohave the advantage of(someone) \"have superiority over\" is from 1560s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advantageous",
    "response": "1590s, \"furnishing advantages,\" formed in English fromadvantage+-ouson the model of Frenchavantageux(15c.). Related:Advantageously;advantageousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Advent",
    "response": "\"important arrival,\" 1742, an extended sense ofAdvent\"season preceding Christmas\" (in reference to the \"coming\" of Christ), which was in late Old English, from Latinadventus\"a coming, approach, arrival,\" in Church Latin \"the coming of the Savior,\" from past participle ofadvenire\"arrive at, come to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +venire\"to come\" (from a suffixed form of PIE root*gwa-\"to go, come\"). Related:Adventual."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Adventist",
    "response": "\"one of a religious denomination that believes in or looks for the early second coming of Christ to establish a personal reign,\" 1843; seeadvent+-ist. In Church Latinadventuswas applied to the coming of the Savior, both the first or the anticipated second, henceAdventistwas applied to millenarian sects, especially and originally the Millerites (U.S.). By the end of the 19c. there were three main divisions of them; theSeventh-Day Adventists(by 1860, seeseventh) were so called for their observation of Saturday as the Sabbath."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adventitious",
    "response": "\"of the nature of an addition from without, not from the essence of the subject; accidentally or casually acquired,\" c. 1600, from Medieval Latinadventitius\"coming from abroad, extraneous,\" a corruption of Latinadventicius\"foreign, strange, accidental,\" fromadvent-past-participle stem ofadvenire\"to arrive at, reach, come to\" (seeadvent). Related:Adventitiously;adventitiousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adventure",
    "response": "c. 1200,aventure,auenture\"that which happens by chance, fortune, luck,\" from Old Frenchaventure(11c.) \"chance, accident, occurrence, event, happening,\" from Latinadventura (res)\"(a thing) about to happen,\" from fem. ofadventurus, future participle ofadvenire\"to come to, reach, arrive at.\" This is fromad\"to\" (seead-) +venire\"to come\" (from a suffixed form of PIE root*gwa-\"to go, come\").The meaning developed through \"risk; danger\" (a trial of one's chances), c. 1300, and \"perilous undertaking\" (late 14c.) to \"novel or exciting incident, remarkable occurrence in one's life\" (1560s).Earlier it also meant \"a wonder, a miracle; accounts of marvelous things\" (13c.). The-d-was restored in English 15c.-16c.; in French the attempt to restore it at about the same time was rejected.Ventureis a 15c. variant. GermanAbenteueris a borrowing of the French word, apparently deformed whimsically by influence ofAbend\"evening.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adventurer",
    "response": "late 15c., \"one who plays at games of chance,\" agent noun fromadventure(v.). The meaning \"one who undertakes commercial ventures\" is from c. 1600. The meaning \"one who seeks adventures\" is from 1660s. It often is used in a bad sense, \"seeker of fortune by rash or underhanded means;\" henceadventurism(1843, in early 20c. a term in communist jargon). Fem. formadventuressattested by 1754."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adventuresome",
    "response": "1731, \"bold, daring,\" fromadventure+-some(1). Related:Adventuresomeness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adventurous",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"hazardous;\" late 14c., \"occurring by chance\" (senses now obsolete), from Old Frenchaventuros\"chance, accidental, fortuitous;\" of persons, \"devoted to adventure\" (Modern Frenchaventureux), fromaventure(seeadventure(n.)). In English the sense of \"rash, risk-taking\" is from c. 1400, thence \"daring, fond of adventure\" (mid-15c.). Related:Adventurously;adventurousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adverb",
    "response": "\"one of the indeclinable parts of speech, so called from being ordinarily joined to verbs for the purpose of limiting or extending their signification, but used also to qualify adjectives and other adverbs\" [Century Dictionary], late 14c., from Late Latinadverbium\"adverb,\" literally \"that which is added to a verb\" (to extend or limit its meaning), fromad\"to\" (seead-) +verbum\"verb, word\" (from PIE root*were-(3) \"to speak;\" seeverb). Coined by Flavius Sosipater Charisius as a translation of Greekepirrhema\"adverb,\" fromepi-\"upon, on\" +rhema\"verb.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adverbial",
    "response": "1610s, \"pertaining to adverbs;\" earlier it meant \"fond of using adverbs\" (1590s), from Late Latinadverbialis, fromadverbium\"an adverb\" (seeadverb). Related:Adverbially(mid-15c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adversary",
    "response": "\"unfriendly opponent, enemy\" (originally especially of Satan as the enemy of mankind), mid-14c.,aduersere, from Anglo-Frenchadverser(13c.), Old Frenchadversarie(12c., Modern Frenchadversaire) \"hostile opponent, enemy,\" or directly from Latinadversarius\"an opponent, rival, enemy,\" noun use of adjective meaning \"opposite, hostile, contrary,\" literally \"turned toward one,\" fromadversus\"turned against, turned toward, fronting, facing,\" figuratively \"hostile, adverse, unfavorable,\" past participle ofadvertere\"to turn toward,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +vertere\"to turn, turn back, be turned; convert, transform, translate; be changed\" (seeversus). The Latin word is glossed in Old English bywiðerbroca."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adverse",
    "response": "late 14c., \"contrary, opposing,\" from Old Frenchadvers, earlieravers(13c., Modern Frenchadverse) \"antagonistic, unfriendly, contrary, foreign\" (as ingent avers\"infidel race\"), from Latinadversus\"turned against, turned toward, fronting, facing,\" figuratively \"hostile, adverse, unfavorable,\" past participle ofadvertere\"to turn toward,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +vertere\"to turn, turn back; be turned; convert, transform, translate; be changed\" (from PIE root*wer-(2) \"to turn, bend\"). For distinction of use, seeaverse. Related:Adversely."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adversity",
    "response": "c. 1200,aduersite\"condition of misfortune, hardship, difficulty, distress,\" from Old Frenchadversite,aversite\"adversity, calamity, misfortune; hostility, wickedness, malice\" (Modern Frenchadversité), from Latinadversitatem(nominativeadversitas) \"opposition,\" fromadversus\"turned against, hostile\" (seeadverse)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advert",
    "response": "mid-15c.,averten\"to turn (something) aside\" (the mind, the attention, etc.), from Old Frenchavertir(lateradvertir) \"to turn, direct; turn aside; make aware, inform\" (12c.), from Latinadvertere\"turn toward, turn to,\" fromad\"toward\" (seead-) +vertere\"to turn\" (seeversus). The-d-was restored in English 16c. Especially in speaking or writing, \"turn to (a topic) abruptly and plainly\" (18c.). Related:Adverted;adverting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advertence",
    "response": "late 14c., \"attention, heed, act of calling attention to,\" from Old Frenchavertence,avertance, from Late Latinadvertentia\"attention, notice,\" abstract noun from past participle stem ofadvertere\"direct one's attention to; give heed,\" literally \"to turn toward\" (seeadvertise)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advertise",
    "response": "early 15c.,advertisen, \"to take notice of\" (a sense now obsolete), from Old Frenchadvertiss-, present-participle stem ofadvertir(earlieravertir) \"make aware, call attention, remark; turn, turn to\" (12c.), from Latinadvertere\"to direct one's attention to; give heed,\" literally \"to turn toward,\" fromad\"to, toward\" (seead-) +vertere\"to turn\" (seeversus).The transitive sense of \"give notice to others, inform, warn; make clear or manifest\" (mid-15c.) is by influence ofadvertisement; the specific commercial meaning \"call attention to goods for sale, rewards, etc.\" emerged by late 18c. Compareadvert(v.) \"turn (someone's) attention to.\"  Related:Advertised;advertising."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advertisement",
    "response": "early 15c., \"written statement calling attention to (something), public notice\" (of anything, but often of a sale); from Old Frenchavertissement(15c., later respelled pedantically asadvertissement, a change rejected in French but accepted in English), from stem ofavertir\"to turn, direct, make aware\" (seeadvertise). Meaning \"public notice (usually paid) in a newspaper or other publication,\" the main modern sense, emerged 1580s and was fully developed by 18c.; later extended to Web sites."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advertiser",
    "response": "1560s, \"one who notifies,\" agent noun fromadvertise(v.). From 1712 as \"one who issues public notice,\" hence its use as a name for newspapers or journals (1769)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advice",
    "response": "late 13c.,auys\"opinion,\" from Old Frenchavis\"opinion, view, judgment, idea\" (13c.), from phraseço m'est à vis\"it seems to me,\" or from Vulgar Latin*mi est visum\"in my view,\" ultimately from Latinvisum, neuter past participle ofvidere\"to see\" (from PIE root*weid-\"to see\"). Meaning \"opinion offered as worthy to be followed, counsel\" is from late 14c.The unetymological-d-(on model of Latin words inad-) was inserted occasionally in French by scribes 14c.-16c. and was made regular in English 15c. by Caxton. Substitution of-c-for-s-is 18c., to preserve the breath sound and to distinguish fromadvise. Early Modern English tended to alternate-ceand-seendings in otherwise confusable noun-verb pairs, using-sefor the verb and-cefor the noun:devise/device, peace/appease, practice/practise, license/licence, prophecy/prophesy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advisability",
    "response": "\"quality of being advisable or expedient,\" 1778 (in a letter from George Washington at Valley Forge), fromadvisable+-ity.Advisablenessis from 1731."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advisable",
    "response": "1640s, \"\"prudent, expedient, proper to be advised,\" fromadvise(v.) +-able(q.v.). It also can mean \"open to advice\" (1660s), but this is rare."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advise",
    "response": "late 13c.,avisen\"to view, consider\" (a sense now obsolete); late 14c., \"to give counsel to,\" from Old Frenchaviser\"deliberate, reflect, consider\" (13c.), fromavis\"opinion,\" from phraseço m'est à vis\"it seems to me,\" or from Vulgar Latin*mi est visum\"in my view,\" ultimately from Latinvisum, neuter past participle ofvidere\"to see\" (from PIE root*weid-\"to see\"). The unetymological-d-is from 16c. Related:Advised;advising."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advisement",
    "response": "early 14c.,avisement,\"examination, inspection, observation,\" from Old Frenchavisement\"consideration, reflection; counsel, advice,\" fromaviser\"deliberate, reflect, consider,\" fromavis\"opinion\" (seeadvice). The meaning \"advice, counsel\" is from c. 1400, as is that of \"consultation, conference,\" now obsolete except in the legalese phraseunder advisement. The unetymological-d-is a 16c. scribal overcorrection."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adviser",
    "response": "1610s, \"one who gives advice,\" agent noun fromadvise(v.). The meaning \"faculty assigned to mentor students\" is from 1887. The meaning \"military person sent to help a government or army in a foreign country\" is recorded from 1915. Alternative form, Latinateadvisor, is perhaps a back-formation fromadvisory."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advisory",
    "response": "1778, \"having the power to advise;\" seeadvise+-ory. The noun meaning \"weather warning\" is from 1936, used by U.S. agencies, probably short foradvisory bulletin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advocacy",
    "response": "\"the act of pleading for, supporting, or recommending,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchavocacie\"profession of anavocat\" (14c.), from Medieval Latinadvocatia, abstract noun from Latinadvocat-, stem ofadvocare\"to call, summon, invite\" (seeadvocate(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advocate",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"one whose profession is to plead cases in a court of justice,\" a technical term from Roman law, from Old Frenchavocat\"barrister, advocate, spokesman,\" from Latinadvocatus\"one called to aid (another); a pleader (on one's behalf), advocate,\" noun use of past participle ofadvocare\"to call (as witness or adviser), summon, invite; call to aid; invoke,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +vocare\"to call,\" which is related tovox(genitivevocis) \"voice\" (from PIE root*wekw-\"to speak\").Also in Middle English as \"one who intercedes for another,\" and \"protector, champion, patron.\" Feminine formsadvocatess,advocatricewere in use in 15c.;advocatrixis from 17c. Old English glossed Latinadvocatuswithþingere(seething)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advocation",
    "response": "\"a calling in of legal assistance,\" 1520s, from Latinadvocationem(nominativeadvocatio) \"a calling or summoning of legal assistance,\" in Medieval Latin \"duty of defense or protection,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofadvocare\"to call, summon, invite; call to aid,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +vocare\"to call,\" which is related tovox(genitivevocis) \"voice\" (from PIE root*wekw-\"to speak\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "advowson",
    "response": "\"right of presentation to an ancient benefice,\" c. 1300, from Anglo-Frenchadvouison, Old Frenchavoeson, from Latinadvocationem(seeadvocation)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "adze",
    "response": "alsoadz, \"cutting tool used for dressing timber, resembling an axe but with a curved blade at a right-angle to the handle,\" 18c. spelling modification ofads,addes, from Middle Englishadese,adse, from Old Englishadesa\"adze, hatchet,\" which is of unknown origin.Adze\"has been monosyllabic only since the seventeenth century. The word has no cognates, though it resembles the names of the adz and the hammer in many languages\" [Liberman, 2008]. Perhaps somehow related to Old Frenchaisse, Latinascia\"axe\" (seeaxe)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ae",
    "response": "seeæ. As a word, it can represent Old Englishæ\"law,\" especially law of nature or God's law; hence \"legal custom, marriage,\" from Proto-Germanic*aiwi-(cognate with Old High Germanewa, Old Saxoneo), according to Buck probably literally \"way, manner, custom,\" from PIE*ei-\"to go,\" but Boutkan (2005) finds it to be of no certain Indo-European etymology."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aegean",
    "response": "sea between Greece and Asia Minor, 1570s, traditionally named forAegeus, father of Theseus, who threw himself to his death in it when he thought his son had perished; but perhaps from Greekaiges\"waves,\" a word of unknown origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aegina",
    "response": "island in the Saronic Gulf, Latinized form of GreekAigina, which also was the name of a nymph beloved by Zeus. Related:Aeginetan."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aegis",
    "response": "\"protection,\" 1793, a figurative use of Latinaegis, from GreekAigis, the name of the shield of Zeus, a word said by Herodotus to be related toaix(genitiveaigos) \"goat,\" from PIE*aig-\"goat\" (source also of Sanskritajah, Lithuanianožys\"he-goat\"), as the shield was of goatskin. Athene'saigiswas a short goat-skin cloak, set with a gorgon's head and fringed with snakes. The exact use and purpose of it is not now clear."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aeolian",
    "response": "alsoAeolean, c. 1600, \"of the wind,\" from LatinÆolus\"god of the winds,\" from GreekAiolos\"lord of the winds,\" literally \"the Rapid,\" or \"the Changeable,\" fromaiolos\"quickly moving,\" also \"changeful, shifting, varied\" (an adjective used of wasps, serpents, flickering stars, clouds, sounds).TheAeolian harp(the phrase is attested from 1791) was made of tuned strings set in a frame; passing breezes caused them to sound harmoniously. Another name for it wasanemochord(1832). The ancient district ofAiolisin Asia Minor was said to have been named for the wind god, henceAeolianalso refers to one branch of the ancient Greek people."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aeon",
    "response": "\"immeasurable period of time,\" 1640s; seeeon; also seeæ(1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerate",
    "response": "\"cause to mix with carbonic acid or other gas,\" 1794 (implied inaerated), fromaer/aër(used in old science for specific kinds of air, a sense later given togas(n.1)), from Latinaer(seeair(n.1)) + verbal suffix-ate(2). The meaning \"expose to air\" is from 1799, probably a back-formation fromaeration. Related:Aerating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aeration",
    "response": "1570s, \"act of exposing to air,\" from Frenchaération, noun of action fromaérer(v.), from Latinaer\"the air, atmosphere\" (seeair(n.1)). In some cases, fromaerate. In early scientific writing,aer/aërwas used for specific kinds of air, a sense later given togas(n.1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerator",
    "response": "\"a blower,\" also \"an apparatus for forcing air or carbon dioxide into water or other liquids,\" 1861, agent noun fromaerate(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerial",
    "response": "alsoaërial, c. 1600, \"pertaining to the air,\" from Latinaerius\"airy, aerial, lofty, high\" (from Greekaerios\"of the air, pertaining to air,\" fromaēr\"air;\" seeair(n.1)). With adjectival suffix-al(1). Also in English \"consisting of air,\" hence, figuratively, \"of a light and graceful beauty; insubstantial\" (c. 1600). From 1915 as \"by means of aircraft.\" From the Latin collateral formaereuscomes the alternative English spellingaereal."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerie",
    "response": "\"eagle's nest,\" 1580s (attested in Anglo-Latin from early 13c.), from Old Frenchaire\"nest,\" Medieval Latinarea\"nest of a bird of prey\" (12c.), perhaps from Latinarea\"level ground, garden bed\" [Littré], though some doubt this [Klein]. Another theory connects it toatrium. Formerly spelledeyrie(1660s) on the mistaken assumption that it derived from Middle Englishey\"egg.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerobatics",
    "response": "\"aircraft tricks, trick flying,\" 1914, fromaero-+ ending fromacrobatics. Earlier (1879) it meant \"the art of constructing and using airships; aerial navigation; aeronautics.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerobic",
    "response": "\"able to live or living only in the presence of oxygen, requiring or using free oxygen from the air,\" 1875, after Frenchaérobie(n.), coined 1863 by Louis Pasteur in reference to certain bacteria; from Greekaero-\"air\" (seeaero-) +bios\"life\" (from PIE root*gwei-\"to live\").Aerobianandaerobiousalso were used in English. Henceaerobe\"type of micro-organism which lives on oxygen from the air.\" The meaning \"pertaining toaerobicsis from 1968."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerodonetics",
    "response": "science of gliding, 1907, Modern Latin coinage by English engineer Frederick W. Lanchester (1868-1946) from Greekaēr(genitiveaeros) \"air\" (seeair(n.1)) + stem ofdonein\"to shake, drive about,\" for which Beekes gives no etymology. Also see-ics."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerodrome",
    "response": "1902, \"hangar for airships,\" fromaero-on analogy ofhippodrome. From 1909 as \"airport.\" Earlier (1891) a name for a flying machine, from Greekaerodromos\"a running through the air.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerodynamic",
    "response": "alsoaero-dynamic, \"pertaining to the forces of air in motion,\" 1847; seeaero-+dynamic(adj.). Compare Germanaerodynamische(1835), Frenchaérodynamique."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerodynamics",
    "response": "\"science of the motion of air or other gases,\" 1837, fromaero-\"air\" +dynamics."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerofoil",
    "response": "\"lifting surface of an aircraft, etc.,\" 1907, fromaero-+foil(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerogram",
    "response": "alsoaerogramme, 1899, \"message sent through the air\" (by radio waves, i.e. \"wireless telegraphy\"), fromaero-+-gram. From 1920 as \"air-mail letter.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aeronautics",
    "response": "1824, \"art of aerial navigation by means of a balloon,\" fromaeronautic(1784), from Frenchaéronautique, fromaéro-(seeaero-) +nautique\"of ships,\" from Latinnauticus, from Greeknautikos\"pertaining to sailing\" (seenautical). Also see-ics.Aeronaut\"balloonist\" is from 1784, from Frenchaéronaute."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerophobia",
    "response": "\"morbid dread of a current of air,\" 1785; seeaero-+phobia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerophyte",
    "response": "\"plant which lives exclusively on air,\" 1838, perhaps via Frenchaerophyte, fromaero-\"air\" +-phyte\"plant.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aeroplane",
    "response": "1866, originally in reference to surfaces such as shell casings of beetle wings, from Frenchaéroplane(1855), from Greek-derivedaero-\"air\" (seeair(n.1)) + stem of Frenchplaner\"to soar,\" from Latinplanus\"level, flat\" (from PIE root*pele-(2)  \"flat; to spread\").The word was later extended to the wing of a heavier-than-air flying machine. The use of the word in reference to the machine itself is first attested 1873 and probably is an independent coinage in English. Also seeairplane. Ancient Greek had a wordaeroplanos, but it meant \"wandering in the air,\" fromplanos\"wandering\" (seeplanet)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aerosol",
    "response": "\"substance enclosed under pressure and able to be released as a fine spray,\" 1919, fromaero-\"air\" + first syllable insolution, in the chemical sense. A term in physics; modern commercial application is from 1940s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aerosol",
    "response": "\"substance enclosed under pressure and able to be released as a fine spray,\" 1919, fromaero-\"air\" + first syllable insolution, in the chemical sense. A term in physics; modern commercial application is from 1940s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aesculapius",
    "response": "Greek god of medicine, a Latinized form of GreekAisklepios. Related:Aesculapian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aesopic",
    "response": "1927, in the context of Soviet literary censorship; in reference to writing, \"obscure or ambiguous, often allegorical, and disguising dissent;\" fromAesop, the traditional father of the allegorical fable, +-ic. It translates Russianezopovskii(1875), which arose there under the Tsars. In the empire the style was employed by Russian communists, who, once they took power, found themselves disguised in animal fables written by their own dissidents. In the sense \"pertaining to the ancient Greek fable-writer Aesop,\"Aesopianis attested in English from 1875; it is recorded from 1950 in general reference to shrouding of real meaning to avoid censorship."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aesthete",
    "response": "\"person of advanced and fine artistic sensibilities,\" attested from 1878, in vogue 1881, from Greekaisthētēs\"one who perceives,\" from stem ofaisthanesthai\"to perceive (by the senses or by the mind), to feel,\" from PIE*awis-dh-yo-, from root*au-\"to perceive.\" Or perhaps it is fromaestheticon the model ofathlete/athletic. The idea is somewhat older than the word.Aesthetician\"professor of taste\" is from 1829;aestheticistis from 1868."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aesthetic",
    "response": "1798, from GermanÄsthetisch(mid-18c.) or Frenchesthétique(which is from German), ultimately from Greekaisthetikos\"of or for perception by the senses, perceptive,\" of things, \"perceptible,\" fromaisthanesthai\"to perceive (by the senses or by the mind), to feel,\" from PIE*awis-dh-yo-, from root*au-\"to perceive.\"Popularized in English by translations of Kant and used originally in the classically correct sense \"science which treats of the conditions of sensuous perception\" [OED]. Kant had tried to reclaim the word after Alexander Baumgarten had taken it in German to mean \"criticism of taste\" (1750s), but Baumgarten's sense attained popularity in English c. 1830s (despite scholarly resistance) and freed the word from philosophy.Walter Pater used it (1868) to describe the late 19c. movement that advocated \"art for art's sake,\" which further blurred the sense. [Whewell had proposedcallestheticsfor \"the science of the perception of the beautiful.\"]As an adjective by 1798 \"of or pertaining to sensual perception;\" 1821 as \"of or pertaining to appreciation of the beautiful.\" Related:Aesthetically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aestheticism",
    "response": "\"devotion to what is sensuously beautiful,\" 1855, fromaesthetic+-ism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aesthetics",
    "response": "1803, fromaesthetic(adj.); also see-ics."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Afar",
    "response": "\"from far, from a distance,\" a contraction of Middle Englishof feor(late 12c.),on ferr(c. 1300), from Old Englishfeor\"far\" (seefar); thea-(1) in compounds representing bothofandon(which in this use meant the same). Spelledaferin 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afar",
    "response": "\"from far, from a distance,\" a contraction of Middle Englishof feor(late 12c.),on ferr(c. 1300), from Old Englishfeor\"far\" (seefar); thea-(1) in compounds representing bothofandon(which in this use meant the same). Spelledaferin 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afeared",
    "response": "Old Englishafæred, past participle of now-obsoleteafear(Old Englishafæran) \"terrify, cause to fear,\" froma-(1) +færan(seefear(v.)). Used frequently by Shakespeare, but supplanted in literary English after 1700 byafraid(q.v.), to which it has no connection. It survived in popular speech and colloquial writing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affability",
    "response": "\"readiness to be sociable or to converse,\" late 15c., from Old Frenchaffabilité(14c.), noun of quality fromaffable(seeaffable)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affable",
    "response": "of persons, \"open to conversation or approach,\" late 15c., from Old Frenchaffable\"benign, approachable\" (14c.), from Latinaffabilis\"approachable, courteous, kind, friendly,\" literally \"who can be (easily) spoken to,\" fromaffari\"to speak to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +fari\"to speak\" (from PIE root*bha-(2) \"to speak, tell, say\"). Related:Affably. Glossed in Old English aswordwynsum."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affair",
    "response": "c. 1300,afere, \"what one has to do, ordinary business,\" from Anglo-Frenchafere, Old Frenchafaire\"business, event; rank, estate\" (12c., Modern Frenchaffaire), from the infinitive phraseà faire\"to do,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +facere\"to do, make\" (from PIE root*dhe-\"to set, put\").Originally a Northern word according to OED, it was brought into general use and given a French spelling by Caxton (late 15c.). The general sense of \"vague proceedings\" (in romance, war, etc.) is attested by 1702. The meaning \"an affair of the heart; a passionate episode\" is from Frenchaffaire de coeur(itself attested as a French phrase in English from 1809); tohave an affairwith someone in this sense is by 1726, earlierhave an affair of love:Related:Affairs."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affect",
    "response": "late 14c., \"mental state,\" from Latinaffectus\"disposition, mood, state of mind or body produced by some external influence,\" noun use of adjectiveaffectus\"disposed, constituted, inclined,\" literally \"furnished, supplied, endowed,\" past participle ofafficere\"to do; treat, use, manage, handle; act on, do something to; attack with disease; have influence on, apply force to.\" This Latin verb, used of many different actions, is literally \"to do to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +facere(past participlefactus) \"to make, do\" (from PIE root*dhe-\"to set, put\"). The nounaffectseems to have been obsolete outside of psychology, where it is a modern coinage, translating GermanAffekt. Related:Affects."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affectation",
    "response": "\"studied display, artificiality of manner or conduct,\" 1540s, from Frenchaffectation(16c.) or directly from Latinaffectationem(nominativeaffectatio) \"a striving after, a claiming,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaffectare\"to strive for\" (seeaffect(v.2))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affected",
    "response": "\"artificially displayed,\" 1580s, past-participle adjective fromaffect(v.2) \"make a pretense of.\" Related:Affectedly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affecting",
    "response": "\"having power to move or excite the feelings,\" 1720, present-participle adjective fromaffect(v.1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affection",
    "response": "c. 1200,affeccioun, \"desire, inclination, wish, intention;\" mid-14c., \"an emotion of the mind, passion, lust as opposed to reason;\" from Old Frenchafection(12c., Modern Frenchaffection) \"emotion, inclination, disposition; love, attraction, enthusiasm,\" from Latinaffectionem(nominativeaffectio) \"a relation, disposition; a temporary state; a frame, constitution,\" noun of state from past-participle stem ofafficere\"to do something to, act on,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +facere(past participlefactus) \"to make, do\" (from PIE root*dhe-\"to set, put\").The sense developed in Latin from \"disposition\" to \"good disposition, zealous attachment.\" In English the sense of \"love\" is from late 14c. Formally it goes withaffect(v.2), but it has absorbed some sense from (v.1). Related:Affections."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affectionate",
    "response": "1580s, \"fond, loving,\" fromaffection+-ate(1); suggested by Frenchaffectionné. Early, now mostly obsolete, senses included \"prejudiced\" (1530s), \"inclined\" (1530s), \"passionate\" (1540s), \"earnest\" (c. 1600). Other forms also used in the main modern sense of this word includedaffectual\"zealous; affectionate\" (early 15c.),affectuous\"eager, loving\" (mid-15c.),affectious(1580s), from Latinaffectuosus. Related:Affectionately."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affiance",
    "response": "1520s, \"to promise,\" from Old Frenchafiancier\"to pledge, promise, give one's word,\" fromafiance(n.) \"confidence, trust,\" fromafier\"to trust,\" from Late Latinaffidare, fromad\"to\" (seead-) +fidare\"to trust,\" fromfidus\"faithful\" (from PIE root*bheidh-\"to trust, confide, persuade\").From mid-16c. especially \"to promise in marriage.\" The earlier form of the word wasaffy(Middle Englishaffien\"to trust, have faith; have faith in\" c. 1300), from Old Frenchafier. Related:Affianced;affiancing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affidavit",
    "response": "\"written declaration upon an oath,\" 1590s, from Medieval Latinaffidavit, literally \"he has stated on oath,\" third person singular perfective ofaffidare\"to trust; to make an oath,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +fidare\"to trust,\" fromfidus\"faithful\" (from PIE root*bheidh-\"to trust, confide, persuade\"). So called from being the first word of sworn statements."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affiliate",
    "response": "1761, \"bring into close association,\" from Latinaffiliatus, past participle ofaffiliare\"to adopt a son,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +filius\"son\" (seefilial). Outside legal use, always figurative. Related:Affiliated;affiliating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affiliation",
    "response": "1751, \"adoption,\" from Frenchaffiliation, from Medieval Latinaffiliationem(nominativeaffiliatio), noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinaffiliare\"to adopt as a son,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +filius\"son\" (seefilial).The figurative sense of \"adoption by a society,\" in reference to a local chapter or branch, is recorded by 1799 (the verbaffiliatein a related sense is from 1761). The meaning \"friendship, relationship, association\" is by 1852."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affinity",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"relation by marriage\" (as opposed toconsanguinity), from Old Frenchafinite\"relationship, kinship; neighborhood, vicinity\" (12c., Modern Frenchaffinité), from Latinaffinitatem(nominativeaffinitas) \"relationship by marriage; neighborhood,\" noun of state fromaffinis\"adjoining, adjacent,\" also \"kin by marriage,\" literally \"bordering on,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +finis\"a border, a boundary\" (seefinish(v.)).The spelling was re-Latinized in early Modern English. It has been used figuratively in English since c. 1600 of structural relationships in chemistry, philology, geometry, etc. The meaning \"natural liking or attraction, a relationship as close as family between persons not related by blood\" is from 1610s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affirm",
    "response": "Middle Englishaffermen,affirmen, \"to decide upon\" (c. 1300); \"to state positively\" (late 14c.), from Old Frenchafermer(Modern Frenchaffirmer) \"affirm, confirm; strengthen, consolidate,\" from Latinaffirmare\"to make steady, strengthen,\" figuratively \"confirm, corroborate,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +firmare\"strengthen, make firm,\" fromfirmus\"strong\" (from suffixed form of PIE root*dher-\"to hold firmly, support\").The spelling was refashioned 16c. in French and English on the Latin model. The legal sense of \"declare solemnly (as before a court) but without an oath\" is from early 15c. Related:Affirmed;affirming."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affirmation",
    "response": "early 15c.,affirmacioun, \"assertion that something is true,\" from Old Frenchafermacion\"confirmation\" (14c.), from Latinaffirmationem(nominativeaffirmatio) \"an affirmation, solid assurance,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaffirmare\"to make steady; strengthen; confirm,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +firmare\"strengthen, make firm,\" fromfirmus\"strong\" (seefirm(adj.)).In law, as the word for the conscientious-objector alternative to oath-taking (Quakers, Moravians, etc.), it is attested from 1690s; if false, it incurs the same penalty as perjury."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affirmative",
    "response": "\"answering 'yes,' \" mid-15c., from use in logic; from Old Frenchaffirmatif, earlierafirmatif(13c.), from Latinaffirmativus, fromaffirmat-, past-participle stem ofaffirmare\"to make steady; strengthen; confirm,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +firmare\"strengthen, make firm,\" fromfirmus\"strong\" (seefirm(adj.)).As a noun from early 15c., \"that which affirms or asserts.\" American Englishaffirmative action\"positive or corrective effort by employers to prevent discrimination in hiring or promotion\" is attested from 1935 with regard to labor unions (reinstatement of fired members, etc.). The specific racial sense is attested from 1961; by late 1970s the sense had shifted toward pro-active methods such as hiring quotas. Related:Affirmatively."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affix",
    "response": "\"fasten, join, attach,\" 1530s, from Medieval Latinaffixare, frequentative of Latinaffigere(past participleaffixus) \"fasten to, attach,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +figere\"to fasten\" (from PIE root*dheigw-\"to stick, fix\").According to OED first used by Scottish writers and thus perhaps the immediate source was Frenchaffixer, a temporarily re-Latinized spelling of Old Frenchafichier(Modern Frenchafficher), from a Medieval Latin variant of the Latin verb. The older form in English wasaffitch(Middle Englishafficchen, late 14c.), from Old Frenchafichier. Related:Affixed;affixt;affixing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afflatus",
    "response": "\"miraculous communication of supernatural knowledge or power,\" 1660s, from Latinafflatus\"a breathing upon, blast,\" figuratively \"inspiration,\" noun use of past participle ofafflare\"to blow upon,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +flare\"to blow\" (from PIE root*bhle-\"to blow\"). The literal meaning \"a blowing or breathing upon\" is rare in English, this sense being taken byafflation."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afflict",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to cast down\" (a sense now obsolete), from Old Frenchaflicter, from Latinafflictare\"to damage, harass, torment,\" frequentative ofaffligere(past participleafflictus) \"to dash down, overthrow,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +fligere(past participleflictus) \"to strike.\"This is reconstructed to be from PIE root*bhlig-\"to strike\" (source also of Greekphlibein\"to press, crush,\" Czechblizna\"scar,\" Welshblif\"catapult\"). The weakened or transferred meaning \"to trouble in body or mind, harass, distress,\" is attested from 1530s. Related:Afflicted;afflicting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afflicted",
    "response": "\"person or persons in constant suffering of body or mind,\" 1650s, noun use of past-participle adjective fromafflict. Related:Afflictedness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affliction",
    "response": "c. 1300,affliccioun, \"misery, sorrow, pain, distress\" (originally especially \"self-inflicted pain, self-mortification, religious asceticism\"), from Old Frenchafliction\"act of humility, humiliation, mortification, punishment\" (11c.) and directly from Latinafflictionem(nominativeafflictio) \"pain, suffering, torment,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaffligere\"to dash down, overthrow,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +fligere(past participleflictus) \"to strike\" (seeafflict). The meaning \"a cause of constant pain or sorrow\" is from 1590s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affluence",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"a plentiful flowing, an abundant supply,\" from Old Frenchaffluence, from Latinaffluentia\"affluence, abundance,\" literally \"a flowing to,\" abstract noun fromaffluentem(nominativeaffluens) \"flowing toward; abounding, rich, copious\" (seeaffluent). The notion in the figurative Latin sense is of \"a plentiful flow\" of the gifts of fortune, hence \"wealth, abundance of earthly goods,\" a sense attested in English from c. 1600. Latinaffluentiais glossed in Ælfric's vocabulary (late Old English) byoferflowendnys."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affluent",
    "response": "early-15c., \"abounding in, copious\" (of God's grace); mid-15c. \"flowing to\" (of liquids), both senses now obsolete, from Old Frenchafluent(14c.) or directly from Latinaffluentem(nominativeaffluens) \"abounding, rich, copious,\" literally \"flowing toward,\" present participle ofaffluere\"flow toward,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +fluere\"to flow\" (seefluent). The especial sense of \"abounding in wealth or possessions\" is from 1753."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afflux",
    "response": "\"a flowing toward,\" 1610s, from Medieval Latinaffluxus, noun use of past participle ofaffluere(seeaffluent)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afford",
    "response": "Middle Englishaforth, from Old Englishgeforðian\"to put forth, contribute; further, advance; carry out, accomplish,\" fromge-completive prefix (which in Middle English regularly reduces toa-; seea-(1)) +forðian\"to further,\" fromforð\"forward, onward\" (seeforth).The prefix shift toaf-took place 16c. under mistaken belief that it was a Latin word inad-; change of-th-to-d-took place late 16c. (and also transformedburthen,spither,murther, etc. into their modern forms).The notion of \"accomplish\" (late Old English) gradually became \"be able to bear the expense of, have enough money\" to do something (late 14c.), and the original senses became obsolete. Of things, \"be capable of yielding,\" 1580s, which is the sense inafford (one) an opportunity. Related:Afforded;affording."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affordable",
    "response": "1804, \"that can be spared;\" 1853, \"that can be paid for,\" fromafford+-able. Related:Affordably(1969);affordability(1910)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afforest",
    "response": "\"convert to forest\" (especially for hunting grounds), c. 1500, from Anglo-Latinafforestare, from assimilated form of Latinad\"to\" (seead-) + Medieval Latinforestis(seeforest(n.)). Related:Afforested; afforestation."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affray",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"fear, terror, state of alarm produced by a sudden disturbance,\" from Old Frenchaffrai,effrei,esfrei\"disturbance, fright,\" fromesfreer(v.) \"to worry, concern, trouble, disturb,\" from Vulgar Latin*exfridare, a hybrid word meaning literally \"to take out of peace.\"The first element is from Latinex\"out of\" (seeex-). The second is Frankish*frithu\"peace,\" from Proto-Germanic*frithuz\"peace, consideration, forbearance\" (source also of Old Saxonfrithu, Old Englishfriðu, Old High Germanfridu\"peace, truce,\" GermanFriede\"peace\"), from a suffixed form of PIE root*pri-\"to be friendly, to love.\"The meaning \"breach of the peace, riotous fight in public\" is from late 15c., via the notion of \"disturbance causing terror.\" The French verb also entered Middle English, asafrey\"to terrify, frighten\" (early 14c.), but it survives almost exclusively in its past participle,afraid(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affricative",
    "response": "in phonetics, 1879 (perhaps from German); the elements are-ive+ Latinaffricat-, past-participle stem ofaffricare\"rub against,\" from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +fricare\"to rub\" (seefriction)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affright",
    "response": "\"frighten, terrify, alarm,\" mid-15c.; seea-(1) +fright(v.). It probably was back-formed from olderaffright(adj.) \"struck with sudden fear\" (which is metathesized from Old Englishafyrht, past participle ofafyrhtan\"to frighten, terrify\"). The doubled-f-is 16c., probably an erroneous Latin correction of a non-Latin word (compareafford). Related:Affrighted;affrighting;affrightment."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "affront",
    "response": "early 14c., \"offend by open disrespect,\" a figurative use, from Old Frenchafronter\"to face, confront; to slap in the face\" (13c., Modern Frenchaffronter), from Late Latinaffrontare\"to strike against,\" from Latinad frontem\"to the face,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +frons(genitivefrontis) \"forehead, front\" (seefront(n.)). Related:Affronted;affronting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Afghan",
    "response": "native or inhabitant of Afghanistan, 1784, properly only the Durani Afghans; a name of uncertain origin. It is first attested in Arabic in al-'Utbi's \"History of Sultan Mahmud\" written c.1030 C.E. and was in use in India from 13c. Old Afghan chronicles trace the name to a legendaryAfghana, son of Jeremiah, son of Israelite King Saul, from whom they claimed descent.In English, attested from 1833 as a type of blanket or wrap (short forAfghan shawl); by 1877 as a type of carpet; by 1895 as a breed of hunting dog; by 1973 as a style of sheepskin coat."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afield",
    "response": "\"in or to a field,\" 1590s, a contraction of Middle English prepositional phrasein felde, from Old Englishon felda\"in the field\" (especially of battle); seea-(1) +field(n.). Meaning \"away from home, at a distance\" is attested by early 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afire",
    "response": "\"on fire,\" c. 1200,afure, froma-(1) \"on\" +fire(n.). Figurative use by late 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aflame",
    "response": "\"on fire, ablaze,\" 1550s, froma-(1) \"on\" +flame(n.). Figurative use by 1856."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aflaunt",
    "response": "\"flaunting; flauntingly,\" 1560s, froma-(1) +flaunt."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aflicker",
    "response": "1875, froma-(1) +flicker."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afloat",
    "response": "Old Englishaflote, contraction of prepositional phraseon flot; seea-(1) \"to\" +flot\"body of water deep enough for a boat\" (seefloat(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aflush",
    "response": "\"blushing,\" 1880, froma-(1) +flush(n.) \"redness in the face.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aflutter",
    "response": "\"in a fluttering state, agitated,\" 1830, froma-(1) +flutter(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afoot",
    "response": "c. 1200,afote, \"on foot, walking, not on horseback,\" contraction of prepositional phraseon fotum; seea-(1) \"on\" +foot(n.). Meaning \"astir, on the move\" is from 1520s; figurative sense of \"in active operation\" is from 1601 (\"Julius Caesar\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afore",
    "response": "Middle English, from Old Englishonforan, contraction of prepositional phraseon foran\"before in place, at the beginning of, in front of,\" fromon(prep.), seea-(1), +foran(adv.) \"in front,\" dative offor. In some cases probably it represents Old Englishætforan\"at-fore.\"Attested from early 14c. as a preposition, \"before in time,\" and as a conjunction, \"earlier than the time when, before.\" Once the literary equivalent ofbefore, it now has been replaced by that word except in nautical use, colloquial dialects, and in combinations such asaforesaid,aforethought."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aforesaid",
    "response": "\"mentioned before in a preceding part of the same writing or speech,\" a common legal word, late 14c., fromafore+said."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aforethought",
    "response": "\"premeditated,\" a legal word, 1580s, fromafore+ past tense ofthink. Apparently an English loan-translation of the Old French legalese wordprepense(seeprepense) in the phrasemalice prepense\"malice aforethought\" (Coke)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aforetime",
    "response": "early 15c., \"before the present, in the past,\" fromafore+time(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afoul",
    "response": "1809, originally nautical, \"in a state of collision or entanglement,\" froma-(1) +foul(adj.). From 1833 in general sense of \"in violent or hostile conflict,\" mainly in phrases such asrun afoul of."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afraid",
    "response": "\"impressed with fear, fearful,\" early 14c., originally the past participle of the now-obsolete Middle English verbafray\"frighten,\" from Anglo-Frenchafrayer, Old Frenchaffrai, effrei, esfrei\"disturbance, fright,\" fromesfreer(v.) \"to worry, concern, trouble, disturb,\" from Vulgar Latin*exfridare, a hybrid word meaning literally \"to take out of peace.\"The first element is from Latinex\"out of\" (seeex-). The second is Frankish*frithu\"peace,\" from Proto-Germanic*frithuz\"peace, consideration, forbearance\" (source also of Old Saxonfrithu, Old Englishfriu, Old High Germanfridu\"peace, truce,\" GermanFreide\"peace\"), from a suffixed form of PIE root*pri-\"to be friendly, to love.\"A rare case of an English adjective that never stands before a noun. Because it was used in the King James Bible, it acquired independent standing and thrived whileaffrayfaded, and it chased off the once more commonafeared. Colloquial sense inI'm afraid\"I regret to say, I suspect\" (without implication of fear, as a polite introduction to a correction, admission, etc.) is recorded by 1590s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afresh",
    "response": "\"anew, again,\" c. 1500, perhaps on analogy ofanew[see note in OED], froma-(1) +fresh(adj.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Afric",
    "response": "\"African,\" 1580s, from LatinAfricus(seeAfrica). Also sometimes used as a noun."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "African",
    "response": "Old EnglishAfricanas(plural) \"native or inhabitant of Africa,\" from LatinAfricanus(adj.) \"of Africa, African,\" fromAfrica(seeAfrica). Used of white residents of Africa from 1815. Used of black residents of the U.S. from 18c., when it especially meant \"one brought from Africa\" and sometimes was contrasted to native-bornNegro. As an adjective by 1560s, \"pertaining to Africa or Africans\" (Old English hadAfricanisc); from 1722 as \"of or pertaining to black Americans.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Africanism",
    "response": "1640s in reference to qualities of Latin peculiar to writers from Roman Africa (especially Church fathers), fromAfrican+-ism. By 1836 as \"mode of speech peculiar to African-Americans.\" From 1957 in reference to the political development of African nations or peoples."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Afrikaans",
    "response": "\"the Germanic language of South Africa, the Dutch language as spoken in South Africa,\" 1892, from DutchAfrikaansch\"Africanish\" (seeAfrikander). Also known asSouth African Dutch."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Afrikander",
    "response": "1822, \"South African native of Dutch descent,\" from DutchAfrikaner\"African,\" with unetymological-d-on analogy ofHollander,Englander, etc. (Afrikaneris attested from 1824)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aft",
    "response": "Old Englishæftan\"from behind, behind, farthest back,\" superlative of Old Englishæf,af,of\"away, away from, off\" (from PIE root*apo-\"off, away\"). Cognate with Old Frisianeft\"later, afterwards; as well,\" Old Norseeft\"after,\" Middle Dutchechter,efter\"later, again,\" Gothicafta\"behind, past.\" The Germanic superlative suffix*-tacorresponds to PIE*-to(compare Greekprōtos\"first,\" superlative ofpro\"before\"). The English word is now purely nautical, \"in, near, or toward the stern of a ship.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "after",
    "response": "Old Englishæfter\"behind; later in time\" (adv.); \"behind in place; later than in time; in pursuit, following with intent to overtake\" (prep.), fromof\"off\" (seeoff(adv.)) +-ter, a comparative suffix; thus the original meaning was \"more away, farther off.\" Compare Old Norseeptir\"after,\" Old Frisianefter, Dutchachter, Old High Germanaftar, Gothicaftra\"behind;\" also seeaft. Cognate with Greekapotero\"farther off,\" Old Persianapataram\"further.\"From c. 1300 as \"in imitation of.\" As a conjunction, \"subsequent to the time that,\" from late Old English.After hours\"hours after regular working hours\" is from 1814.Afterwit\"wisdom that comes too late\" is attested from c. 1500 but seems to have fallen from use.After youas an expression in yielding precedence is recorded by 1650."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterbirth",
    "response": "alsoafter-birth, \"placenta, etc., expelled from the uterus after birth,\" 1580s, perhaps based on older, similar Scandinavian compounds; seeafter+birth(n.). As \"a birth after the death or last will of the father,\" 1875 (translating Latinagnatioin Roman law). Old English hadæfterboren(adj.) \"posthumous\" in reference to birth."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterglow",
    "response": "alsoafter-glow, \"glow in the western sky after sunset,\" 1829, fromafter+glow(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterlife",
    "response": "alsoafter-life, 1590s, \"a future life\" (especially after resurrection), fromafter+life."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aftermath",
    "response": "1520s, originally \"a second crop of grass grown on the same land after the first had been harvested,\" fromafter+-math, which is from Old Englishmæð\"a mowing, cutting of grass\" (from PIE root*me-(4) \"to cut down grass or grain\").Other words for it wereaftercrop(1560s),aftergrass(1680s),lattermath,fog(n.2). The figurative sense is by 1650s. Compare Frenchregain\"aftermath,\" fromre-+ Old Frenchgain,gaain\"grass which grows in mown meadows,\" from Frankish or some other Germanic source similar to Old High Germanweida\"grass, pasture.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afternoon",
    "response": "\"part of the day from noon to evening,\" c. 1300, fromafter+noon. In 15c.-16c., the form wasat afternoon; from c. 1600 it has beenin the afternoon. As an adjective from 1570s. Middle English had alsoaftermete\"afternoon, part of the day following the noon meal\" (mid-14c.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aftershock",
    "response": "alsoafter-shock, \"smaller earthquake after a larger one,\" 1894, fromafter+shock(n.1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterthought",
    "response": "1660s, \"a later thought,\" fromafter+thought(n.). As \"reflection after an act,\" 1680s. The colloquial sense of \"youngest child of a family\" (especially one born much later than the others) is by 1902."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterward",
    "response": "Old Englishæfterwearde\"behind, in back, in the rear,\" fromæft\"after\" (seeaft) +-weardsuffix indicating direction (see-ward); expanded by influence ofafter. Variantafterwardsshows adverbial genitive. Old English had alsoæfterweardnes\"posterity.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "afterwards",
    "response": "c. 1300, fromafterward(q.v.) + adverbial genitive-s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aftward",
    "response": "\"toward the stern or back part of a vessel,\" Middle Englishafteward, from Old Englishæftewearde; seeaft+-ward. The original form ofafterward(q.v.), retained in nautical use. Related:Aftwards."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aga",
    "response": "alsoagha, title of rank, especially in Turkey, c. 1600, from Turkishagha\"chief, master, lord,\" related to East Turkicagha\"elder brother.\" TheAgha Khanis the title of the spiritual leader of Nizari Ismaili Muslims."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "again",
    "response": "late Old Englishagan, from earlierongean(prep.) \"toward; opposite, against, contrary to; in exchange for,\" as an adverb \"in the opposite direction, back, to or toward a former place or position,\" fromon\"on\" (seeon(prep.) and comparea-(1)) +-gegn\"against, toward.\" This is from the Germanic root*gagina(source also of Old Norsegegn\"straight, direct;\" Danishigen\"against;\" Old Frisianjen, Old High Germangegin, Germangegen\"against, toward,\"entgegen\"against, in opposition to\").In Old English,eft(seeeftsoons) was the main word for \"again,\" but this often was strengthened byongean, which became the principal word by 13c. Norse influence is responsible for the hard-g-. It was differentiated fromagainst(q.v.) 16c. in southern writers,againbecoming an adverb only, andagainsttaking over as preposition and conjunction, butagainclung to all senses in northern and Scottish dialect (whereagainstwas not adopted). Of action, \"in return,\" early 13c.; of action or fact, \"once more,\" late 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "against",
    "response": "12c.,agenes\"in opposition to, adverse, hostile; in an opposite direction or position, in contact with, in front of, so as to meet,\" originally a southern variant ofagan(prep.) \"again\" (seeagain), with adverbial genitive. The unetymological-tturned up mid-14c. and was standard by early 16c., perhaps from influence of superlatives (seeamidst). The word's use as a conjunction, \"against the time that,\" hence \"before,\" is now archaic or obsolete."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Agamemnon",
    "response": "king of Mycenae, leader of the Greeks in the Trojan War, his name perhaps represents Greek*Aga-med-mon, literally \"ruling mightily,\" from intensifying prefixaga-\"very much\" +medon\"ruler\" (from PIE root*med-\"take appropriate measures\"). But others (Liddell & Scott) connect the second part withmenein\"to stay, abide, remain,\" for a literal sense \"very steadfast.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agamy",
    "response": "\"non-recognition of marriage\" (by a state, etc.), from Greeka-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +-gamia, fromgamos\"marriage\" (seegamete)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agape",
    "response": "c. 1600, from Greekagapē\"brotherly love, charity,\" in Ecclesiastical use \"the love of God for man and man for God,\" a late and mostly Christian formation from the verbagapan\"greet with affection, receive with friendship; to like, love,\" which is of unknown origin. It sometimes is explained as*aga-pa-\"to protect greatly,\" with intensifying prefixaga-. \"The Christian use may have been influenced by Hebr.'ahaba'love'\" [Beekes].Agape, in plural, was used by early Christians for their \"love feast,\" a communal meal held in connection with the Lord's Supper. \"The loss of their original character and the growth of abuses led to the prohibition of them in church buildings, and in the fourth century to their separation from the Lord's supper and their gradual discontinuance\" [Century Dictionary]. In modern use, often in simpler sense of \"Christian love\" (1856, frequently opposed toerosas \"carnal or sensual love\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agaric",
    "response": "1530s, an herbalists' name for a wide range of fungi, from Latinized form of Greekagarikon, name of a corky tree-fungus used as tinder, said by ancient sources to be fromAgariin Sarmatia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agate",
    "response": "variety of banded, colored quartz, 1560s, from Frenchagate, from Latinachates, from Greekakhatēs, the name of a river in Sicily where the stones were found (Pliny). But the river could as easily be named for the stone.Earlier in English asachate(early 13c.), directly from Latin. The Elizabethan sense of \"a diminutive person\" is from the small figures cut in agates for seals, etc., and the notion of smallness is preserved in typographer'sagate(1838), the U.S. name of the 5.5-point font called in Great Britainruby. Meaning \"toy marble made of glass resembling agate\" is from 1843 (colloquially called anaggie). Related:Agatine."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Agatha",
    "response": "fem. proper name, Latinized form of GreekAgathē, fem. ofagathos\"good, fit; gentle, noble\" (of persons, opposed tokakoi), which is of unknown origin. Never a popular name in U.S., and all but unused there since 1940. The Greek adjective grew to include notions of \"wealthy, powerful,\" also \"brave, good at fighting\" (as qualities attributed to the chiefs) as well as \"good\" in a moral sense. Also, of things, \"serviceable, useful,\" and, abstractly, \"the good.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agathism",
    "response": "the doctrine that all things tend toward the good, 1830, fromagathist+-ism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agathist",
    "response": "1816, from Greekagathos\"good\" (seeAgatha) +-ist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Agave",
    "response": "American aloe plant, 1797, from Latinagave, from Greekagauē, proper name in mythology (mother of Pentheus), fromagauos\"noble, illustrious,\" a word of uncertain origin, perhaps fromagasthai\"wonder at,\" fromgaiein\"to rejoice, exult,\" with intensive prefixa-. The name seems to have been taken generically by botanists, the plant perhaps so called for its \"stately\" flower stem."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "age",
    "response": "late 13c., \"long but indefinite period in human history,\" from Old Frenchaage,eage(12c., Modern Frenchâge) \"age; life, lifetime, lifespan; maturity,\" earlieredage(11c.), from Vulgar Latin*aetaticum(source also of Spanishedad, Italianeta, Portugueseidade\"age\"), extended form of Latinaetatem(nominativeaetas), \"period of life, age, lifetime, years,\" fromaevum\"lifetime, eternity, age\" (from PIE root*aiw-\"vital force, life; long life, eternity\").Expelled nativeeld(Old Englisheald) \"old age; an age; age as a period of life.\" The meaning \"time something has lived, particular length or stage of life\" is from early 14c. Used especially for \"old age\" since early 14c.; the meaning \"effects of old age\" (feebleness, senility, etc.) is from mid-15c.In geology, in reference to great periods in the history of the earth, by 1855; in archaeology, from 1865 (Stone Age, etc.) naming periods for the materials used to make weapons and tools. Sometimes in early modern English \"a century\" (similar to Frenchsiècle\"century,\" literally \"an age\"), hence plural use inDark Ages,Middle Ages. Toact (one's) age\"behave with appropriate maturity\" is attested by 1927."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aged",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"having lived long,\" mid-15c., past-participle adjective fromage(v.). Meaning \"having been allowed to get old\" (of cheese, etc.) is by 1873. Meaning \"of the age of\" is from 1630s.Aged Parentis from \"Great Expectations\" (1860-61). Related:Agedness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ageless",
    "response": "1650s, \"without age,\" fromage(n.) +-less. Related:Agelessly;agelessness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agency",
    "response": "1650s, \"active operation;\" 1670s, \"a mode of exerting power or producing effect,\" from Medieval Latinagentia, abstract noun from Latinagentem(nominativeagens) \"effective, powerful,\" present participle ofagere\"to set in motion, drive forward; to do, perform,\" figuratively \"incite to action; keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). The meaning \"establishment where business is done for another\" is recorded by 1861."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agenda",
    "response": "1650s, originally theological, \"matters of practice,\" as opposed tocredenda\"things to be believed, matters of faith,\" from Latinagenda, literally \"things to be done,\" neuter plural ofagendus, gerundive ofagere\"to do\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").The modern sense of \"items of business to be done at a meeting\" is attested by 1882. \"If a singular is required (=one item of the agenda) it is nowagendum, the former singularagendbeing obsolete\" [Fowler]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agendum",
    "response": "\"an item on an agenda;\" seeagenda."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agent",
    "response": "late 15c., \"one who acts,\" from Latinagentem(nominativeagens) \"effective, powerful,\" present participle ofagere\"to set in motion, drive forward; to do, perform; keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").The meaning \"any natural force or substance which produces a phenomenon\" is from 1550s. The meaning \"deputy, representative\" is from 1590s. The sense of \"spy, secret agent\" is attested by 1916."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agential",
    "response": "\"pertaining to an agent or to an agency,\" 1847, from Medieval Latinagentia(seeagency) +-al(1). Related:Agentially."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aggie",
    "response": "\"college student studying agriculture,\" by 1880, American English college slang, fromag, abbreviation ofagriculture, +-ie."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agglomerate",
    "response": "1680s, \"collect or gather in a mass\" (transitive), from Latinagglomeratus, past participle ofagglomerare\"to wind or add onto a ball,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +glomerare\"wind up in a ball,\" fromglomus(genitiveglomeris) \"ball of yarn,\" which is of uncertain origin (seeglebe). The intransitive sense of \"grow into a mass\" is from 1730. Related:Agglomerated;agglomerating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agglomeration",
    "response": "1774, \"action of collecting in a mass,\" from Latinagglomerationem(nominativeagglomeratio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofagglomerare\"to wind or add onto a ball,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +glomerare\"wind up in a ball,\" fromglomus(genitiveglomeris) \"ball, ball of yarn, ball-shaped mass,\" which is of uncertain origin (seeglebe). In reference to a mass so formed, it is recorded from 1833."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agglutinate",
    "response": "1580s, \"unite or cause to adhere,\" from Latinagglutinatus, past participle ofagglutinare\"fasten with glue,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +glutinare\"to glue,\" fromgluten\"glue\" (from PIE*glei-;seeglue(n.)). Related:Agglutinated;agglutinating. Perhaps suggested by the earlier use of the same word in English as a past-participle adjective (1540s) \"united as by glue,\" from the Latin past participle."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agglutination",
    "response": "1540s, \"act of uniting by glue,\" from Latinagglutinationem(nominativeagglutinatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofagglutinare\"fasten with glue, stick on,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +glutinare\"to glue,\" fromgluten\"glue\" (from PIE*glei-\"clay,\" also forming words with a sense of \"to stick together;\" seeclay). The use in philology is from mid-17c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agglutinative",
    "response": "\"having the power or tendency to unite or adhere,\" 1630s, originally in a medical sense, from Latinagglutinat-, past-participle stem ofagglutinare\"stick on, fasten with glue,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +glutinare\"to glue,\" fromgluten\"glue\" (from PIE*glei-\"clay,\" also forming words with a sense of \"to stick together;\" seeclay). Philological sense is from 1650s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggrandize",
    "response": "1630s, \"to make larger, increase,\" from Frenchagrandiss-, present-participle stem ofagrandir\"to augment, enlarge\" (16c.), ultimately from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +grandire\"to make great,\" fromgrandis\"big, great; full, abundant\" (seegrand(adj.)). The double-g-spelling in English (also formerly in French) is by analogy with Latin words inad-. Related:Aggrandized;aggrandizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggrandizement",
    "response": "1650s, \"a greatening, enlarging, advancement,\" usually not in a physical sense, from Frenchagrandissement, formerly alsoaggrandissement, noun of action fromagrandir\"to augment\" (seeaggrandize)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggravate",
    "response": "1520s, \"make heavy, burden down,\" from Latinaggravatus, past participle ofaggravare\"to render more troublesome,\" literally \"to make heavy or heavier, add to the weight of,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gravare\"weigh down,\" fromgravis\"heavy\" (from PIE root*gwere-(1)  \"heavy\").The literal sense in English has become obsolete; the meaning \"to make a bad thing worse\" is from 1590s; the colloquial sense of \"exasperate, annoy\" is from 1610s. The earlier English verb wasaggrege\"make heavier or more burdensome; make more oppressive; increase, intensify\" (late 14c.), from Old Frenchagreger."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggravating",
    "response": "1670s, \"making worse or more heinous\" (implied inaggravatingly), present-participle adjective fromaggravate(v.). The phraseaggravating circumstancesis recorded from 1790. The weakened sense of \"provoking, annoying\" is by 1775. An earlier adjective in the sense \"troublesome, causing difficulty\" was Middle Englishaggravaunt(mid-15c.)"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggravation",
    "response": "late 15c., \"an increasing in gravity or seriousness,\" from Frenchaggravation, from Late Latinaggravationem(nominativeaggravatio), noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinaggravare\"make heavier,\" figuratively \"to embarrass further, increase in oppressiveness,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gravare\"weigh down,\" fromgravis\"heavy\" (from PIE root*gwere-(1) \"heavy\"). The sense of \"irritation\" is from 1610s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggregate",
    "response": "c. 1400, from Latinaggregatus\"associated, united,\" past participle ofaggregare\"add to (a flock), lead to a flock, bring together (in a flock),\" figuratively \"attach, join, include; collect, bring together,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gregare\"to collect into a flock, gather,\" fromgrex(genitivegregis) \"a flock\" (from PIE root*ger-\"to gather\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggregation",
    "response": "early 15c.,aggregacioun, originally in medicine (Chauliac), \"formation of a pustule,\" from Medieval Latinaggregationem(nominativeaggregatio), noun of action from past-participle stem of Latinaggregare\"collect, bring together,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gregare\"to collect into a flock, gather,\" fromgrex(genitivegregis) \"a flock\" (from PIE root*ger-\"to gather\"). From 1540s as \"a combined whole;\" by 1560s as \"act of collecting in an unorganized mass.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggregator",
    "response": "1530s, \"an adherent;\" 1620s, \"a collector, compiler,\" agent noun fromaggregate(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggress",
    "response": "\"make an attack,\" 1714, probably a back-formation fromaggression; an identical word was used earlier with a sense of \"approach\" (1570s) and in this sense it is from Frenchaggresser, from Late Latinaggressare, frequentative of Latinaggredi\"to approach, attack.\" Related:Aggressed;aggressing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggression",
    "response": "1610s, \"unprovoked attack,\" from Frenchaggression(16c., Modern Frenchagression), from Latinaggressionem(nominativeaggressio) \"a going to, an attack,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaggredi\"to approach; to attempt; to attack,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gradi(past participlegressus) \"to step,\" fromgradus\"a step,\" figuratively \"a step toward something, an approach\" (from PIE root*ghredh-\"to walk, go\"). The psychological sense of \"hostile or destructive behavior\" is recorded by 1912 in A.A. Brill's translation of Freud."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggressive",
    "response": "1791, \"characterized by aggression, tending to make the first attack,\" with-ive+ Latinaggress-, past-participle stem ofaggredi\"to approach; to attempt; to attack,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gradi(past participlegressus) \"to step,\" fromgradus\"a step,\" figuratively \"a step toward something, an approach\" (from PIE root*ghredh-\"to walk, go\"). In psychological use from 1913, first in translations of Freud. The colloquial meaning \"self-assertive, pushy\" is from 1931. Related:Aggressively;aggressiveness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggressor",
    "response": "1670s, \"person who first attacks,\" from Latinaggressor, agent noun from past-participle stem ofaggredi\"to approach; to attempt; to attack\" (seeaggression)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggrieve",
    "response": "c. 1300,agreven, \"to disturb, trouble, attack,\" from Old Frenchagrever\"make worse, make more severe\" (Modern Frenchaggraver), from Latinaggravare\"make heavier; make worse or more oppressive,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +gravare\"weigh down,\" fromgravis\"heavy\" (from PIE root*gwere-(1)  \"heavy\"). The spelling was corrected toagg-in French 14c., in English 15c. Related:Aggrieved;aggrieving."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aggrieved",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"annoyed, incensed, resentful, angry;\" late 14c., \"oppressed in spirit,\" past-participle adjective fromaggrieve(v.). The legal sense of \"injured or wronged in one's rights\" is from 1580s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aghast",
    "response": "c. 1300,agast, \"terrified, suddenly filled with frightened amazement,\" past participle of Middle Englishagasten\"to frighten\" (c. 1200), froma-intensive prefix (seea-(1)) + Old Englishgæstan\"to terrify,\" fromgæst\"spirit, ghost\" (seeghost(n.)). The unetymological-gh-is perhaps a Flemish influence, or afterghost, etc., and became general after 1700."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agile",
    "response": "\"having quickness of motion, nimble, active\" (of body or mind), 1580s, from Frenchagile(14c.) and directly from Latinagilis\"nimble, quick,\" fromagere\"to set in motion, keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). Related:Agilely."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agility",
    "response": "early 15c., \"nimbleness, quickness,\" from Old Frenchagilité(14c.), from Latinagilitatem(nominativeagilitas) \"mobility, nimbleness, quickness,\" fromagilis\"nimble, quick,\" fromagere\"to set in motion; keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). Of mental swiftness from mid-15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aging",
    "response": "alsoageing, \"process of imparting age or the qualities of age to,\" 1860, verbal noun fromage(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agitate",
    "response": "1580s, \"to disturb,\" from Latinagitatus, past participle ofagitare\"to put in constant or violent motion, drive onward, impel,\" frequentative ofagere\"to set in motion, drive, drive forward,\" figuratively \"incite to action; keep in movement, stir up\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").The sense of \"move to and fro, shake\" is from 1590s. The meaning \"to discuss, debate\" is from 1640s, that of \"keep (a political or social question) constantly in public view\" is by 1828. Related:Agitated;agitating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agitation",
    "response": "1560s, \"debate, discussion\" (on the notion of \"a mental tossing to and fro\"), from Frenchagitation, from Latinagitationem(nominativeagitatio) \"motion, agitation,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofagitare\"move to and fro,\" frequentative ofagere\"to set in motion, drive forward; keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").The physical sense of \"state of being shaken or moving violently\" is from 1580s; the meaning \"state of being mentally agitated\" is from 1722; that of \"arousing and sustaining public attention\" to some political or social cause is from 1828. Old English glossed Latinagitatiowithunstilnis."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agitator",
    "response": "1640s, agent noun fromagitate(v.); originally \"elected representative of the common soldiers in Cromwell's army,\" who brought grievances (chiefly over lack of pay) to their officers and Parliament.The political sense is recorded by 1734, and negative overtones began with its association with Irish patriots such as Daniel O'Connell (1775-1847). Historically, in American English, often withoutsideand referring to people who stir up a supposedly contented class or race. Latinagitatormeant \"a driver, a charioteer.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agitprop",
    "response": "alsoagit-prop, \"political propaganda in the arts or literature,\" 1938, from Russianagitatsiya\"agitation\" (from Frenchagitation; seeagitation) +propaganda(seepropaganda), a word Russian got from German."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aglaia",
    "response": "name of one of the Graces, Greek, literally \"splendor, beauty, brightness,\" fromaglaos\"splendid, beautiful, bright,\" which is of unknown origin (probably connected withagauos\"noble, illustrious;\" seeagave), + abstract noun ending-ia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agleam",
    "response": "\"gleaming,\" 1854, froma-(1) +gleam(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aglet",
    "response": "alsoaiglet, \"metal tag of a lace,\" meant to make it easier to thread through the eyelet-holes, but later often ornamental, mid-15c., from Old Frenchaiguillette, diminutive ofaiguille\"needle,\" from Late Latinacucula, an extended form (via diminutive suffix, but not necessarily implying smallness) of Latinacus\"a needle\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\"). Compare Italianagucchia, Portugueseagulha, Spanishaguja\"needle.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aglimmer",
    "response": "\"in a glimmer, glimmering,\" 1828, froma-(1) +glimmer(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aglow",
    "response": "\"in a glow, glowing,\" 1817 (in Coleridge), froma-(1) +glow(v.). The figurative sense of \"flushed with pleasurable excitement\" is from 1830."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agnail",
    "response": "seehangnail."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Agnes",
    "response": "fem. proper name, mid-12c., from Old FrenchAgnes, from GreekHagnē\"pure, chaste,\" fem. ofhagnos\"holy, sacred\" (of places); \"chaste, pure; guiltless, morally upright\" (of persons), from PIE*yag-no-, suffixed form of root*yag-\"to worship, reverence\" (seehagiology).St. Agnes, martyred 303 C.E., is patron saint of young girls, hence the folk connection ofSt. Agnes' Eve(Jan. 20-21) with love divinations. In Middle English, the name was frequently written phonetically asAnnis,Annys. In U.S., among the top 50 names for girls born between 1887 and 1919."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agnostic",
    "response": "1870, \"one who professes that the existence of a First Cause and the essential nature of things are not and cannot be known\" [Klein]; coined by T.H. Huxley, supposedly in September 1869, from Greekagnostos\"unknown, unknowable,\" froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +gnōstos\"(to be) known\" (from PIE root*gno-\"to know\"). The coinage is sometimes said to be a reference to Paul's mention of the altar to \"the Unknown God\" in Acts, but according to Huxley it was a reference to the early Church movement known as Gnosticism (seeGnostic). The adjective also is from 1870."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agnosticism",
    "response": "\"doctrines of the agnostics, the doctrine that ultimate causes and essential natures of things are unknowable or unknown,\" 1870, fromagnostic+-ism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ago",
    "response": "\"gone, gone by; gone away,\" early 14c., a shortened form ofagon\"departed, passed away,\" past participle of a now-obsolete verbago,agon\"to go, proceed, go forth, pass away, come to an end,\" from Old Englishagan. This was formed froma-(1) \"away\" (perhaps here used as an intensive prefix) +gan\"to go\" (seego(v.)).As an adverb, \"in past times\" (as inlong ago) from late 14c. The formagoneis now obsolete except as a dialectal variant."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agog",
    "response": "\"in a state of desire; in a state of imagination; heated with the notion of some enjoyment; longing\" [Johnson], c. 1400,agogge, probably from Old Frenchen gogues\"in jest, good humor, joyfulness,\" fromgogue\"fun,\" which is of unknown origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agon",
    "response": "1650s, in reference to ancient Greece, \"contest for a prize,\" from Greekagōn\"struggle, trial,\" especially in the public games (seeagony) but also of contests for prizes in poetry, theater, music. Meaning \"verbal dispute between characters in a Greek play\" is from 1887. Related:Agonal."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agonic",
    "response": "\"having no angle,\" 1846, from Greekagōnos, froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +-gōnos\"angled,\" fromgōnia\"angle, corner\" (from PIE root*genu-(1) \"knee; angle\"). In reference to the imaginary line on the earth's surface connecting points where the magnetic declination is zero."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agonist",
    "response": "1876, in writings on Greek drama, \"a hero (attacked in the play by anantagonist),\" from Latinagonista, Greekagōnistes\"rival combatant in the games, competitor; opponent (in a debate),\" also, generally \"one who struggles (for something),\" fromagōnia\"a struggle for victory\" (in wrestling, etc.), in a general sense \"exercise, gymnastics;\" also of mental struggles, \"agony, anguish\" (seeagony).Agonistesas an (ironic) epithet seems to have been introduced in English by T.S. Eliot (1932)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agonistic",
    "response": "\"pertaining to an agonist,\" 1640s, from Latinized form of Greekagōnistikos, fromagōnistes(seeagonist)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agonize",
    "response": "1580s, \"to torture\" (trans.), from Frenchagoniser(14c.) or directly from Medieval Latinagonizare\"to labor, strive, contend,\" also \"be at the point of death,\" from Greekagōnizesthai\"contend in the struggle, contend for victory or a prize\" (in reference to physical combat, stage competitions, lawsuits), fromagōnia\"a struggle for victory,\" originally \"a struggle for victory in the games\" (seeagony). The intransitive sense of \"suffer extreme physical pain\" is recorded from 1660s; the mental sense of \"to worry intensely\" is from 1853. Related:Agonized;agonizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agony",
    "response": "late 14c., \"mental suffering\" (especially that of Christ in the Garden of Gethsemane), from Old Frenchagonie,agoine\"anguish, terror, death agony\" (14c.), and directly from Late Latinagonia, from Greekagōnia\"a struggle for victory\" (in wrestling, etc.), in a general sense \"exercise, gymnastics;\" also of mental struggles, \"agony, anguish.\" This is fromagōn\"assembly, mass of people brought together,\" especially to watch the games, hence, \"a contest,\" then, generally, \"any struggle or trial;\" from the verbagein\"put in motion, move\" (here specifically as \"assemble, bring together\"), from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move.\"Specifically of the struggle that precedes natural death (mortal agony) from 1540s. The sense development perhaps involves \"pain so severe as to cause struggling.\" Sense of \"extreme bodily suffering\" is recorded by c. 1600."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agora",
    "response": "1590s, \"open assembly place, chief public square and marketplace of a town; popular political assembly held in such a place,\" from Greekagora\"an assembly of the People\" (as opposed to a council of Chiefs); \"the place of assembly; a marketplace\" (the typical spot for such an assembly), fromageirein\"to assemble\" (from PIE root*ger-\"to gather\").The Greek word also could mean \"public speaking,\" and \"things to be sold.\" For sense, compare Romanforum."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agoraphobia",
    "response": "\"fear of crossing open spaces,\" 1873, from GermanAgorophobie, coined 1871 by Berlin psychiatrist Carl Westphal from Greekagora\"place of assembly, city market\" (but here with the general sense \"open space;\" seeagora) +-phobia\"fear.\" Related:Agoraphobe;agoraphobic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agrarian",
    "response": "1610s, \"relating to the land,\" from Frenchagrarienne, from Latinagrarius\"of the land,\" fromager(genitiveagri) \"a field\" (from PIE root*agro-\"field\").The specialized meaning \"having to do with cultivated land\" is recorded by 1792. Originally, and often subsequently, \"pertaining to the division or sharing of landed property,\" which was the Roman sense. Earlier in English asagrarie(1530s), from Latinagraria. As a noun, by 1650s (\"Oceana\") as \"an agrarian law;\" by 1818 as \"one in favor of redistribution of landed property.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agree",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to give consent, assent,\" from Old Frenchagreer\"to please, satisfy; to receive with favor, take pleasure in\" (12c.), a contraction of the phrasea gré\"favorably, of good will,\" literally \"to (one's) liking,\" or a like contraction in Medieval Latin. The French phrase is froma\"to,\" from Latinad(seead-) + Old Frenchgre,gret\"that which pleases,\" from Latingratum, neuter ofgratus\"pleasing, welcome, agreeable\" (from suffixed form of PIE root*gwere-(2) \"to favor\").In Middle English it also meant \"to please, gratify, satisfy,\" a sense preserved inagreeable. Of parties, \"come to agreement; make a settlement,\" mid-15c.; the meaning \"to be in harmony in opinions\" is from late 15c. Of things, \"to coincide,\" from 1520s. Toagree to differis from 1785 (alsoagree to disagree, 1792). Related:Agreed;agreeing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agreeable",
    "response": "late 14c., of things, \"to one's liking, pleasant, satisfactory, suitable,\" from Old Frenchagreable\"pleasing; in agreement; consenting\" (12c., Modern Frenchagréable), fromagreer\"to satisfy; to take pleasure in\" (seeagree). Of persons, \"willing or ready to consent,\" mid-15c. Related:Agreeably;agreeability;agreeableness. Todo the agreeable(1825) was to \"act in a courteous manner.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agreement",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"mutual understanding\" (among persons), also (of things) \"mutual conformity,\" from Old Frenchagrement,agreement, noun of action fromagreer\"to please\" (seeagree). Attested in English by early 15c. as \"formal or documentary agreement, terms of settlement.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agricultural",
    "response": "\"of or pertaining to or engaged in agriculture,\" 1766, fromagriculture+-al(1). Related:Agriculturally;agriculturalist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agriculture",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"tillage, cultivation of large areas of land to provide food,\" from Late Latinagricultura\"cultivation of the land,\" a contraction ofagri cultura\"cultivation of land,\" fromagri, genitive ofager\"a field\" (from PIE root*agro-\"field\") +cultura\"cultivation\" (seeculture(n.)). In Old English, the idea could be expressed byeorðtilþ."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agrimony",
    "response": "plant of the rosaceous genusAgrimonia, from Old Englishagrimoniafrom Latinagrimonia. Prior says it is \"probably\" from Greekargemōnē, \"but what this plant was, or why it was called so, is unknown.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agriology",
    "response": "study of prehistoric human customs, 1878, fromagrio-, from Greekagrios\"wild,\" literally \"living in the fields,\" fromagros\"field\" (from PIE root*agro-\"field\") +-logy. Related:Agriologist(n., 1875);agriological."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "agronomy",
    "response": "\"science of land management for crop production,\" 1796, from Frenchagronomie(1761), from Greekagronomos\"overseer of land.\" This is a compound ofagros\"a field, a farm; the country,\" as opposed to the town (seeagro-), andnomos\"law or custom, administering\" (see-nomy). Related:Agronomist;agronomic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aground",
    "response": "late 13c., \"on the ground,\" froma-\"on\" (seea-(1)) +ground(n.). Of ships and boats, \"stranded,\" from c. 1500."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ague",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"acute fever,\" also (late 14c.) \"malarial fever (involving episodes of chills and shivering)\" from Old Frenchague\"acute fever,\" from Medieval Latin(febris) acuta\"sharp (fever),\" from fem. ofacutus\"sharp\" (from PIE root*ak-\"be sharp, rise (out) to a point, pierce\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ah",
    "response": "mid-15c., an expression of surprise, delight, disgust, or pain in nearly all Indo-European languages, but not found in Old English (where the equivalent expression wasla!), so perhaps from Old Frencha\"ah!, oh! woe!\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ah",
    "response": "mid-15c., an expression of surprise, delight, disgust, or pain in nearly all Indo-European languages, but not found in Old English (where the equivalent expression wasla!), so perhaps from Old Frencha\"ah!, oh! woe!\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aha",
    "response": "expression of surprise or delighted discovery, late 14c.; seea-ha."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ahead",
    "response": "1620s, \"at the head, in front,\" froma-\"on\" (seea-(1)) +head(n.) \"front.\" Originally nautical (opposed toastern). The meaning \"forward, onward\" (the sense ingo ahead) is from 1640s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ahem",
    "response": "attention-getting interjection, c. 1600, lengthened fromhem, which is imitative of clearing one's throat (as if about to speak)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ahimsa",
    "response": "doctrine of non-violence, 1875, from Sanskritahimsa, froma\"without\" (from PIE root*ne-\"not\") +himsa\"injury.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ahoy",
    "response": "alsoa hoy, 1751, froma(probably merely a preliminary sound) +hoy, a nautical call used in hauling. The original form of the greeting seems to have beenho, the ship ahoy!"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ai",
    "response": "alsoa.i., by 1971, abbreviation ofartificialintelligence. Earlier in 20c. it stood forartificial insemination."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aid",
    "response": "early 15c.,aide, \"war-time tax,\" also \"help, support, assistance,\" from Old Frenchaide, earlieraiudha\"aid, help, assistance,\" from Late Latinadiuta, noun use of fem. ofadiutus, past participle of Latinadiuvare\"to give help to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +iuvare\"to help, give strength, support, sustain,\" which is from a PIE source perhaps related to the root ofiuvenis\"young person\" (seeyoung(adj.)).The meaning \"thing by which assistance is given\" is recorded from 1590s; the sense of \"person who assists, helper\" is from 1560s. The meaning \"material help given by one country to another\" is from 1940."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aide",
    "response": "\"officer whose duty is to receive and communicate the orders of a general officer,\" 1777, short foraide-de-camp(1660s), a French term in English, literally \"camp assistant\" (seeaid(n.)). Plural of the full term isaides-de-camp."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ail",
    "response": "Middle Englisheilen,ailen, \"trouble, afflict, harm,\" from Old Englisheglan\"to trouble, plague, afflict,\" from Proto-Germanic*azljaz(source also of Old Englishegle\"hideous, loathsome, troublesome, painful;\" Gothicagls\"shameful, disgraceful,\"agliþa\"distress, affliction, hardship,\"us-agljan\"to oppress, afflict\"), from PIE*agh-lo-, suffixed form of root*agh-(1) \"to be depressed, be afraid.\" Related:Ailed;ailing;ails.From late Old English also of mental states and moods. Phrasewhat ails you?\"what is wrong with you? why do you behave that way?\" is by c. 1300 (what eileth the?)"
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ailanthus",
    "response": "\"tree of heaven,\" type of fast-growing weed-tree native to China, brought to Europe and America in 18c.; 1807, Modern Latin, from Amboyna Malay (Austronesian)ailanto, said to mean \"tree of the gods.\" The spelling was altered by influence of Greekanthos\"flower\" (for which seeanther)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aileron",
    "response": "\"hinged flap on the trailing edge of an airplane wing,\" 1909, from Frenchaileron, diminutive ofaile\"wing,\" from Old Frenchele\"wing\" (12c.), from Latinala\"wing\" (seeaisle)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ailing",
    "response": "\"sick, ill, suffering,\" 1590s, present-participle adjective fromail(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ailment",
    "response": "\"sickness, disease, indisposition,\" 1706, fromail+-ment."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aim",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"to estimate (number or size), calculate, count,\" senses now obsolete, from Old Frenchaesmer,esmer(Old North Frenchamer) \"to value, rate; count, estimate,\" ultimately from Latinaestimare\"appraise, determine the value of\" (seeesteem(v.)).The meaning in English apparently developed from \"calculate,\" to \"calculate with a view to action, plan,\" then to \"direct a missile, a blow, etc.\" (late 14c.). It also was used in Middle English of directing a letter, planting an altar, pitching a tent. The intransitive sense of \"intend, attempt\" (early 14c.) was used by Shakespeare but is now considered colloquial. Related:Aimed;aiming."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aimless",
    "response": "\"without aim or purpose,\" 1620s, fromaim(n.) +-less. Related:Aimlessly;aimlessness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ainu",
    "response": "people native to northern Japan and far eastern Russia, 1819, from the Ainu self-designation, literally \"man, human.\" Once considered to be Caucasian, based on their appearance; DNA testing has disproved this. Their language is an isolate with no known relatives."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "air",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"invisible gases that surround the earth,\" from Old Frenchair\"atmosphere, breeze, weather\" (12c.), from Latinaer\"air, lower atmosphere, sky,\" from Greekaēr(genitiveaeros) \"mist, haze, clouds,\" later \"atmosphere\" (perhaps related toaenai\"to blow, breathe\"), which is of unknown origin. It is possibly from a PIE*awer-and thus related toaeirein\"to raise\" andarteria\"windpipe, artery\" (seeaorta) on notion of \"lifting, suspended, that which rises,\" but this has phonetic difficulties.In Homer mostly \"thick air, mist;\" later \"air\" as one of the four elements. Words for \"air\" in Indo-European languages tend to be associated with wind, brightness, sky. In English,airreplaced nativelyft,luft(seeloft(n.)). In old chemistry,air(with a qualifying adjective) was used of any gas.To bein the air\"in general awareness\" is from 1875;up in the air\"uncertain, doubtful\" is from 1752. To buildcastles in the air\"entertain visionary schemes that have no practical foundation\" is from 1590s (in 17c. English hadairmonger\"one preoccupied with visionary projects\"). Broadcasting sense (as inon the air,airplay) is by 1927. Togive (someone) the air\"dismiss\" is from 1900.Air pollutionis attested by 1870.Air guitaris by 1983.Air traffic controlleris from 1956."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aircraft",
    "response": "\"craft or vessel which navigates through the air,\" 1850,air-craft, in the writings of John Wise, originally in reference to balloons, fromair(n.1) +craft(n.). An image from boating, as were many early aviation words. Of airplanes from 1907 and since 1930s exclusively of them.Aircraft carrieris attested from 1919, in reference to H.M.S. Hermes, launched September 1919, the first ship built from the hull up as an aircraft carrier."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Airedale",
    "response": "type of terrier, 1880, named forAiredale, a district in West Riding, Yorkshire. The place name is from the riverAire, which bears a name of uncertain origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airedale",
    "response": "type of terrier, 1880, named forAiredale, a district in West Riding, Yorkshire. The place name is from the riverAire, which bears a name of uncertain origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airfoil",
    "response": "\"shaped surface that produces lift and drag when moving through air,\" especially of aircraft body parts, 1922, U.S. form ofaerofoil."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airhead",
    "response": "\"empty-headed person,\" 1972, fromair(n.1) +head(n.). Earlier as a term in mining (mid-19c.) and as a military term (1950) based onbeach-head."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airily",
    "response": "1766, \"pretentiously jaunty,\" fromairy\"with ostentatious air\" +-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airing",
    "response": "\"action of exposing to air,\" c. 1600, verbal noun fromair(v.). Meaning \"display, public exposure\" is from 1870."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airlift",
    "response": "alsoair-lift, 1893 as a type of pumping device; 1945 in the sense \"transportation of supplies by aircraft,\" fromair(n.1) +lift(n.). As a verb by 1949; popularized in reference to the U.S.-British response to the Soviet blockade of West Berlin. Related:Airlifted;airlifting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airman",
    "response": "alsoair-man, \"aeronaut,\" 1873 of pilots of balloons; 1910 of airplane pilots, fromair(n.1) +man(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airplane",
    "response": "1907,air-plane, fromair(n.1) +plane(n.1); though the earliest uses are British, the word predominated in American English, where it largely superseded earlieraeroplane(1873 in this sense and still common in British English).Aircraftas \"airplane\" also is from 1907. Lord Byron, speculating on future travel, usedair-vessel(1822); and in 1865aeromotive(based onlocomotive) was used, alsoair-boat(1870)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airport",
    "response": "alsoair port, \"facility for commercial air transport,\" used regularly from 1919 (used once, by Alberto Santos-Dumont, in reference to airships, in 1902), fromair(n.1) meaning \"aircraft\" +port(n.1). First reference is to Bader Field, outside Atlantic City, New Jersey, U.S., which opened in 1910. An older word for such a thing wasaerodrome."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airship",
    "response": "alsoair-ship, 1819, \"ship propelled by an air engine,\" fromair(n.1) +ship(n.). From 1888 as a translation of GermanLuftschiff\"motor-driver dirigible.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airstrip",
    "response": "alsoair-strip, a runway for aircraft, typically one without an air base or airport, 1942, fromair(n.1) meaning \"aircraft\" +strip(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airtight",
    "response": "alsoair-tight, \"impermeable to air,\" 1760, fromair(n.1) +tight. Figurative sense of \"incontrovertible\" (of arguments, alibis, etc.) is from 1929."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "airy",
    "response": "late 14c., \"of the air, containing air, made of air,\" fromair(n.1) +-y(2).The meanings \"breezy, exposed to the air, open to currents of air; lofty, high; light, buoyant; flimsy; flippant, jaunty, affectedly lofty; vain; unreal\" all are attested by late 16c. From 1620s as \"done in the air;\" 1640s as \"sprightly, light in movement;\" 1660s as \"visionary, speculative.\" Disparagingairy-fairy\"unrealistic, fanciful\" is attested from 1920 (earlier in a sense of \"delicate or light as a fairy,\" which is how Tennyson used it in 1830)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aisle",
    "response": "late 14c.,ele, \"lateral division of a church\" (usually separated from the nave or transept by a row of pillars), from Old Frenchele\"wing (of a bird or an army), side of a ship\" (12c., Modern Frenchaile), from Latinala, related to or contracted fromaxilla\"wing, upper arm, armpit; wing of an army,\" from PIE*aks-la-, suffixed form of root*aks-\"axis\" (seeaxis). The notion is of \"turning,\" which also connects it withaxle.It was confused from 15c. with unrelated Middle Englishile\"island\" (perhaps from notion of a \"detached\" part of a church), and so it took an unetymological-s-c. 1700 whenisledid; by 1750 it had acquired ana-, on the model of French cognateaile. Englishaisleperhaps also was confused withalley, which helped give it the sense of \"passage between rows of pews or seats\" (1731), which subsequently was extended to railway cars, theaters, Congress, etc."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aitch",
    "response": "\"the letterH,\" representing the pronunciation of the letter-name, by 1887, originally especially in reference to dropping it in colloquial speech."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aitchbone",
    "response": "\"rump-bone in cattle,\" also the cut of beef which includes this, late 15c., a misdivision of Middle Englishnache-bone(seeN), fromnache\"buttocks\" (c. 1300), from Old Frenchnache,nage\"the buttocks,\" from Medieval Latin*natica, from Latinnatis\"buttock,\" from PIE*not-\"buttock, back.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ajar",
    "response": "\"slightly open, neither open nor shut,\" 1718, alsoon a jar,on the jar, perhaps from Scottish dialectala char\"turned a little way,\" earlieron char(mid-15c.) \"on the turn (of a door or gate),\" from Middle Englishchar\"a turn,\" from Old Englishcier\"a turn\" (seechore). For first element seea-(1). For unusual change ofch-toj-, comparejowl."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Akan",
    "response": "people and language of West Africa (Ghana and surrounding regions), 1690s, a native name."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "akimbo",
    "response": "\"with the hands on the hips and the elbows bent outward at sharp angles,\" c. 1400,in kenebowe, of unknown origin, perhaps from Middle English phrasein keen bow\"at a sharp angle\" (withkeenin its Middle English sense of \"sharp\" +bow\"arch\"), or from a Scandinavian word akin to Icelandickengboginn\"bow-bent,\" but this seems not to have been used in this exact sense. Middle English Compendium compares Old Frenchchane/kane/quenne\"can, pot, jug.\" Many languages use a teapot metaphor for this, such as Modern Frenchfaire le pot a deux anses\"to play the pot with two handles.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "akin",
    "response": "1550s, \"related by blood,\" contraction ofof kin; seea-(1) +kin(n.). Figuratively, \"allied by nature,\" from 1630s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Akkadian",
    "response": "1855 (Accadian), fromAkkad(SumerianAgde, BiblicalAcca), name of city founded by Sargon I in northern Babylonia (the name is of unknown origin); applied by modern scholars to the East Semitic language spoken there (c. 2300-2100 B.C.E.) and preserved in cuneiform inscriptions."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alabama",
    "response": "created and named as a U.S. territory 1817 by a division of Mississippi Territory; ultimately named for one of the native peoples who lived there, who speak Muskogean. Their name probably is from a Choctaw term meaning \"plant-cutters.\" Related:Alabamian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alabaster",
    "response": "\"translucent, whitish, marble-like mineral used for vases, ornaments, and busts,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchalabastre(12c., Modern Frenchalbâtre), from Latinalabaster\"colored rock used to make boxes and vessels for unguents,\" from later Greekalabastros(earlieralbastos) \"vase for perfumes,\" probably a foreign word, perhaps from Egyptian'a-labaste\"vessel of the goddess Bast.\" Used figuratively for whiteness and smoothness from 1570s. \"The spelling in 16-17th c. is almost alwaysalablaster...\" [OED]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alabastrine",
    "response": "\"of or resembling alabaster,\" 1590s, from Medieval Latinalabastrinus, fromalabaster(seealabaster)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alack",
    "response": "expression of sorrow or dismay, mid-15c. contraction ofah, lack, which according to Skeat is fromlack(n.) in its secondary Middle English sense of \"loss, failure, fault, reproach, shame.\" According to OED, originally an expression of dissatisfaction, later of regret or unpleasant surprise. Sometimes extended asalackaday(\"alack the day\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alacrity",
    "response": "\"liveliness, briskness,\" mid-15c., from Latinalacritatem(nominativealacritas) \"liveliness, ardor, eagerness,\" fromalacer(genitivealacris) \"cheerful, brisk, lively;\" a word of uncertain origin. Perhaps cognate with Gothicaljan\"zeal,\" Old Englishellen\"courage, zeal, strength,\" Old High Germanellian. But de Vaan suggests the root sense is \"to wander, roam\" and sees a possible connection withambulare."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aladdin",
    "response": "name of a hero in stories from the \"Arabian Nights,\" from ArabicAla' al Din, literally \"height (or nobility) of the faith,\" froma'la\"height\" +din\"faith, creed.\" Figurative use often in reference to his magic lamp, by which difficulties are overcome, or his cave full of riches."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alamo",
    "response": "nickname of FranciscanMission San Antonio de Valeroin(begun 1718, dissolved 1793) in San Antonio, Texas; American Spanish, literally \"poplar\" (in New Spain, also \"cottonwood\"), fromalno\"the black poplar,\" from Latinalnus\"alder\" (seealder).Perhaps so called in reference to trees growing nearby (compareAlamogordo, New Mexico, literally \"big poplar,\" and Spanishalameda\"a shaded public walk with a row of trees on each side\"); but the popular name seems to date from the period 1803-13, when the old mission building was the base for a Spanish cavalry company from the Mexican town ofAlamo de Parrasin Nueva Vizcaya."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alan",
    "response": "masc. proper name, 1066, from Old BretonAlan, name of a popular Welsh and Breton saint; brought to England by the large contingent of Bretons who fought alongside William the Conqueror."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alan",
    "response": "masc. proper name, 1066, from Old BretonAlan, name of a popular Welsh and Breton saint; brought to England by the large contingent of Bretons who fought alongside William the Conqueror."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alar",
    "response": "\"wing-like,\" 1839; \"of or pertaining to wings,\" 1847, from Latinalaris, fromala\"wing, armpit, wing of an army\" (source of Spanishala, Frenchaile), from*axla, originally \"joint of the wing or arm;\" from PIE*aks-\"axis\" (seeaxis)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alaric",
    "response": "Visigothic masc. proper name, literally \"all-ruler,\" from Proto-Germanic*ala-\"all\" (seeall) +*rikja\"rule\" (from PIE root*reg-\"move in a straight line,\" with derivatives meaning \"to direct in a straight line,\" thus \"to lead, rule\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alarm",
    "response": "late 14c., \"a call to arms in the face of danger or an enemy,\" from Old Frenchalarme(14c.), from Italianall'arme\"to arms!\" (literally \"to the arms\"); this is a contraction of phrasealle arme.Alleis itself a contraction ofa\"to\" (from Latinad; seead-) +le, from Latinillas, fem. accusative plural ofille\"the\" (seele); witharme, from Latinarma\"weapons\" (including armor), literally \"tools, implements (of war),\" from PIE root*ar-\"to fit together.\"The interjection came to be used as the word for the call or warning (comparealert). It was extended 16c. to \"any sound to warn of danger or to arouse,\" and to the device that gives it. From mid-15c. as \"a state of fearful surprise;\" the weakened sense of \"apprehension, unease\" is from 1833. The variantalarum(mid-15c.) is due to the rolling-r-in the vocalized form. Sometimes in early years it was Englished asall-arm.Alarm clockis attested from 1690s (asA Larum clock)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alarmed",
    "response": "\"disturbed by prospects of peril,\" 1640s, past-participle adjective fromalarm(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alarmingly",
    "response": "1787, fromalarming, present-participle adjective fromalarm(v.), +-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alarmist",
    "response": "\"one addicted to sounding alarms,\" 1793, fromalarm(n.) +-ist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alarum",
    "response": "obsolete and poetic spelling ofalarm(q.v.), attested from Middle English and perhaps indicating a rolling \"r.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alas",
    "response": "mid-13c., from Old Frenchha, las(later Frenchhélas), fromha\"ah\" +las\"unfortunate,\" originally \"tired, weary,\" from Latinlassus\"weary\" (from PIE root*‌‌lē-\"to let go, slacken\"). At first an expression of weariness rather than woe."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alaska",
    "response": "large peninsula in northwestern North America, purchased by U.S. from Russia in 1867, a state since 1959. The name first was applied 18c. by Russian explorers, from Aleutalaxsxaq, literally \"the object toward which the action of the sea is directed\" [Bright]. Related:Alaskan.Baked Alaskais attested by 1896, so called either for its whiteness or for being cold inside."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alate",
    "response": "\"having wings, winged,\" 1660s, from Latinalatus, fromala\"wing, armpit, wing of an army,\" from*axla, originally \"joint of the wing or arm;\" from PIE*aks-\"axis\" (seeaxis)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alb",
    "response": "late Old Englishalbe\"white linen robe\" worn by priests, converts, etc., from Late Latinalba(intunica albaorvestis alba\"white vestment\"), fem. ofalbus\"white,\" from PIE root*albho-\"white\" (source also of Greekalphos\"white leprosy,\"alphiton\"barley meal;\" Old High Germanalbiz, Old Englishelfet\"swan,\" literally \"the white bird;\" Old Church Slavonic and Russianlebedi, Polishłabędź\"swan;\" Hittitealpash\"cloud\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alb",
    "response": "late Old Englishalbe\"white linen robe\" worn by priests, converts, etc., from Late Latinalba(intunica albaorvestis alba\"white vestment\"), fem. ofalbus\"white,\" from PIE root*albho-\"white\" (source also of Greekalphos\"white leprosy,\"alphiton\"barley meal;\" Old High Germanalbiz, Old Englishelfet\"swan,\" literally \"the white bird;\" Old Church Slavonic and Russianlebedi, Polishłabędź\"swan;\" Hittitealpash\"cloud\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albacore",
    "response": "name given to a large type of tuna caught in the Tropics, 1570s, from Portuguesealbacora, from Arabical bakara\"milk cow;\" the fish so called for its size."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Albania",
    "response": "Medieval Latin name of the country called by its inhabitantsShqipëri(literally \"land of eagles,\" fromshqiponje\"eagle\"), from Medieval GreekAlbania, which is possibly from a pre-IE word*alb\"hill\" (also proposed as the source ofAlps) or from the PIE root*albho-\"white\" (seealb). RomanAlbaniawas a land by the Caspian Sea (modern Daghestan); in EnglishAlbaniaalso was a sometime name for Scotland. Related:Albanian(1590s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albatross",
    "response": "\"large web-footed sea-bird of the petrel family,\" 1670s, probably from Spanish or Portuguesealbatros, an alteration ofalcatraz\"web-footed sea-bird; cormorant,\" originally \"pelican\" (16c.). This name is perhaps from Arabical-ghattas\"sea eagle\" [Barnhart]; or from Portuguesealcatruz\"the bucket of a water wheel\" [OED], from Arabical-qadus\"machine for drawing water, jar\" (which is said to be from Greekkados\"jar\"). If the second, the name would be a reference to the pelican's pouch (compare Arabicsaqqa\"pelican,\" literally \"water carrier\").The spelling was influenced by Latinalbus\"white.\" The name was extended by 17c. English sailors to a larger sea-bird (orderTubinares), which are not found in the North Atlantic. [In English the word also formerly was extended to the frigate-bird.]These albatrosses follow ships for days without resting and were held in superstitious awe by sailors. The figurative sense of \"burden\" (1936) is from Coleridge's \"Rime of the Ancient Mariner\" (1798) about a sailor who shoots an albatross and then is forced to wear its corpse as an indication that he alone, not the crew, offended against the bird. The prison-island ofAlcatrazin San Francisco Bay is named for pelicans that roosted there. In Dutch,stormvogel; in GermanSturmvogel\"storm-bird.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albedo",
    "response": "in astronomy \"proportion of light reflected from a surface,\" 1859, from scientific use of Latinalbedo\"whiteness,\" fromalbus\"white\" (seealb)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albeit",
    "response": "late 14c., a contraction ofal be it\"al(though) it be (that);\" seeallbeit. Chaucer also uses a past-tense form,al were it."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Albert",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from German (the French form isAubert), from Old High GermanAdalbert, literally \"noble-bright,\" from Old High Germanadal\"noble family,\" from Proto-Germanic*athala-(seeatheling) + second element from Proto-Germanic*berhta-\"bright\" (from PIE root*bhereg-\"to shine; bright, white\").The compound is cognate with Old EnglishÆþelbeorht(which sometimes was metathesized asÆþelbriht, hence the surnameAlbright). As a kind of watch chain, from 1861 (seePrince Albert)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alberta",
    "response": "Canadian province, founded in 1882 and named for Princess Louise CarolineAlberta, fourth daughter of Queen Victoria, wife of the governor general, John Douglas Sutherland Campbell, Marquess of Lorne. She was named for her father, PrinceAlbert."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albescent",
    "response": "\"becoming white,\" 1825, from Latinalbescentem(nominativealbescens), present participle ofalbescere\"become white,\" inceptive ofalbere\"be white\" (from Latinalbus\"white;\" seealb), with inchoative suffix-escere. Related:Albescence."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Albigensian",
    "response": "c. 1600, \"relating to theAlbigenses,\" collective name for the Catharist religious reformers of southern France c. 1020-1250, from Medieval LatinAlbigenses(12c.), from FrenchAlbi, name of the town in Languedoc where they lived and first were condemned as heretics (1176) and vigorously persecuted (theAlbigensian Crusade). The town name is from Roman personal nameAlbius, from Latinalbus\"white\" (seealb). Also sometimesAlbanesian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albinism",
    "response": "\"state or condition of being an albino,\" by 1821; seealbino+-ism. Alternative formalbinoismis recorded by 1835."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albino",
    "response": "\"a person of pale, milky complexion, with light hair and pink eyes,\" also used of an animal characterized by the same condition or a plant with white leaves or flowers, 1777, from Spanish or Portuguesealbino, from Latinalbus\"white\" (seealb). Used by Portuguese of white-spotted African negroes. Extended 1859 to animals having the same peculiarity. As an adjective formalbinoticis modeled onhypnoticand other words from Greek;albinisticalso is used. A female form, if one is still wanted, wasalbiness(1808)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Albion",
    "response": "ancient name of England, attested in Old English, from Latin, sometimes said to be from the non-Indo-European base*alb\"mountain,\" which also is suggested as the source of LatinAlpes\"Alps,\"Albania, andAlba, an Irish name for \"Scotland.\" But more likely from Latinalbus\"white\" (seealb), which would be an apt description of the chalk cliffs of the island's southern coast.Perfidious Albion, a reference to the supposedly treacherous policies of Britain when dealing with foreign powers, translates French rhetorical phrasela perfide Albion, said to have been in use since 16c. but popularized by Napoleon in the recruiting drive of 1813."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "album",
    "response": "1650s (albo) \"souvenir book,\" from Latinalbum, which in classical times was a board chalked or painted white, upon which public notices (theAnnales Maximi, edicts of the praetor, lists of senators, etc.) were inscribed in black, hence \"a list of names.\" Latinalbumis literally \"white color, whiteness;\" it is a noun use of the neuter of the adjectivealbus\"white\" (seealb).This Latin word was revived 16c. by German scholars, whose custom was to keep analbum amicorumof colleagues' signatures; its meaning then expanded to \"book with blank leaves meant to collect signatures and other souvenirs.\" Johnson [1755] still defined it as \"a book in which foreigners have long been accustomed to insert autographs of celebrated people.\"The English word in reference to bound photographic collections is recorded by 1859. The meaning \"long-playing gramophone record\" is by 1951, because the sleeves they came in resembled large albums."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albumen",
    "response": "1590s, \"white of an egg,\" from Latinalbumen (ovi)\"white (of an egg),\" literally \"whiteness,\" from the neuter ofalbus\"white\" (seealb). The organic substance (which exists nearly pure in egg whites) so called from 1800, also known asalbumin(1869, from Frenchalbumine)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albumin",
    "response": "chemical substance named for the Latin word for \"the whites of eggs,\" where it occurs naturally, 1869; seealbumen."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "albuminous",
    "response": "\"full of or containing albumen,\" 1791, fromalbumin, variant ofalbumen+-ous. Also sometimesalbuminose, as if from Modern Latinalbuminosus."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alchemical",
    "response": "\"relating to or produced by alchemy,\" 1580s; seealchemy+-ical. Related:Alchemistical(1550s);alchemically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alchemist",
    "response": "\"one who practices or is versed in alchemy,\" 1510s, from Old Frenchalquemiste, from Medieval Latinalchimista, from Old Frenchalchimie/Medieval Latinalkimia(seealchemy). Also see-ist. Earlier forms werealchemister(late 14c.),alkanamyer(late 15c.), with agent noun suffix-er."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alchemy",
    "response": "\"medieval chemistry; the supposed science of transmutation of base metals into silver or gold\" (involving also the quest for the universal solvent, quintessence, etc.), mid-14c., from Old Frenchalchimie(14c.),alquemie(13c.), from Medieval Latinalkimia, from Arabical-kimiya, from Greekkhemeioa(found c.300 C.E. in a decree of Diocletian against \"the old writings of the Egyptians\"), all meaning \"alchemy,\" and of uncertain origin.Perhaps from an old name for Egypt (Khemia, literally \"land of black earth,\" found in Plutarch), or from Greekkhymatos\"that which is poured out,\" fromkhein\"to pour,\" from PIE root*gheu-\"to pour\" [Watkins, but Klein, citing W. Muss-Arnolt, calls this folk etymology]. The word seems to have elements of both origins.Theal-is the Arabic definite article, \"the.\" The art and the name were adopted by the Arabs from Alexandrians and entered Europe via Arabic Spain. Alchemy was the \"chemistry\" of the Middle Ages and early modern times, involving both occult and natural philosophy and practical chemistry and metallurgy. After c. 1600 the strictly scientific sense went withchemistry, andalchemywas left with the sense \"pursuit of the transmutation of baser metals into gold, search for the universal solvent and the panacea.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alcohol",
    "response": "1540s (early 15c. asalcofol), \"fine powder produced by sublimation,\" from Medieval Latinalcohol\"powdered ore of antimony,\" from Arabical-kuhul\"kohl,\" the fine metallic powder used to darken the eyelids, fromkahala\"to stain, paint.\" Theal-is the Arabic definite article, \"the.\"Paracelsus (1493-1541) used the word to refer to a fine powder but also a volatile liquid. By 1670s it was being used in English for \"any sublimated substance, the pure spirit of anything,\" including liquids.The sense of \"intoxicating ingredient in strong liquor\" is attested by 1753, short foralcohol of wine, which then was extended to the intoxicating element in fermented liquors. The formerly preferred terms for the substance wererectified spiritsorbrandy.In organic chemistry, the word was extended by 1808 to the class of compounds of the same type as this (a 1790 translation of Lavoisier's \"Elements of Chemistry\" hasalkoholic gasfor \"the combination of alkohol with caloric\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alcoholic",
    "response": "1790, \"of or pertaining to alcohol;\" seealcohol+-ic. The meaning \"caused by drunkenness\" is attested by 1872; the meaning \"habitually drunk\" by 1910. The noun sense of \"one who is addicted to drinking in excess, chronic drunkard, old rounder\" is recorded from 1891; an earlier term for one wasalcoholist(1877 in clinical writing, earlier in temperance literature this word simply meant \"a drinker of alcohol\").Alcoholics Anonymouswas founded 1935 in Akron, Ohio, U.S."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alcoholism",
    "response": "\"disease of alcohol addiction,\" by 1882, fromalcohol+-ism, or else from Modern Latinalcoholismus, coined in 1852 by Swedish professor of medicine Magnus Huss to mean what we now would call \"alcohol poisoning, effects of excessive ingestion of alcohol.\" In earlier times, alcohol addiction would have been calledhabitual drunkennessor some such term."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alcoran",
    "response": "older form ofKoran, mid-14c., from Old Frenchalcoran, from Arabical-quran\"the Koran,\" literally \"the Book,\" with the definite article (al-) taken in European languages as part of the name."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alcove",
    "response": "\"vaulted recess,\" 1670s, from Frenchalcôve(17c.), from Spanishalcoba, from Arabical-qobbah\"the vaulted chamber,\" from Semitic baseq-b-b\"to be bent, crooked, vaulted.\" Theal-is the Arabic definite article, \"the.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alcyone",
    "response": "brightest of the Pleiades (Eta Tauri), in Greek myth a daughter of Aeolus; Latinized form of GreekAklyone, fromalkyon\"kingfisher,\" a word of unknown origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aldebaran",
    "response": "bright star in Taurus, late 14c., from ArabicAl Dabaran\"the follower\" (of the Pleiades, which rise shortly before it does), fromdabara\"he followed.\" Theal-is the Arabic definite article, \"the.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aldehyde",
    "response": "first oxidation product of alcohol, 1833, discovered in 1774 by German-born Swedish chemist Carl Wilhelm Scheele, the name said to have been coined by German chemist Justus von Liebig from abbreviation of Modern Latinalcohol dehydrogenatum\"dehydrogenated alcohol.\" Related:Aldehydic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alder",
    "response": "tree related to the birch, Old Englishalor\"alder,\" from Proto-Germanic*aliso(source also of Old Norseölr, Danishelle, Swedishal, Dutchels, Germanerle), from the ancient PIE name of the tree (source also of Russianolicha, Polisholcha, Latinalnus(Frenchaune), Lithuanianalksnis), from root*el-(2) \"red, brown,\" used in forming animal and tree names (seeelk).The unetymological-d-was added 14c.; the historical formallersurvived until 18c. in literary English and persists in dialects, such as Lancashireowler, which is partly from Norse."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alderman",
    "response": "Old Englishaldormonn(Mercian),ealdormann(West Saxon) \"Anglo-Saxon ruler, prince, chief; chief officer of a shire,\" fromaldor,ealder\"patriarch\" (comparative ofald\"old;\" seeold) +monn,mann\"man\" (from PIE root*man-(1) \"man\").Presumably originally of elders of the clan or tribe, but already in Old English used for king's viceroys, regardless of age. In later Old English a more specific title, \"chief magistrate of a county,\" having both civic and military duties. The word yielded under Canute toeorl(seeearl), and after the Norman Conquest tocount(n.). Having lost its specific sense,aldermanwas then applied to any head man; meaning \"headman of a guild\" (early 12c.) passed to \"magistrate of a city\" (c. 1200) as the guilds became identified with municipal government. Related:Aldermancy;aldermanic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aldine",
    "response": "typeface, 1837, fromAldusManutius (1450-1515), Venetian printer who used it in his popular editions of Greek and Roman classics. His name is a Latinized form of ItalianAldoManuzio; the first name is short forTeobaldo(seeTheobald), and, like many Italian masc. given names, of Germanic origin. The device characteristic of Aldine books is a figure of a dolphin on an anchor."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aldine",
    "response": "typeface, 1837, fromAldusManutius (1450-1515), Venetian printer who used it in his popular editions of Greek and Roman classics. His name is a Latinized form of ItalianAldoManuzio; the first name is short forTeobaldo(seeTheobald), and, like many Italian masc. given names, of Germanic origin. The device characteristic of Aldine books is a figure of a dolphin on an anchor."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ale",
    "response": "\"intoxicating liquor made by malt fermentation,\" Old Englishealu\"ale, beer,\" from Proto-Germanic*aluth-(source also of Old Saxonalo, Old Norseöl), which is of uncertain origin. Perhaps from a PIE root meaning \"bitter\" (source also of Latinalumen\"alum\"), or from PIE*alu-t\"ale,\" from root*alu-, which has connotations of \"sorcery, magic, possession, and intoxication\" [Watkins]. The word was borrowed from Germanic into Lithuanian (alus) and Old Church Slavonic (olu).Meaning \"festival or merry-meeting at which much ale was drunk\" was in Old English (seebridal)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aleatory",
    "response": "\"of uncertain outcome, depending on a contingent event,\" literally \"depending on the throw of a die,\" 1690s, from Latinaleatorius\"pertaining to a gamester,\" fromaleator\"a dice player,\" fromalea\"a game with dice; chance, hazard, risk; a die, the dice;\" perhaps literally \"a joint-bone\" (marked knuckle-bones used as early dice), \"a pivot-bone,\" and related toaxis.Aleatoric\"incorporating chance and randomness\" was used as a term in the arts from 1961."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alectryomachy",
    "response": "alsoalectoromachy, \"cock-fighting,\" 1650s, from Latinized form of Greekalektryon\"cock\" (seealectryomancy) +-machy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alectryomancy",
    "response": "\"divination by means of a cock and grains of corn,\" 1680s, from-mancy\"divination\" + Latinized form of Greekalektryon\"cock,\" literally \"warder-off, fighter,\" related toalexein\"to ward off, drive or keep off\" (seeAlexander, and compareAlekto, name of one of the three Furies). Perhaps originally a personal name, applied at first to the fighting cock, then to cocks generally. The earlier form of the word in English wasalectoromancy(1650s). Letters of the alphabet were traced on the ground and a grain of corn was placed on each."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alee",
    "response": "\"on or toward the lee side of a ship or boat,\" late 14c., froma-(1) +lee(n.). Nautical, opposed toaweather."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alehouse",
    "response": "alsoale-house, \"house where ale is retailed,\" Old Englishealahus; seeale+house(n.). In the same sense Old English had alsoealusele. Analehouse\"is distinguished from atavern, where they sell wine\" [Johnson]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alemanni",
    "response": "name of a Germanic tribe or confederation from the Elbe River region that in late Roman times settled along the upper Rhine in Alsace and part of Switzerland, from Proto-Germanic*Alamanniz, probably meaning \"all-man\" (seeall+man(n.)) and likely denoting a coalition or alliance of tribes rather than a single group.But on another theory perhaps meaning rather \"foreign men\" (compareAllobroges, name of a Celtic tribe in what is now Savoy, in Latin literally \"the aliens,\" in reference to their having driven out the original inhabitants), in which case theal-is cognate with the first element in Latinalius\"the other\" and Englishelse.The defeat of the Alemanni by a Frank-led army at Strasburg in 496 C.E. led to the conversion of Clovis and the rise of Frankish political power. The Alemanni were absorbed into the Frankish Kingdom in 796. Not historically important, but through proximity and frequent conflict with the Franks their name became the source of FrenchAllemand, the usual word for \"German, a German,\" andAllemagne\"Germany.\" In modern use,Alemannish,Alemannicrefers to the dialects of modern southwestern Germany;Alamannicrefers to the ancient tribes and their language."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alembic",
    "response": "\"distillation vessel used in old chemistry,\" late 14c., earlierlimbeck(mid-14c.), from Old Frenchalambic(13c.), via Old Spanish, from Arabical-anbiq\"distilling flask,\" via Persian, from Greekambix\"cup,\" a word of unknown, possibly Semitic, origin. Often spelledlimbeck15c.-17c. Theal-is the Arabic definite article, \"the.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aleph",
    "response": "name for the Hebrew and Phoenician first letter, ancestor ofA, c. 1300, from Semitic languages, pausal form ofeleph\"ox\" (the character might have developed from a hieroglyph of an ox's head); also seealphabet."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alert",
    "response": "\"on the watch,\" 1610s, from Frenchalerte\"vigilant\" (17c.), from prepositional phraseà l'erte\"on the watch,\" from Italianall'erta\"to the height.\" The second element is fromerta\"lookout, high tower,\" noun use of fem. oferto, past participle ofergere\"raise up,\" from Latinerigere\"raise\" (seeerect(adj.)).The adjective is attested from 1712; the noun is from 1796 as \"attitude of vigilance\" (as inon the alert); 1803 as \"a warning report.\" The verb is by 1864. Related:Alerted;alerting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alertly",
    "response": "\"in an alert manner, with watchfulness,\" 1763, fromalert(adj.) +-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alertness",
    "response": "\"state or quality of being alert,\" 1714, fromalert(adj.) +-ness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alethea",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from Greekalētheia\"truth, truthfulness,\" fromalēthēs\"true,\" literally \"not concealing,\" from privative prefixa-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +lēthē\"forgetfulness, oblivion, concealment\" (from PIE root*ladh-\"be hidden;\" seelatent)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aleut",
    "response": "native of the Aleutian Islands, 1780, of unknown origin, probably from a native word. First applied by Russian explorers c. 1750, perhaps fromAlut, name of a coastal village in Kamchatka [Bright]. Their name for themselves isunangax. Related:Aleutian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alewife",
    "response": "herring-like fish of North America, 1630s, named from the word for female tavern-keepers (attested from late 14c.), fromale+wife; the fish so called in reference to its large abdomen."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alexander",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from Latin, from GreekAlexandros\"defending men,\" fromalexein\"to ward off, keep off, turn (something) away, defend, protect\" +anēr(genitiveandros) \"man\" (from PIE root*ner-(2)  \"man\"). The first element perhaps is related to Greekalke\"protection, help, strength, power, courage,\"alkimos\"strong;\" and cognate with Sanskritraksati\"protects,\" Old Englishealgian\"to defend.\"As a kind of cocktail recipe featuringcrème de cacaoand cream,Alexanderis attested from 1913; the reason for the name is unclear."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alexandrine",
    "response": "in reference to a type of verse line, 1580s (adj.); 1660s (n.), said to be from Old FrenchRoman d'Alexandre, name of a poem about Alexander the Great that was popular in the Middle Ages, which used a 12-syllable line of 6 feet (the French heroic verse); it was used in English to vary the heroic verse of 5 feet. The name also sometimes is said to be fromAlexandrede Paris, 13c. French poet, who used such a line (and who also wrote one of the popular Alexander the Great poems)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alexia",
    "response": "\"inability to read\" as a result of some mental condition, 1878, from Greeka-\"not\" (seea-(3)) + abstract noun fromlexis\"a speaking or reading,\" fromlegein\"to speak,\" from PIE root*leg-(1) \"to collect, gather,\" with derivatives meaning \"to speak (to 'pick out words').\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alexia",
    "response": "\"inability to read\" as a result of some mental condition, 1878, from Greeka-\"not\" (seea-(3)) + abstract noun fromlexis\"a speaking or reading,\" fromlegein\"to speak,\" from PIE root*leg-(1) \"to collect, gather,\" with derivatives meaning \"to speak (to 'pick out words').\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alexis",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from Greekalexis, fromalexein\"to ward off, keep, protect\" (seeAlexander). The Latin form wasAlexius."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alfalfa",
    "response": "common name in North America for \"lucerne,\" a plant in the legume family important as a forage crop, 1845, from Spanishalfalfa, earlieralfalfez, said by Iberian sources to be from Arabical-fisfisa\"fresh fodder.\" Watkins says it is ultimately from an Old Iranian compound*aspa-sti-\"alfalfa, clover,\" from*aspa-\"horse\" (from PIE root*ekwo-\"horse\") +-sti-\"food,\" from suffixed form of PIE root*ed-\"to eat.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alfred",
    "response": "masc. proper name, Old EnglishÆlfræd, literally \"elf-counsel,\" fromælf(seeelf) +ræd\"counsel\" (seerede).Alfredthe Great was king of the West Saxons 871-899. Related:Alfredian(1814)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alfresco",
    "response": "seeal fresco."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alga",
    "response": "1550s, singular ofalgae(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algae",
    "response": "(plural), 1794, fromalga(singular), 1550s, from Latinalga\"seaweed,\" which is of uncertain origin. Perhaps connected to Latinulva\"grass-like or rush-like aquatic plant,\" or perhaps from a PIE root meaning \"to putrefy, rot,\" but de Vaan considers this unlikely and suggests it might be a foreign loan-word."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algal",
    "response": "\"of or pertaining to the algae,\" 1846, from Latinalga(seealgae) +-al(1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algebra",
    "response": "\"formal mathematics; the analysis of equations; the art of reasoning about quantitative relations by the aid of a compact and highly systematized notation,\" 1550s, from Medieval Latinalgebra, from Arabic\"al-mukhtasar fi hisab al-jabr wa al-muqabala\"(\"the compendium on calculation by restoring and balancing\"), the title of the famous 9c. treatise on equations by Baghdad mathematician Abu Ja'far Muhammad ibn Musa al-Khwarizmi. Arabical jabr(\"in vulgar pronunciation,al-jebr\" [Klein]) \"reunion of broken parts\" (reducing fractions to integers in computation) was one of the two preparatory steps to solving algebraic equations; it is from Arabicjabara\"reintegrate, reunite, consolidate.\" Al-Khwarizmi's book (translated into Latin in 12c.) also introduced Arabic numerals to the West. John Dee (16c.) calls italgiebar and almachabel. The accent shifted 17c. from second syllable to first.The same word was used in English 15c.-16c. to mean \"bone-setting,\" as was Medieval Latinalgebra, a usage picked up probably from Arab medical men in Spain."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algebraic",
    "response": "\"pertaining to algebra,\" 1660s, fromalgebra+-ic. Earlier wasalgebraical(1570s). Related:algebraically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Algernon",
    "response": "masc. proper name, literally \"with mustaches,\" from Old Frenchals gernons, froma les\"to the, with the\" +gernon, variant ofgrenon\"mustache,\" from Vulgar Latin*granonem, from a Germanic source (compare Old Englishgranu\"mustache\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Algol",
    "response": "variable star (Beta Persei) in the constellation Perseus, late 14c., literally \"the Demon,\" from Arabical-ghul\"the demon\" (seeghoul). It corresponds, in modern representations of the constellation, to the gorgon's head Perseus holds, but probably it was so called because it visibly varies in brightness every three days, which sets it apart from other bright stars.The computer language (1959) is a contraction ofalgo(rithmic) l(anguage); seealgorithm."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algolagnia",
    "response": "\"sado-masochism, sexuality that fetishizes violence and pain,\" 1900, Modern Latin, coined in German in 1892 by German doctor and paranormalist Albert von Schrenck-Notzing (1862-1929) from Greekalgos\"pain\" (see-algia) +lagneia\"lust,\" fromlagnein\"to lust\" (from PIE root*sleg-\"be slack, be languid\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algologist",
    "response": "\"student of seaweed,\" 1830, from Latinalga(seealgae) +-logist(see-logue). Related:Algology."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Algonquian",
    "response": "alsoAlgonkian, Native American people and language family, 1885, an ethnologist's word, fromAlgonquin, name of one of the tribes, +-ian. Both forms of the name have been used as adjectives and nouns. The people originally were spread over northeast and north-central North America, from Nova Scotia (Micmac) to Montana (Cheyenne). From 1890 in geology."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Algonquin",
    "response": "one of a Native American people living near the Ottawa River in Canada, 1620s, from FrenchAlgonquin, perhaps a contraction ofAlgoumequin, from Micmacalgoomeaking\"at the place of spearing fish and eels.\" But Bright suggests Maliseet (Algonquian)elægomogwik\"they are our relatives or allies.\"Algonquianwas the name taken late 19c. by ethnologists to describe a large group of North American Indian peoples, including this tribe. The Algonquin Hotel (59 W. 44th Street, Manhattan) opened 1902 and was named by manager Frank Case for the tribes that had lived in that area. A circle of journalists, authors, critics, and wits began meeting there daily in 1919 and continued through the twenties; they called themselves \"The Vicious Circle,\" but to others they became \"The Round Table.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algorism",
    "response": "13c., early alternative form ofalgorithm(q.v.), from Old Frenchalgorisme. Related:Algorismic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algorithm",
    "response": "1690s, \"Arabic system of computation,\" from Frenchalgorithme, refashioned (under mistaken connection with Greekarithmos\"number\") from Old Frenchalgorisme\"the Arabic numeral system\" (13c.), from Medieval Latinalgorismus, a mangled transliteration of Arabical-Khwarizmi\"native of Khwarazm\" (modernKhivain Uzbekistan), surname of the mathematician whose works introduced sophisticated mathematics to the West (seealgebra). The earlier form in Middle English wasalgorism(early 13c.), from Old French. The meaning broadened to any method of computation; from mid-20c. especially with reference to computing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "algorithmic",
    "response": "by 1799, \"arithmetical,\" fromalgorithm+-ic. In reference to symbolic rules or language, by 1881."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alhambra",
    "response": "palace of the Moorish kings in Granada, built 13c. and early 14c., a Spanish rendering of Arabic(al kal'at) al hamra\"the red (castle),\" from fem. ofahmuru\"red.\" So called for the sun-dried bricks of which its outer walls were built. Related:Alhambresque."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alias",
    "response": "mid-15c., \"otherwise called,\" from Latinalias(adv.) \"at another time,\" in Late Latin also \"in another way, under other circumstances,\" fromalius\"another, other, different,\" from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond,\" which is the source also of Englishelse."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alibi",
    "response": "1743, \"a plea of having been elsewhere when an action took place,\" from Latinalibi(adv.) \"elsewhere, somewhere else,\" locative ofalius\"another, other, different\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\"). The weakened sense of \"excuse\" is attested since 1912, but technically any proof of innocence that doesn't involve being \"elsewhere\" is anexcuse(n.) and not analibi."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alice",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from Old FrenchAliz, from Old High GermanAdalhaid, literally \"nobility, of noble kind\" (seeAdelaide). Among the top 20 most popular names for girls born in the U.S. c. 1880-1920. \"Alice's Adventures in Wonderland,\" published in 1865, was written for  Alice Pleasance Liddell (1852-1934)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alien",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"strange, foreign,\" from Old Frenchalien\"strange, foreign;\" as a noun, \"an alien, stranger, foreigner,\" from Latinalienus\"of or belonging to another, not one's own, foreign, strange,\" also, as a noun, \"a stranger, foreigner,\" adjective fromalius(adv.) \"another, other, different\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\").The meaning \"residing in a country not of one's birth\" is from mid-15c. The sense of \"wholly different in nature\" is from 1670s. The meaning \"not of this Earth\" is recorded by 1920. Analien priory(mid 15c.) is one owing obedience to a religious jurisdiction in a foreign country."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alienable",
    "response": "\"that can be surrendered or given up,\" 1610s; from obsoletealien(v.), for which seealienate, +-able. Related:Alienability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alienage",
    "response": "\"state of being alien,\" 1753, fromalien(adj.) +-age. Other abstract noun forms includealienship(1846);alienness(1881)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alienate",
    "response": "1510s, \"transfer to the ownership of another;\" 1540s, \"make estranged\" (in feelings or affections), from Latinalienatus, past participle ofalienare\"to make another's, part with; estrange, set at variance,\" fromalienus\"of or belonging to another person or place,\" fromalius\"another, other, different\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\"). Related:Alienated;alienating.In Middle English the verb was simplyalien,from Old Frenchalienerand directly from Latinalienare. It is attested from mid-14c. in theology, \"estrange\" (from God, etc.; in past participlealiened); late 14c. as \"break away (from), desert;\" c. 1400 in law, \"transfer or surrender one's title to property or rights.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alienation",
    "response": "late 14c.,alienacioun, \"action of estranging, disownment;\" early 15c., \"transfer of one's title to property or rights,\" from Old Frenchalienacionand directly from Latinalienationem(nominativealienatio) \"a transfer, surrender, separation,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofalienare\"to make another's, part with; estrange, set at variance.\" This is fromalienus\"of or belonging to another person or place,\" fromalius\"another, other, different\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\").Middle Englishalienationalso meant \"deprivation of mental faculties, insanity\" (early 15c.), from Latinalienarein a secondary sense \"deprive of reason, drive mad;\" hencealienist. Phrasealienation of affectionas a U.S. legal term in divorce cases for \"falling in love with someone else\" dates to 1861."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alienist",
    "response": "\"one who scientifically treats or studies mental illness,\" 1864, from Frenchaliéniste, fromalienationin the sense of \"insanity, loss of mental faculty,\" from Latinalienare\"deprive of reason, drive mad,\" literally \"to make another's, estrange\" (seealienate). The mental sense ofalienatehas since mostly died out in English, but Middle English hadaliened from mind\"deranged, not rational\" (late 14c.), andalienationwas used from 15c. in a sense of \"loss or derangement of mental faculties, insanity.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alight",
    "response": "\"to descend (from horseback, etc.), dismount,\" Middle Englishalighten, from Old Englishalihtan\"alight,\" originally \"to lighten, take off, take away,\" froma-\"down, aside\" (seea-(1)) +lihtan\"get off, make light\" (seelight(v.)). The notion is of getting down off a horse or vehicle, thus lightening it. Of aircraft (originally balloons) from 1786. Related:Alighted;alighting."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "align",
    "response": "early 15c., \"to copulate\" (of wolves, dogs), literally \"to range (things) in a line,\" from Old Frenchalignier\"set, lay in line\" (Modern Frenchaligner), fromà\"to\" (seead-) +lignier\"to line,\" from Latinlineare\"reduce to a straight line,\" fromlinea(seeline(n.)). Transitive or reflexive sense of \"fall into line\" is from 1853. The international political sense is attested from 1934. The French spelling with-g-is unetymological, andalinewas an early form in English. Related:Aligned;aligning."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alignment",
    "response": "1790, \"arrangement in a line,\" from Frenchalignement, fromaligner\"to arrange in a line\" (seealign). Political sense is from 1933."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alike",
    "response": "\"like one another, very similar,\" c. 1300,aliche,ylike,ilike, from Old Englishanlig,onlic\"similar, resembling;\" from Old Englishan,on(seea-(1) +like(adj.), which is related to Old Englishlic\"body, corpse.\"The notion is \"having a corresponding form (body).\" The more usual Germanic compound is represented by Old Englishgelic, from Proto-Germanic*galikam\"associated form\" (source also of Old Frisiangelik, Dutchgelijk, Germangleich, Gothicgaleiks, Old Norseglikr). As an adverb, late Old Englishonlice,gelice."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aliment",
    "response": "\"food, nutriment,\" late 15c., from Latinalimentum\"nourishment,\" in plural, \"food, provisions,\" fromalere\"to suckle, nourish\" (from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\"). Related:Alimental."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alimentary",
    "response": "\"pertaining to nutrition,\" 1610s, from Medieval Latinalimentarius\"pertaining to food,\" from Latinalimentum\"nourishment, food,\" fromalere\"to nourish, rear, support, maintain\" (from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alimony",
    "response": "1650s, \"nourishment,\" also \"allowance to a wife from a husband's estate, or in certain cases of separation,\" from Latinalimonia\"food, support, nourishment, sustenance,\" fromalere\"to nourish, rear, support, maintain\" (from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\") +-moniasuffix signifying action, state, condition (cognate with Greek-men). Derived formpalimonywas coined 1979, frompal(n.). Related:Alimonious."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aline",
    "response": "fem. proper name, French, short forAdeline."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alison",
    "response": "alsoAllison, fem. proper name popular in England and Scotland 13c.-17c., from FrenchAlison, a pet form ofAlice. As a surname, from this or representing \"Alice's son\" or in some cases \"Alan's son.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alison",
    "response": "alsoAllison, fem. proper name popular in England and Scotland 13c.-17c., from FrenchAlison, a pet form ofAlice. As a surname, from this or representing \"Alice's son\" or in some cases \"Alan's son.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alit",
    "response": "poetic past tense and past participle ofalight(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alive",
    "response": "c. 1200, \"in life, living,\" contraction of Old Englishon life\"in living, not dead,\" froma-(1) + dative oflif\"life\" (seelife). The full formon livewas still current 17c. Of abstract things (love, lawsuits, etc.) \"in a state of operation, unextinguished,\" c. 1600. From 1709 as \"active, lively;\" 1732 as \"attentive, open\" (usually withto). Used emphatically, especially withman(n.); as in:Thus it was abstracted as an expletive,man alive!(1845).Alive and kicking\"alert, vigorous,\" attested from 1823; Farmer says \"The allusion is to a child in the womb after quickening,\" butkickingin the sense \"lively and active\" is recorded from 1550s (e.g. \"the wanton or kicking flesh of yong maydes,\" \"Lives of Women Saints,\" c. 1610)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aliveness",
    "response": "\"life, vigor, state or condition of being alive,\" 1853, fromalive+-ness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkahest",
    "response": "\"universal solvent sought by alchemists,\" 1640s, from Frenchalcahest, from Medieval Latinalcahest, a pseudo-Arabic word coined by Paracelsus (comparealchemy)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkalescent",
    "response": "\"becoming or tending to become alkaline,\" 1732, fromalkali+-escent. Related:Alkalescence."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkali",
    "response": "late 14c., \"soda ash,\" from Medieval Latinalkali, from Arabical-qaliy\"the ashes, burnt ashes\" (of saltwort, which abounds in soda due to growing in alkaline soils), fromqala\"to roast in a pan.\" Later extended to similar substances, natural or manufactured. The modern chemistry sense is from 1813."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkaline",
    "response": "1670s, \"pertaining to alkalis,\" fromalkali+-ine(1). Of soils, from 1850. Related:Alkalinity."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkalize",
    "response": "\"render alkaline,\" 1725 (implied inalkalized), from Frenchalcaliser; seealkali."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkaloid",
    "response": "1831, fromalkali(q.v.) +-oid. \"A general term applied to basic compounds of vegetable origin, bitter in taste, and having powerful effects on the animal system\" [Flood], including morphine and nicotine. As an adjective by 1859."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alkanet",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"the plant alkanet\" or its root (which yields a red dye material and is used as a styptic), from Medieval Latin, from a diminutive ofalcanna, from Arabical-hinna(seehenna). As the name of the plant itself, from 1560s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alky",
    "response": "alsoalchy, 1841, \"an alcoholic drink\" (also \"alcoholic drink personified\"), a slang shortening ofalcoholicliquorfirst attested in temperance publications. As \"a drunkard\" (short foralcoholic(n.)) it is suggested by 1888."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "all",
    "response": "Old Englisheall\"every, entire, the whole quantity of\" (adj.), \"fully, wholly, entirely\" (adv.), from Proto-Germanic*alnaz(source also of Old Frisian, Old High Germanal; Germanall,alle; Old Norseallr; Gothicalls), with no certain connection outside Germanic. As a noun, in Old English, \"all that is, everything.\"Combinations withallmeaning \"wholly, without limit\" were common in Old English (such aseall-halig\"all-holy,\"eall-mihtig\"all-mighty\") and the habit has continued. Middle English hadal-wher\"wherever; whenever\" (early 14c.);al-soon\"as soon as possible,\"al-what(c. 1300) \"all sorts of things, whatever.\"Of the common modern phrases with it,at all\"in any way\" is from mid-14c.,and all\"and everything (else)\" is from 1530s,all but\"everything short of\" is from 1590s. First record ofall out\"to one's full powers\" is by 1880.All clearas a signal of \"no danger\" is recorded from 1902.All right, indicative of assent or approval, is attested by 1837; the meaning \"satisfactory, acceptable\" is by 1939, from the notion of \"turning out well.\"The use ofa,a'as an abbreviation ofall(as in Burns' \"A Man's a Man for A' that\") is a modern Scottishism but has history in English to 13c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Allah",
    "response": "Arabic name for the Supreme Being, 1702,Alha, from ArabicAllah, contraction ofal-Ilah, literally \"the God,\" fromal\"the\" +Ilah\"God,\" which is cognate with Aramaicelah, Hebreweloah(seeElohim)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allative",
    "response": "in reference to the grammatical case expressing motion towards, 1854, with-ive+ Latinallat-, past-participle stem of the irregular verbadferre/affere\"to bring to;\" from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +lātus\"borne, carried\" (seeoblate(n.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allay",
    "response": "\"put down, quiet, assuage, pacify,\" Middle Englishalegen, from Old Englishalecgan\"to put, place, put down; remit, give up, suppress, abolish; diminish, lessen,\" froma-\"down, aside\" (seea-(1)) +lecgan\"to lay\" (seelay(v.)). A common Germanic compound (cognates: Gothicuslagjan\"lay down,\" Old High Germanirleccan, Germanerlegen\"to bring down\").Early Middle English pronunciations of-y-and-g-were not always distinct, and the word was confused in Middle English with various senses of Romanic-derivedalloy(v.) and especially a now-obsolete verballege\"to alleviate, lighten\" (from Latinalleviare, fromad\"to\" +levis\"light\" in weight; from PIE root*legwh-\"not heavy, having little weight\").Hence the senses \"lighten, alleviate; mix, temper, weaken.\" The confusion with the Latin words probably also accounts for the unetymological double-l-, attested from 17c. Related:Allayed;allaying."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegation",
    "response": "early 15c., \"action of alleging, formal declaration in court,\" from Old Frenchalegacion\"allegation, affirmation\" (Modern Frenchallégation) and directly from Latinallegationem(nominativeallegatio) \"a sending, dispatching,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofallegare\"send for, bring forth, name, produce in evidence, send on business\" (seeallege). Specifically in law, \"assertion of a party to a suit or action, which he intends to prove.\" In general (non-legal) use, since 17c., often suggesting an assertion without proof."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allege",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"make a formal declaration in court;\" mid-14c., \"pronounce positively, claim as true,\" with or without proof; it has the form of one French verb and the meaning of another. The form is Anglo-Frenchaleger, Old Frencheslegier\"to clear at law\" (from a compound of Latinex\"out of;\" seeex-+litigare\"bring suit\" (seelitigation).Howevereslegiermeant \"acquit, clear of charges in a lawsuit,\" and the Middle English word somehow acquired the meaning of Frenchalléguer, from Latinallegare/adlegare\"send for, bring forth, name, produce in evidence, send on business,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +legare\"to depute, send\" (seelegate). Related:Alleged;alleging."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegedly",
    "response": "indicating assertion but not proof, 1828, fromalleged+-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alleger",
    "response": "\"one who alleges or affirms,\" 1570s, agent noun fromallege. The Latinate form,allegator(1680s) rarely is used, for some reason."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegiance",
    "response": "\"ties or obligations of a citizen or subject to a government or sovereign,\" late 14c.,alligeaunce, formed in English from Anglo-Frenchlegaunce\"loyalty of a liege-man to his lord,\" from Old Frenchlegeance, fromliege(seeliege(adj.)). Corrupted in spelling by confusion with the now-obsolete legal termallegeance\"alleviation, mitigation\" (for which seeallay(v.)). The general figurative sense of \"recognition of claims to respect or duty, observance of obligation\" is attested from 1732. Frenchallégeancein this sense is said to be from English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegorical",
    "response": "\"consisting of or pertaining to allegory, figurative, describing by resemblance,\" 1520s, earlierallegoric(late 14c.); from Frenchallégorique, from Latinallegoricus, from Greekallegorikos, fromallegoria\"figurative language, description of one thing in terms of another\" (seeallegory). Related:Allegorically. Anallegorical interpretationdraws spiritual or figurative meaning from historical matter."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegorize",
    "response": "\"turn (something) into allegory, interpret allegorically,\" 1570s; seeallegory+-ize. Related:Allegorized;allegorizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegory",
    "response": "\"figurative treatment of an unmentioned subject under the guise of another similar to it in some way,\" late 14c.,allegorie, from Old Frenchallegorie(12c.), from Latinallegoria, from Greekallegoria\"figurative language, description of one thing under the image of another,\" literally \"a speaking about something else,\" fromallos\"another, different\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\") +agoreuein\"speak openly, speak in the assembly,\" fromagora\"assembly\" (seeagora). Related:Allegorist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegretto",
    "response": "1740, in music, In music, indicating \"quicker in time than andante, but not so quick asallegro;\" from Italianallegretto, diminutive ofallegro(q.v.) \"brisk, sprightly.\" Also as a noun, a musical movement in such time."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allegro",
    "response": "1721 as a musical term, from Italianallegro\"brisk, sprightly, cheerful,\" from Latinalacrem(nominativealacer) \"lively, cheerful, brisk\" (seealacrity). The same Latin word came into English 17c. asaleger\"lively, brisk,\" from Old Frenchalegre, from Latinalacris; and Milton used\"L'Allegro\"in its literal sense as a poem title (1632)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allele",
    "response": "1931 in genetics, from Germanallel, abbreviation ofallelomorph\"alternative form of a gene\" (1902), coined from Greekallel-\"one another\" (fromallos\"other;\" from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\") +morphē\"form,\" a word of uncertain etymology."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alleluia",
    "response": "late 14c., from Latinalleluja, from Greekallelouia, from Hebrewhallelu-yah\"praise Jehovah\" (seehallelujah). Related:Alleluiatic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allemande",
    "response": "name of a German dance in 3/4 time, 1775, from FrenchAllemande, fem. ofallemand\"German\" (seeAlemanni). As a piece of music in a suite, 1680s. As a figure in country or square dancing, from 1808."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Allen",
    "response": "masc. proper name and surname, variant ofAlan(q.v.). In reference to a wrench, key, screw, etc. with a hexagonal socket or head, 1913, from theAllenManufacturing Company of Hartford, Connecticut, U.S."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allergen",
    "response": "\"substance causing allergy,\" 1912, fromallergyon model ofantigen."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allergic",
    "response": "\"having an allergy (to something),\" 1911, fromallergy(q.v.) +-ic; perhaps modeled on Frenchallergique(1906). The figurative use, \"antipathetic, repulsed\" is by 1936."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allergist",
    "response": "\"one who treats or studies allergic diseases,\" 1937, fromallergy+-ist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allergy",
    "response": "\"condition caused by hypersensitivity of the immune system to typically harmless substances,\" 1911, from GermanAllergie, coined 1906 by Austrian pediatrician Clemens E. von Pirquet (1874-1929) as an abstract noun from Greekallos\"other, different, strange\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\") +ergon\"work, activity\" (from PIE root*werg-\"to do\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alleviate",
    "response": "early 15c.,alleviaten, \"to mitigate, relieve (sorrows, suffering, etc.),\" from Late Latinalleviatus, past participle ofalleviare\"lift up, raise,\" figuratively \"to lighten (a burden), comfort, console,\" from assimilated form of Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +levis\"light\" in weight (from PIE root*legwh-\"not heavy, having little weight\"). Related:Alleviated;alleviating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alleviation",
    "response": "early 15c., \"mitigation, relief,\" from Medieval Latinalleviationem(nominativealleviatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofalleviare\"lift up, raise,\" figuratively \"to lighten (a burden), comfort, console,\" from assimilated form of Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +levis\"light\" in weight (from PIE root*legwh-\"not heavy, having little weight\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alley",
    "response": "mid-14c., \"passage in a house; open passage between buildings; walkway in a garden,\" from Old Frenchalee(13c., Modern Frenchallée) \"a path, passage, way, corridor,\" also \"a going,\" from fem. ofale, past participle ofaler\"to go,\" which is of uncertain origin. It might be a contraction of Latinambulare\"to walk\" (Watkins, seeamble(v.)), or it might be from Gallo-Romanallari, a back-formation from Latinallatus\"having been brought to\" [Barnhart]. Compare sense evolution ofgate.Applied by c. 1500 to \"long narrow enclosure for playing at bowls, skittles, etc.\" Used in place names from c. 1500. \"In U.S. applied to what in London is called aMews\" [OED], and in American English especially of a back-lane parallel to a main street (1729). To beup someone's alley\"in someone's neighborhood\" (literally or figuratively) is from 1931;alley-cat(n.) is attested by 1890."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alleyway",
    "response": "alsoalley-way, \"small, short alley,\" as between two houses, 1788, fromalley(n.1) +way(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alliance",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"bond of marriage\" (between ruling houses or noble families), from Old Frenchaliance(12c., Modern Frenchalliance) \"alliance, bond; marriage, union,\" fromaliier(Modern Frenchallier) \"combine, unite\" (seeally(v.)).The general sense of \"combination for a common object\" is from mid-14c., as are those of \"bond or treaty between rulers or nations, contracted by treaty\" and \"aggregate of persons allied.\" Unlike its synonyms, \"rarely used of a combination for evil\" [Century Dictionary]. Meaning \"state of being allied or connected\" is from 1670s. The Latin word wasalligantia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allied",
    "response": "c. 1300, past-participle adjective fromally(v.). Originally of kindred (comparealliance); in reference to a league or formal treaty, it is recorded by late 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alligator",
    "response": "1560s, \"large carnivorous reptile of the Americas,\"lagarto,aligarto, a corruption of Spanishel lagarto (de Indias)\"the lizard (of the Indies),\" from Latinlacertus(seelizard), with Spanish definite articleel, from Latinille(seele).The modern form of the English word is attested from 1620s, with unetymological-ras intater,feller, etc. (Alligarterwas an early variant) and an overall Latin appearance. The slang meaning \"non-playing devotee of swing music\" is attested from 1936; the phrasesee you later, alligatoris from a 1956 song title."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alliterate",
    "response": "\"begin with the same letter or sound,\" 1776 (implied inalliterated), back-formation fromalliteration. Related:Alliterating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alliteration",
    "response": "1650s, \"repetition of the same sound or letter at the beginning of words in close succession,\" from Modern Latinalliterationem(nominativealliteratio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofalliterare\"to begin with the same letter,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +littera(alsolitera) \"letter, script\" (seeletter(n.1)). Related:Alliterational."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alliterative",
    "response": "1764, \"characterized by alliteration,\" from stem ofalliteration+-ive. Related:Alliteratively;Alliterativeness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allocate",
    "response": "\"to set aside for a special purpose,\" 1630s, from Medieval Latinallocate(the common first word of writs authorizing payment), imperative plural ofallocare\"allocate, allot,\" from Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +locare\"to place,\" fromlocus\"a place\" (seelocus). It is a twin ofallow. Related:Allocated;allocating. Englishallocateas an adjective is attested from mid-15c. in legal use."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allocation",
    "response": "mid-15c.,allocacion, \"authorization,\" from Medieval Latinallocationem(nominativeallocatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofallocare\"allocate, allot,\" from assimilated form of Latinad\"to\" (seead-) +locare\"to place,\" fromlocus\"a place\" (seelocus)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allogenic",
    "response": "1888 in geology, \"transported to its present position from elsewhere,\" from Greekallogenēs\"of another race, stranger,\" fromallos\"other, another, different\" (seeallo-) +-genēs\"born\" (see-gen) +-ic. An earlier adjective wasallogeneous\"of a different kind or nature\" (1842)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allograph",
    "response": "\"writing made by another person,\" by 1900, fromallo-\"other\" +-graph\"something written.\" Especially in law, \"a deed not written by any of the parties to it.\" The linguistics sense of \"form of an alphabetic letter\" is from 1951; here the second element is abstracted fromgrapheme. Related:Allographic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allonym",
    "response": "\"false proper name,\" 1867, from Frenchallonymeor Germanallonym(1847), from Greekallos\"other\" (seeallo-) +onyma\"name\" (from PIE root*no-men-\"name\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allopath",
    "response": "\"one who practices allopathy,\" 1830, a back-formation fromallopathyor else from Germanallopath(1823)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allopathic",
    "response": "\"pertaining to allopathy,\" 1830, from Frenchallopathique, fromallopathie(seeallopathy). Related:Allopathically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allopathy",
    "response": "1836, \"treatment of disease by remedies that produce effects opposite to the symptoms,\" from GermanAllopathie(Hahnemann), from Greekallos\"other\" (from PIE root*al-\"beyond\") +-patheia, \"suffering, disease, feeling\" (see-pathy). It is the term applied by homeopathists to traditional medicine. A word unloved by classicists; it is malformed and the equivalent Greek compound had a different sense and was used in grammar, etc."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allot",
    "response": "\"parcel out, divide or distribute as by lots,\" late 15c., alsoalot, from Old Frenchaloter(Modern Frenchallotir) \"to divide by lots, to divide into lots,\" fromà\"to\" (seead-) +loter\"lot,\" a word of Germanic origin (cognates: Gothichlauts, Old High Germanhloz, Old Englishhlot; seelot). Related:Allotted;allotting;allotter;allottee."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allotheism",
    "response": "\"worship of strange gods,\" 1650s, fromallo-\"other\" +-theism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allotment",
    "response": "1570s, \"action of allotting,\" from Frenchallotement, from Old Frenchaloter\"divide by lots\" (seeallot). Or else a native formation fromallot+-ment. The meaning \"that which is allotted, portion assigned to someone or some purpose\" is from 1670s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allotrope",
    "response": "\"a form in which an element having the property of allotropy may exist,\" 1847, a back-formation fromallotropy\"variation of physical properties without change of substance,\" from Greekallotropos\"in another manner;\" seeallo-\"different\" +-trope\"way, manner.\" Diamond is anallotropeof carbon. Related:Allotropic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allotropy",
    "response": "in chemistry, \"property of existing in two or more distinct forms, variation of physical properties without change of substance,\" 1850, from French or Germanallotropie(1840), from Greekallotropia\"variety,\" fromallos\"different, other\" (from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\") +tropos\"manner, way\" (from PIE root*trep-\"to turn\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allow",
    "response": "early 14c.,allouen, \"to commend, praise; approve of, be pleased with; appreciate the value of;\" also, \"take into account or give credit for,\" also, in law and philosophy, \"recognize, admit as valid\" (a privilege, an excuse, a statement, etc.). From late 14c. as \"sanction or permit; condone;\" in business, of expenses, etc., by early 15c.The Middle English word is from Anglo-Frenchalouer, Old Frenchaloer,alloiier(13c.) \"to place, situate, arrange; allot, apportion, bestow, assign,\" from Latinallocare\"allocate\" (seeallocate). This word in Old French was confused and ultimately merged withaloer;alloer\"to praise, commend, approve,\" from Latinallaudare,adlaudare, a compound ofad\"to\" (seead-) +laudare\"to praise\" (seelaud).From the first word came the sense preserved inallowance\"money granted;\" from the second cameallowance\"permission based on approval.\" The 19c. U.S. colloquial meaning \"assert, say,\" also was in English dialect and goes back to 1570s. Related:Allowed;allowing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allowable",
    "response": "late 14c., \"worthy of praise;\" mid-15c., \"permissible, not forbidden,\" from Old Frenchalloable\"permissible, allowable,\" fromalloer\"allot, apportion, bestow\" (seeallow)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allowance",
    "response": "late 14c., \"praise\" (a sense now obsolete), from Old Frenchaloance\"sanction, granting, allocation,\" fromaloer\"allot, apportion, assign\" (seeallow). As withallow, the English word involves senses of two different French words.The meaning \"sanction, approval, tolerance\" is from 1550s. The sense of \"a sum allotted to meet expenses\" is from c. 1400. In accounts, the meaning \"a sum placed to one's credit\" is attested from 1520s. The mechanical meaning \"permissible deviation from a standard\" is from 1903. Tomake allowancesis to add or deduct a sum from someone's account for some special circumstance; figurative use of the phrase is attested from 1670s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alloy",
    "response": "early 14c. \"relative freedom of a noble metal from alloy or other impurities,\" from Anglo-Frenchalai, Old Frenchaloi\"alloy,\" fromaloiier(seealloy(v.)). The meaning \" base metal alloyed with a noble metal\" is from c. 1400. The modern spelling from late 17c. The meaning \"any mixture of metals,\" without reference to values, is from 1827."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allspice",
    "response": "spice made from the berry of the Jamaican pimento, 1620s, fromall+spice(n.), \"so called because supposed to combine the flavour of cinnamon, nutmeg, and cloves\" [Weekley]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allude",
    "response": "1530s, \"to mock\" (transitive, now obsolete), from Frenchalluderor directly from Latinalludere\"to play, make fun of, joke, jest,\" also of waves lapping the shore, from assimilated form ofad\"to\" (seead-) +ludere\"to play\" (seeludicrous). The meaning \"make an indirect reference, point in passing\" is from 1530s. Related:Alluded;alluding."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allure",
    "response": "\"tempt by the offering of something desired,\" c. 1400, from Anglo-Frenchalurer, Old Frenchaleurer\"to attract, captivate; train (a falcon to hunt),\" fromà\"to\" (seead-) +loirre\"falconer's lure,\" from a Frankish word (seelure), perhaps influenced by Frenchallure\"gait, way of walking.\" Related:Allured;alluring."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allurement",
    "response": "1540s, \"means of alluring;\" seeallure(v.) +-ment. The meaning \"act of alluring\" is recorded from 1560s. The verbal nounalluring(n.) \"action of attracting\" is from 1530s;allurance(1580s) sometimes has been used as well."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alluring",
    "response": "\"appealing to desires,\" 1570s, present-participle adjective fromallure(v.). Related:Alluringly."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allusion",
    "response": "1540s, \"metaphor, parable\" (a sense now obsolete); 1550s, \"word-play, joke;\" 1610s as \"passing or casual reference,\" from Latinallusionem(nominativeallusio) \"a playing with, a reference to,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofalludere\"to play, jest, make fun of,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ludere\"to play\" (seeludicrous). Anallusionis never an outright or explicit mention of the person or thing the speaker seems to have in mind."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "allusive",
    "response": "\"involving allusions,\" c. 1600, from Latinallus-, past-participle stem ofalludere\"to joke, jest\" (seeallude) +-ive. Related:Allusively;allusiveness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alluvial",
    "response": "\"deposited by flowing water,\" 1794; seealluvium+-al(1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alluvium",
    "response": "\"matter deposited by flowing water,\" 1660s, from noun use of Medieval Latinalluvium, neuter ofalluvius\"washed against,\" from Latinalluere\"wash against,\" fromad\"to, against\" (seead-) +-luere, combining form oflavere\"to wash\" (from PIE root*leue-\"to wash\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ally",
    "response": "late 13c.,allien, \"join in marriage\" (transitive), from Old Frenchalier\"combine, unite,\" from a differentiated stem ofaliier(from Latinalligare\"bind to, tie to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ligare\"to bind, bind one thing to another, tie\" (from PIE root*leig-\"to tie, bind\"). The meaning \"form an alliance, join, associate\" is late 14c. Related:allied;allying."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ally",
    "response": "late 13c.,allien, \"join in marriage\" (transitive), from Old Frenchalier\"combine, unite,\" from a differentiated stem ofaliier(from Latinalligare\"bind to, tie to,\" fromad\"to\" (seead-) +ligare\"to bind, bind one thing to another, tie\" (from PIE root*leig-\"to tie, bind\"). The meaning \"form an alliance, join, associate\" is late 14c. Related:allied;allying."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alma",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from LatinAlma\"nourishing,\" fem. ofalmus; fromalere\"to suckle, nourish,\" from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alma",
    "response": "fem. proper name, from LatinAlma\"nourishing,\" fem. ofalmus; fromalere\"to suckle, nourish,\" from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almagest",
    "response": "late 14c., title of a treatise on astronomy by Claudius Ptolemy of Alexandria, from Old Frenchalmageste(13c.), from Arabical majisti, fromal\"the\" + Greekmegiste\"the greatest (composition),\" from fem. ofmegistos, superlative ofmegas\"great\" (from PIE root*meg-\"great\").Originally titled in GreekMathematike syntaxis(\"Mathematical Composition\"), commonly calledMegale syntaxis\"Great Composition\" (Greekmegaleis the fem. ofmegas); Arab translators in their admiration altered this. The name was extended in Middle English to other works on astrology or astronomy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almanac",
    "response": "late 14c., \"book of permanent tables of astronomical data,\" attested in Anglo-Latin from mid-13c., via Old Frenchalmanachor directly from Medieval Latinalmanachus, a word of uncertain origin and the subject of much speculation. The Latin word is often said to be ultimately from Arabic somehow, but an exact phonological and semantic fit is wanting.OED connects it to a supposed Spanish-Arabical-manakh\"calendar, almanac,\" which is possibly ultimately from Late Greekalmenichiakon\"calendar,\" which itself is said to be of Coptic origin. The author ofEnglish words of Arabic Ancestrymakes a detailed case  \"that the word almanac was pseudo-Arabic and was generated within the circle of astronomers in Paris in the mid 13th century.\"One-year versions, showing correspondence of days of the week and month, ecclesiastical calendars, etc., date from 16c.; \"astrological and weather predictions appear in 16-17th c.; the 'useful statistics' are a modern feature\" [OED]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almighty",
    "response": "Old Englishælmihtig\"all-powerful,\" also a by-name of God; compound ofæl(seeall) +mihtig(seemighty); common Germanic (cognates: Old Saxonalomahtig, Old High Germanalamahtic, Germanallmächtig, Old Norsealmattigr), perhaps an early Germanic loan-translation of Latinomnipotens(seeomnipotent). Originally only of deities; general use is by late 14c.Related:Almightily;almightiness. A 15c. text translatesomnipotenciawithallmyghtyhede\"almightihood.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Almohades",
    "response": "12c. Muslim religious power that ruled Spain and North Africa, founded by Mohammed ibn Abdullah, the name is literally \"the Unitarians,\" short for Arabical-muwahhidun\"they who profess the unity (of God),\" so called for their absolutist monotheism."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almond",
    "response": "kernel of the fruit of the almond tree, c. 1300, from Old Frenchalmande,amande, earlieralemondle\"almond,\" from Vulgar Latin*amendla,*amandula, from Latinamygdala(plural), from Greekamygdalos\"an almond tree,\" a word of unknown origin, perhaps from Semitic. Late Old English hadamygdales\"almonds.\"It was altered in Medieval Latin by influence ofamandus\"loveable.\" In French it acquired an unetymological-l-, perhaps from Spanishalmendra\"almond,\" which got it by influence of the many Spanish words beginning with the Arabic definite articleal-. Perhaps through similar confusion, Italian has dropped the first letter entirely (mandorla). As an adjective, applied to eyes shaped like almonds, especially of certain Asiatic peoples, from 1849."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almoner",
    "response": "\"official distributor of alms on behalf of another,\" c. 1300 (mid-13c. as a surname), from Old Frenchalmosnier\"alms-giver\" (12c.; Modern Frenchaumônier), from Vulgar Latin*almosinarius, from Late Latinelemosinarius(adj.) \"connected with alms,\" fromeleemosyna\"alms\" (seealms). OED notes, \"the Renascence brought up a number of artificial spellings,\" and Middle English Compendium listsaumener, aum(s)ner, a(u)moner, aumerer, aumbrer, amener, ambner, aumoiner, almoiner, almer, andhalner."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almonry",
    "response": "\"place where alms are distributed,\" mid-15c.,aumeneri, from Old Frenchaulmosnerie; seealmoner+-ery."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Almoravides",
    "response": "Muslim Berber horde from the Sahara which founded a dynasty in Morocco (11c.) and conquered much of Spain and Portugal. The name is Spanish, from Arabical-Murabitun, literally \"the monks living in a fortified convent,\" fromribat\"fortified convent.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "almost",
    "response": "Old Englisheallmæst\"nearly all, for the most part,\" literally \"mostly all;\" seeall+most. The modern form is from 15c. The original sense is now typically expressed byalmost all; the sense of \"very nearly, all but\" is from c. 1200."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alms",
    "response": "\"charitable relief of the poor,\" especially as a religious duty, also \"that which is given to relieve the poor or needy,\" Old Englishælmesse\"almsgiving, act of relieving the needy,\" from Proto-Germanic*alemosna(source also of Old Saxonalamosna, Old High Germanalamuosan, Old Norseölmusa), an early borrowing of Vulgar Latin*alemosyna(source of Old Spanishalmosna, Old Frenchalmosne, Italianlimosina).This was a variant of Church Latineleemosyna(Tertullian, 3c.), from Greekeleēmosynē\"pity, mercy,\" in Ecclesiastical Greek \"charity, alms,\" fromeleēmōn\"compassionate,\" fromeleos\"pity, mercy,\" which is of unknown origin (Beekes gives it no etymology) and perhaps imitates cries of pleading. The spelling perversion in Vulgar Latin is perhaps by influence ofalimonia(seealimony)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aloe",
    "response": "name of a group of shrubs or herbs with spiky flowers and thick leaves, yielding bitter juice which was used as a purgative drug, late 14c., originally in reference to the drug, from Latinaloe, from Greekaloē, which is of uncertain origin, probably a loan-word from an Oriental language.A secondary sense is older in English: \"Fragrant resin or heartwood of an East Indian tree\" (Old Englishalewe,aloe), which is from misuse of Latin/Greekaloein Biblical translations for Hebrewakhalim(plural), which ultimately is perhaps from a Dravidian language. OED says the Greek word probably was chosen for sound-resemblance to the Hebrew one.The word then was misapplied in 1680s to the Americanagaveplant, which has a similar appearance (and also a Greek name) but is unrelated. The \"true aloe\" (producing the drug) consequently is calledaloe vera(with Latinvera\"true;\" seevery). Related:Aloetic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aloft",
    "response": "\"on high, in the air,\" c. 1200, from a Scandinavian source such as Old Norsea lopt\"up above,\" literally \"up in the air,\" froma\"in, on\" (seeon) +lopt\"sky, air, atmosphere; loft, upper room,\" from the general Germanic word for \"air\" (cognate with Gothicluftus, Old High Germanluft, Old Englishlyft\"air;\" seeloft(n.)). Scandinavian-pt-was pronounced as-ft-. The Old English equivalent wason þa lyft."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alone",
    "response": "\"unaccompanied, solitary; without companions,\" c. 1300, a contraction ofall ane, from Old Englishall ana\"unaccompanied, all by oneself,\" literally \"wholly oneself,\" fromall\"all, wholly\" (seeall) +an\"one\" (seeone). It preserves the old pronunciation ofone.Similar compounds are found in German (allein) and Dutch (alleen). The sense of \"and nothing else\" is from c. 1200, as in \"Man does not live by bread alone\" (Matthew iv.4, KJV; there Tyndale has \"man shall not lyve by brede onlye\"). Related:Aloneness. Adverbialalonelyseems to have become obsolete 17c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "along",
    "response": "Middle English, from Old Englishandlang\"entire, continuous; extended\" (adj.); also \"alongside of\" (prep.); fromand-\"opposite, against\" (from Proto-Germanic*andi-,*anda-, from PIE*anti\"against,\" locative singular of root*ant-\"front, forehead\") +lang\"long\" (seelong(adj.)).Reinforced by its Old Norse cognateendlang. The prepositional sense was extended in Old English to \"through the whole length of.\" Of position, \"lengthwise,\" from c. 1200; of movement, \"onward,\" from c. 1300. The meaning \"in company, together\" is from 1580s.All along\"throughout\" is attested from 1690s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alongshore",
    "response": "\"existing or employed along a shore or coast,\" 1779, fromalong+shore(n.). Comparealong-ships(adv.) \"lengthwise to the ship\" (1680s),alongside."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alongside",
    "response": "1707, \"parallel to the side of,\" a contraction of the prepositional phrase; seealong+side(n.). Originally mostly nautical. As a preposition from 1793."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aloof",
    "response": "1530s, \"to windward,\" froma-(1) \"on\" + Middle Englishloof\"windward direction,\" which is probably from Dutchloef(Middle Dutchlof) \"the weather side of a ship\" (seeluff(n.)).Originally in nautical orders to keep the ship's head to the wind, and thus stay clear of a lee-shore or some other quarter; hence \"at a distance but within view\" (1530s) and, figuratively, \"apart, withdrawn, without community spirit\" (with verbsstand,keep, etc.). As an adjective from c. 1600. Related:Aloofly;aloofness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alopecia",
    "response": "late 14c.,allopicia, \"falling of the hair,\" also a form of leprosy involving loss of facial hair, from Medieval Latinalopecia, from Greekalōpekia, a disease of the skin, alsoalōpekiasis, fromalōpēx,alōpekos\"fox.\" Also known asfox-sickness. Usually explained as transferred to the human condition from the animal's susceptibility to mange.Other theories are that it is so named \"from the fox's being supposed to lose its hair sooner than any other quadruped\" [Hoblyn's \"Dictionary of Terms Used in Medicine\"]."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aloud",
    "response": "late 13c., \"with a loud voice;\" c. 1300, \"audibly, not whispered;\" a contraction ofon loude; seea-(1) +loud."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alow",
    "response": "\"low down,\" mid-13c.; seea-(1) +low(adj.). Older thanbelow. Nautical use is by c. 1500."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Aloysius",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from Medieval LatinAloisius, from Old FrenchLoois(seeLouis)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alp",
    "response": "\"high, snow-capped mountain,\" especially in Switzerland, 1590s, fromAlps, from FrenchAlpes, from LatinAlpes\"the Alps,\" which is perhaps fromaltus\"high,\" oralbus\"white\" or from a Celtic word (according to Maurus Servius Honoratus the grammarian), or a borrowing from a non-Indo-European language.Alps, the central European mountain range, is attested by that name in English from late 14c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpaca",
    "response": "Andean mammal valued for its wool, 1792, from Spanishalpaca, probably from Aymaraallpaca, which is related to Quechua (Inca)p'ake\"yellowish-red.\" The unetymologicalal-is perhaps from influence of the many words in Spanish that contain the Arabic definite article (comparealmond). The word is attested in English from c. 1600 in the formpacos."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpenglow",
    "response": "rose-colored light on high mountains before dawn or after dusk, 1871, translating GermanAlpenglühen; seeAlp+glow(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpenhorn",
    "response": "\"long, powerful horn,\" formerly used to convey messages across valleys, 1864, from German, literally \"horn of the Alps;\" seeAlp+horn(n.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpenstock",
    "response": "\"long iron-pointed staff used for hiking in mountains,\" 1829, German, literally \"Alpine stick;\" seeAlp+stock(n.1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpha",
    "response": "c. 1300, from Latinalpha, from Greekalpha, from Hebrew or Phoenicianaleph(seealeph). The Greeks added-abecause Greek words cannot end in most consonants.The sense of \"beginning\" of anything is from late 14c., and in this it is often paired withomega(the last letter in the Greek alphabet, representing \"the end\"). The sense of \"first in a sequence\" is from 1620s. In astronomy, the designation of the brightest star of each constellation (the use of Greek letters in star names began with Bayer's atlas in 1603).Alpha malewas in use by c. 1960 among scientists studying animals; applied to humans in society from c. 1992."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alphabet",
    "response": "\"letters of a language arranged in customary order,\" 1570s, from Late Latinalphabetum(Tertullian), from Greekalphabetos, fromalpha+beta.It also is attested from early 15c. in a sense of \"learning or lore acquired through reading.\" Words for it in Old English includedstæfræw, literally \"row of letters,\"stæfrof\"array of letters,\" and compareABC.Alphabet soupis attested by 1907."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alphabetical",
    "response": "\"pertaining to an alphabet; in the order of the alphabet,\" 1560s, fromalphabet+-ical.Alphabetary(adj.) also is from 1560s;alphabeticis from 1640s. Related:Alphabetically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alphabetization",
    "response": "\"act of arranging alphabetically; fact of being alphabetically arranged,\" 1864, noun of action fromalphabetize(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alphabetize",
    "response": "1848, \"arrange alphabetically,\" fromalphabet+-ize. The older verb was simplyalphabet(1700). From 1854 as \"express by alphabetic letters.\" Related:Alphabetized;alphabetizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alphonso",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from SpanishAlfonso, from a Germanic source (compare Old High GermanAdalfuns, fromadal\"noble;\" seeatheling+funs\"ready\"). TheAlphonsine tables(1670s) are named for Alphonso the Wise, 13c. king of Castile, who had them compiled."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alpine",
    "response": "\"of the Alps,\" early 15c., from LatinAlpinus; seeAlp. Other adjectives wereAlpish(1590s),Alpian(c. 1600),Alpsian(c. 1600). With a smalla-, \"pertaining to very high mountains,\" 1845."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alpine",
    "response": "\"of the Alps,\" early 15c., from LatinAlpinus; seeAlp. Other adjectives wereAlpish(1590s),Alpian(c. 1600),Alpsian(c. 1600). With a smalla-, \"pertaining to very high mountains,\" 1845."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "already",
    "response": "c. 1300, \"in a state of readiness\" (an adjectival sense, now obsolete), literally \"fully ready, quite prepared,\" a contraction ofall ready; seeall+ready(adj.). Compare Norwegian, Danishallerede\"already.\" As an adverb, \"by this time, previous to some specified time,\" late 14c. The colloquial use in U.S. as a terminal emphatic (as inenough, already!) is attested from 1903, translating Yiddishshoyn, which is used in same sense. The pattern also is attested in Pennsylvania German and in South African."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alright",
    "response": "frequent spelling ofall right, attested in print by 1884."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alsatian",
    "response": "from the Latin form ofAlsace.Alsatianwas adopted 1917 by the Kennel Club for \"German Shepherd dog\" to avoid the wartime associations ofGerman; the breed has no connection with Alsace.Alsatiawas an old popular name for the White Friars district of London (1680s), which drew disreputable inhabitants owing to the privilege of sanctuary from a 13c. church and convent there; the image was of \"debatable ground\" (as Alsatia was between France and Germany). HenceAlsatian\"London criminal,\" 1690s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "also",
    "response": "Old Englisheallswa\"just as, even as, as if, so as, likewise,\" contraction ofeal swa, fromall\"altogether\" +so. Originally an emphatic form ofso.The sense of \"wholly so\" weakened to \"in addition to, in the same way,\" replacingeke. It was used in Old English to introduce a sequel to a preceding statement, \"and so, then, therefore.\" It was used from c. 1200 in connecting sentences, \"in addition, moreover.\" The compound has parallel forms in Germanalso, Dutchalzoo. Englishasis a shortened form of it."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alt",
    "response": "in Internet use (for examplealt.right), it is fromalt.*in the newsgroups naming system in Usenet. The term was introduced in 1987 and is said to be short foralternative, as it was meant to be outside the usual newsgroup administrative controls and thus include groups on controversial topics and pornography."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Altaic",
    "response": "1801 of the mountains; 1850 as an ethnic and linguistic family (comprising Turkish, etc.), from FrenchAltaïque, fromAltaïen, fromAltai, name of a mountain range in Asia between Russia and China, a name of uncertain origin."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Altair",
    "response": "bright star in the constellation Aquila, 16c., from ArabicAl Nasr al Tair\"the Flying Eagle,\" fromtair, participle oftara\"it flew.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altar",
    "response": "Old Englishalter,altar\"altar,\" from Latinaltare(pluralaltaria) \"high altar, altar for sacrifice to the great gods,\" perhaps originally meaning \"burnt offerings\" (compare Latinadolere\"to worship, to offer sacrifice, to honor by burning sacrifices to\"), but influenced by Latinaltus\"high.\"In Middle English, oftenauter, from Old Frenchauter. The Latin spelling was restored 1500s. As a symbol of marriage, by 1820.Altar-clothis from c. 1200.Altar-pieceis from 1640s;altar-boyfrom 1772."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alter",
    "response": "late 14c., \"to change (something), make different in some way,\" from Old Frenchalterer\"to change, alter,\" from Medieval Latinalterare\"to change,\" from Latinalter\"the other (of the two),\" from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\" + comparative suffix-ter(as inother). Intransitive sense \"to become otherwise\" first recorded 1580s. Related:Altered;altering."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alterable",
    "response": "\"capable of being varied or made different,\" 1520s, fromalter+-ableor else from Frenchaltérable. Related:Alterably;alterability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alteration",
    "response": "late 14c.,alteracioun, \"change, transformation, action of altering,\" from Old Frenchalteracion\"change, alteration\" (14c.), and directly from Medieval Latinalterationem(nominativealteratio), noun of action from past-participle stem of Late Latinalterare\"to change,\" from Latinalter\"the other (of the two),\" from PIE root*al-(1) \"beyond\" + comparative suffix-ter(as inother).The meaning \"change in character or appearance\" is from 1530s; that of \"change in ready-made clothes to suit a customer's specifications\" is from 1901. Related:Alterations."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altercate",
    "response": "\"to contend with words,\" 1520s, a back-formation fromaltercation, or else from Latinaltercatus, past participle ofaltercari\"to dispute (with another),\" fromalter\"the other\" (seealter)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altercation",
    "response": "late 14c.,altercacioun, \"angry contention with words,\" from Old Frenchaltercacion\"altercation\" (12c.) and directly from Latinaltercationem(nominativealtercatio) \"a dispute, debate, discussion,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofaltercari\"to dispute (with another),\" fromalter\"the other\" (seealter). The notion perhaps is of \"speaking alternately.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternate",
    "response": "\"following each other by turns, reciprocal,\" 1510s, from Latinalternatus\"one after the other,\" past participle ofalternare\"to do first one thing then the other; exchange parts,\" fromalternus\"one after the other, alternate, in turns, reciprocal,\" fromalter\"the other\" (seealter).Alternatemeans \"by turns;\"alternativemeans \"offering a choice.\" Both imply two kinds or things.Alternationis the process of two things following one another regularly by turns (as night and day); analternativeis a choice of two things, the acceptance of one implying the rejection of the other. Related:Alternacy."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternately",
    "response": "\"in an alternate manner,\" early 15c., fromalternate(adj.) +-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternating",
    "response": "1550s, \"occurring or acting by turns, one after the other,\" present-participle adjective fromalternate(v.). Electricalalternating currentis recorded from 1839, an electrical current which flows alternately in opposite directions without interruption."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternation",
    "response": "\"act of alternating; state of being alternate,\" mid-15c.,alternacioun, from Old Frenchalternacion\"alternation,\" from Latinalternationem(nominativealternatio) \"an interchanging,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofalternare\"to do first one thing then the other; exchange parts,\" fromalternus\"one after the other, alternate, in turns, reciprocal,\" fromalter\"the other\" (seealter)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternative",
    "response": "1580s, \"offering one or the other of two,\" from Medieval Latinalternativus, from Latinalternatus, past participle ofalternare\"do one thing and then another, do by turns,\" fromalternus\"one after the other, alternate, in turns, reciprocal,\" fromalter\"the other\" (seealter). The meaning \"purporting to be a superior choice to what is in general use\" was current by 1970 (earliest reference is to the media); in popular music, by 1984 in reference to pirate radio.Alternative energyis from 1975. Related:Alternatively."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alternator",
    "response": "1878, \"dynamo-electric machine which produces an alternating current,\" agent noun in Latin form fromalternate(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "although",
    "response": "early 14c.,althagh, \"admitting that, in spite of the fact that,\" a contraction ofallthough, preserving the once-common emphatic use ofall. \"All thoughwas originally more emphatic thanthough, but by 1400 it was practically only a variant of it, andallhaving thus lost its independent force, the phrase was written as one word\" [OED]. The choice betweenalthoughandthoughoften is determined by metrics."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altimeter",
    "response": "\"instrument for measuring altitudes,\" 1918, fromalti-\"high\" +-meter."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altimetry",
    "response": "\"the art of measuring heights,\" 1690s, from Medieval Latinaltimetria, from Latinalti-\"high\" (seealti-) + Greek-metria\"a measuring of\" (see-metry). Related:Altimetric."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altitude",
    "response": "late 14c., \"elevation above the horizon\" (of stars, planets), from Latinaltitudinem(nominativealtitudo) \"height, altitude,\" fromaltus\"high\" (literally \"grown tall,\" from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\"). The general sense of \"space upward, height, vertical extent\" is from early 15c. Related:Altitudinal;altitudinous."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alto",
    "response": "1784, \"man with an alto voice,\" literally \"high,\" from Italianalto (canto), from Latinaltus\"high\" (literally \"grown tall,\" from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\"). Originally a man's high voice; now more commonly applied to the lower range of women's voices (which is more strictly thecontralto), an extension attested by 1848. It is so called because higher than thetenor, which in old music had the melody.As a type of saxophone, from 1869. Also an old name for the viola (1833), from Italian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altogether",
    "response": "\"wholly, entirely, completely,\" early 13c.,altogedere, a strengthened form ofall(also seetogether); used in the sense of \"a whole\" from 1660s. OED notes, \"There is a common tendency to writealtogetherwhereall togetheris logically preferable,\" and gives examples from 1765.The altogether\"a condition of nakedness\" is from 1894, probably from the notion of \"completely\" naked."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altruism",
    "response": "1853, \"unselfishness, devotion to the welfare of others, the opposite ofegoism,\" from Frenchaltruisme, coined or popularized 1830 by French philosopher Auguste Comte, with-ism+autrui(Old Frenchaltrui) \"of or to others,\" from Latinalteri, dative ofalter\"other\" (seealter). The-l-in the French coinage perhaps is an etymological reinsertion from the Latin word."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altruist",
    "response": "\"person devoted to the welfare of others,\" 1842, from Frenchaltruiste; seealtruism+-ist."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "altruistic",
    "response": "\"having regard for the interest and well-being of others,\" 1853, fromaltruist+-ic. Related:Altruistically."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alum",
    "response": "\"whitish mineral salt used as an astringent, dye, etc.,\" late 14c., from Old Frenchalum,alun, from Latinalumen\"alum,\" also \"the alum plant,\" from Proto-Italic*alu-\"bitter substance\" literally \"bitter salt,\" cognate with Greekaludoimos\"bitter\" and perhaps with Englishaleand some Balto-Slavic words for \"beer\" (such as Lithuanian alus). The plant's medicinal use on wounds was known to Pliny."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aluminium",
    "response": "1812, chiefly British form ofaluminum(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "aluminum",
    "response": "1812, coined by English chemist Sir Humphry Davy, fromalumina,alumine, the name given by French chemists late 18c. to aluminum oxide, from Latinalumen\"alum\" (seealum). Davy originally called italumium(1808), then amended this toaluminum, which remains the U.S. word. British editors in 1812 further amended it toaluminium, the modern preferred British form, to better harmonize with other metallic element names (sodium,potassium, etc.).Aluminum foilattested by 1859; popularized in food packaging from c. 1950."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alumna",
    "response": "\"female pupil or graduate of a school,\" 1860, fem. ofalumnus(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alumnae",
    "response": "\"female pupils or graduates of a school,\" fem. plural ofalumnus(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alumni",
    "response": "\"pupils or graduates of a school,\" plural ofalumnus(q.v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alumnus",
    "response": "\"pupil or graduate of a school,\" 1640s, from Latinalumnus\"a pupil,\" literally \"foster son,\" vestigial present passive participle ofalere\"to suckle, nourish\" (from PIE root*al-(2) \"to grow, nourish\"). With ending akin to Greek-omenos. Plural isalumni. The fem. form isalumna(1882), pluralalumnae."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alveolar",
    "response": "1799, \"pertaining to the sockets of the teeth,\" from a modern medical use of Latinalveolus\"socket, small hollow or cavity\" (seealveolus) +-ar. Sense extended 19c. to other anatomical hollows."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "alveolus",
    "response": "1706, \"a hollow,\" especially \"the socket of a tooth,\" from Latinalveolus\"a tray, trough, basin; bed of a small river; small hollow or cavity,\" diminutive ofalvus\"belly, stomach, paunch, bowels; hold of a ship,\" from PIE root*aulo-\"hole, cavity\" (source also of Greekaulos\"flute, tube, pipe;\" Serbo-Croatian, Polish, Russianulica\"street,\" originally \"narrow opening;\" Old Church Slavoniculiji, Lithuanianaulys\"beehive\" (hollow trunk), Armenianyli\"pregnant\"). The word was extended in 19c. anatomy to other small pits, sockets, or cells."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "always",
    "response": "mid-14c., contraction of Old English phraseealne weg\"all the time; quite, perpetually,\" literally \"all the way,\" with accusative of space or distance, though the oldest recorded usages refer to time; seeall+way(n.). The adverbial genitive-sappeared early 13c., was rare before c. 1400, but is now standard, though the variantalwaysurvived, archaic, into the 1800s for the sake of poetry (as in \"I Would Not Live Alway\"). Meaning \"every time\" is from early 13c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Alyssum",
    "response": "type of European flowering plant, 1550s, from Latinalysson, from Greekalysson, which is perhaps the neuter of adjectivealyssos\"curing madness,\" froma-\"not, without\" (seea-(3)) +lyssa\"madness, martial rage, fury,\" an abstract word probably literally \"wolf-ness\" and related tolykos\"wolf\" (seewolf(n.)); but some see a connection with \"light\" words, in reference to the glittering eyes of the mad."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "am",
    "response": "first-person singular present indicative ofbe(q.v.); Old Englisheom\"to be, to remain,\" (Mercianeam, Northumbrianam), from Proto-Germanic*izm(i)-, from PIE*esmi-(source also of Old Norseemi, Gothicim, Hittiteesmi, Old Church Slavonicjesmi, Lithuanianesmi), first-person singular form of the root*es-\"to be.\"In Old English it formed only present tenses, other forms being expressed in the \"W-base\" (seewere,was). This cooperative verb is sometimes referred to by linguists as*es-*wes-. Until the distinction broke down 13c.,*es-*wes-tended to express \"existence,\" withbeonmeaning something closer to \"come to be.\"Old Englishamhad two plural forms: 1.sind/sindon, sieand 2.earon/aron. Thes-form (also used in the subjunctive) fell from English in the early 13c. (though its cousin continues in Germansind, the third-person plural of \"to be\") and was replaced by forms ofbe, butaron(seeare) continued, and asamandbemerged it encroached on some uses that previously had belonged tobe. By the early 1500s it had established its place in standard English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amah",
    "response": "\"wet-nurse,\" 1839, Anglo-Indian, from Portugueseama\"nurse,\" from Medieval Latinamma\"mother\" (from PIE root*am-, forming nursery words); no doubt also from or combined withamma\"mother\" in Telegu, etc."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amain",
    "response": "\"with violence, strength, or force,\" 1530s, frommain(adj.) by analogy with other words ina-(such asafoot)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amalgam",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"a blend of mercury with another metal; soft mass formed by chemical manipulation,\" from Old Frenchamalgameor directly from Medieval Latinamalgama, \"alloy of mercury (especially with gold or silver),\" c. 1300, an alchemists' word, probably from Arabical-malgham\"an emollient poultice or unguent for sores (especially warm)\" [Francis Johnson, \"A Dictionary of Persian, Arabic, and English\"], which is itself perhaps from Greekmalagma\"softening substance,\" frommalassein\"to soften,\" frommalakos\"soft\" (from PIE*meldh-, from root*mel-(1) \"soft\"). The figurative meaning \"compound of different things\" is from 1790."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amalgamate",
    "response": "1650s, \"mix (a metal) with mercury,\" a back-formation fromamalgamation, or else from the obsolete adjectiveamalgamate(1640s) fromamalgam(q.v.). Originally in metallurgy. The figurative transitive sense of \"to unite\" (races, etc.) is attested from 1802; the intransitive sense of \"to combine, unite into one body\" is from 1797. Related:Amalgamated;amalgamating. Earlier verbs wereamalgam(1540s);amalgamize(1590s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amalgamation",
    "response": "1610s, \"act of compounding mercury with another metal,\" noun of action from archaicamalgam(v.) \"to alloy with mercury\" (seeamalgamate). The figurative, non-chemical sense of \"a combining of different things into one uniform whole\" is attested from 1775. Especially of the union or merger of corporations under one direction."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amalgamize",
    "response": "1590s, \"reduce to a soft mass by combination with mercury,\" fromamalgam+-ize. Related:Amalgamized;amalgamizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amanda",
    "response": "fem. proper name, literally \"worthy to be loved,\" fem. of Latinamandus\"pleasing,\" gerundive ofamare\"to love\" (seeAmy). A top 10 list name for girls born in U.S. between 1976 and 1995."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amanuensis",
    "response": "\"one who takes dictation or copies what is written by another,\" 1610s, from Latinamanuensis\"adjective used as a noun,\" an alteration of(servus) a manu\"secretary,\" literally \"servant from the hand;\" fromaforab\"from, of,\" here used as a designation of office (seeab-), +manu, ablative ofmanus\"hand\" (from PIE root*man-(2) \"hand\"). With-ensis, for which see-ese."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amaranth",
    "response": "1610s, from Frenchamarante, from Latinamarantus/amaranthus, from Greekamarantos, name of a mythical unfading flower, literally \"unfading, undecaying,\" froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) + stem ofmarainein\"die away, waste away, decay, wither; quench, extinguish,\" from PIE root*mer-\"to rub away, harm\" (also \"to die\" and forming words referring to death and to beings subject to death).In classical use, a poet's word for an imaginary flower that never fades. It was applied in botany to a genus of ornamental plants 1550s. The ending has been influenced by plant names from unrelated Greek-anthos\"flower.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amaranthine",
    "response": "1660s, \"unfading, undying,\" poetic (apparently coined by Milton), alsoamarantine; seeamaranth, the name of a mythical unfading flower, +-ine(1). From late 19c. in reference to a purple color similar to that of the (non-mythical) flowers of the ornamental plant so-called by botanists."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amarillo",
    "response": "name of several species of American trees, from Spanish, from Arabicanbari\"yellow, amber-colored,\" fromanbar\"amber\" (seeamber). The cityAmarilloin Texas, U.S., may be so called from the color of the banks of a nearby stream."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amaryllis",
    "response": "autumn-flowering bulb, 1794, adopted by Linnaeus from Latin, from GreekAmaryllis, a typical name of a country girl or shepherdess (in Theocritus, Virgil, Ovid, etc.), fromamaryssein\"to sparkle, twinkle, glance,\" as the eye, a word which according to Beekes \"may well be of Pre-Greek origin.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amass",
    "response": "late 15c., \"to heap up for oneself,\" from Old Frenchamasser\"bring together, assemble, accumulate\" (12c.), fromà\"to\" (seead-) +masser, frommasse\"lump, heap, pile\" (from PIE root*mag-\"to knead, fashion, fit\"). Related:Amassed;amassing;amassable."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amastia",
    "response": "\"complete failure of one or both breasts, including the nipple, to develop,\" 1878, medical Latin, from Germanamastia(1841), from Greekamastos\"without breasts,\" from privative prefixa-\"not, without\" (seea-(3)) +mastos\"breast\" (seemasto-) + abstract noun ending-ia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amaterialistic",
    "response": "\"opposed to materialism or materialistic philosophy,\" 1878, froma-(3) \"not\" +materialistic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amateur",
    "response": "1784, \"one who has a taste for some art, study, or pursuit, but does not practice it,\" from Frenchamateur\"one who loves, lover\" (16c., restored from Old Frenchameour), from Latinamatorem(nominativeamator) \"lover, friend,\" agent noun fromamatus, past participle ofamare\"to love\" (seeAmy).The meaning \"one who cultivates and participates (in something) but does not pursue it professionally or with an eye to gain\" (as opposed toprofessional) is from 1786; often with disparaging suggestions of \"dabbler, dilettante,\" but not in athletics, where the disparagement shaded the professional, at least formerly. As an adjective, by 1838."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amateurish",
    "response": "\"having the faults and deficiencies of a non-professional,\" 1863; fromamateur+-ish. Related:Amateurishly;amateurishness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amative",
    "response": "1630s, \"disposed to love or sexual passion,\" from Latinamat-, past-participle stem ofamare\"to love\" (seeAmy) +-ive. Related:Amativeness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amatory",
    "response": "1590s, \"pertaining to love, expressive of love\" (especially sexual love), from Latinamatorius\"loving, amorous,\" fromamat-, past-participle stem ofamare\"to love\" (seeAmy). Related:Amatorial."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amaze",
    "response": "\"overwhelm or confound with sudden surprise or wonder,\" 1580s, a back-formation from Middle Englishamased\"stunned, dazed, bewildered,\" (late 14c.), earlier \"stupefied, irrational, foolish\" (c. 1200), from Old Englishamasod, froma-(1), probably used here as an intensive prefix, +*mæs(seemaze). Related:Amazed;amazing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amazement",
    "response": "1590s, \"mental stupefaction, state of being astonished,\" fromamaze+-ment. The meaning \"overwhelming wonder\" is attested from c. 1600."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amazing",
    "response": "early 15c., \"stupefactive;\" 1590s, \"dreadful;\" present-participle adjective fromamaze. The sense of \"wonderful\" is recorded from 1704. Related:Amazingly; amazingness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amazon",
    "response": "late 14c., \"one of a race of female warriors in Scythia,\" via Old French (13c.) or Latin, from GreekAmazon(mostly in pluralAmazones), probably from an unknown non-Indo-European word, or possibly from an Iranian compound*ha-maz-an-\"(one) fighting together\" [Watkins]. But in folk etymology it has been long derived froma-\"without\" +mazos, variant ofmastos\"breast;\" hence the story that the Amazons cut or burned off one breast so they could draw bowstrings more efficiently.It was also used generally in early Modern English of female warriors; strong, tall, or masculine women; and the queen in chess.The river in South America (originally called by the SpanishRio Santa Maria de la Mar Dulce) was rechristened with this name by Francisco de Orellana, 1541, after an encounter with female warriors of the Tapuyas (or, as some say, beardless, long-haired male tribesmen). Others hold that the river name is a corruption of a native word in Tupi or Guarani meaning \"wave.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amazonian",
    "response": "\"bold, warlike,\" generally of women, 1590s, fromAmazon+-ian. From 1847 in reference to the River Amazon."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambage",
    "response": "late 14c., \"winding or roundabout way, especially in speaking,\" usually plural, from Old Frenchambages, from Latinambages\"circumlocutions\" (seeambagious)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambagious",
    "response": "\"winding, devious, circuitous,\" 1650s, from Frenchambagieux, from Latinambagiosus, fromambages\"circuits, avoidings, circumlocutions,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +agere\"to set in motion, drive; to do, perform; keep in movement\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambassador",
    "response": "late 14c., alsoembassador, \"diplomatic emissary of a ruler in the court of another,\" from Old Frenchembassator,ambassateor, which comes via Provençal or Old Spanish from Latinambactus\"a servant, vassal,\" from Celticamb(i)actos\"a messenger, servant\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\" +*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\").Compareembassy. Forms inam-andem-were used indiscriminately in English 17c.-18c. Until 1893 the United States sent and received none, having only ministers (often called ambassadors), who represented the state, not the sovereign."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambassadorial",
    "response": "\"of or belonging to an ambassador,\" 1759, fromambassador+-al(1)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amber",
    "response": "mid-14c.,ambre grice\"ambergris; perfume made from ambergris,\" from the phrase in Old French (13c.) and Medieval Latin, from Arabic'anbar\"ambergris, morbid secretion of sperm-whale intestines used in perfumes and cookery\" (seeambergris), which was introduced in the West at the time of the Crusades. Arabic-nb-often is pronounced \"-mb-.\"In Europe, the wordamberwas extended to fossil resins from the Baltic (late 13c. in Anglo-Latin; c. 1400 in English), and this has become the main sense as the use of ambergris has waned. Perhaps the perceived connection is that both were found washed up on seashores. Or perhaps it is a different word entirely, of unknown origin. Formerly they were distinguished aswhiteoryellow amberfor the Baltic fossil resin andambergris\"gray amber;\" French distinguished the two substances asambre grisandambre jaune.Remarkable for its static electricity properties, Baltic amber was known to the Romans aselectrum(compareelectric).Amberas an adjective in English is from c. 1500; as a color name 1735. In the Old Testament it translates Hebrewchashmal, a shining metal."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambergris",
    "response": "early 15c., from Old Frenchambre gris\"gray amber,\" \"a wax-like substance of ashy colour, found floating in tropical seas, a morbid secretion from the intestines of the sperm-whale. Used in perfumery, and formerly in cookery\" [OED], via Medieval Latin from Arabic'anbar(seeamber).Its origin was known to Constantinus Africanus (obit c. 1087), but it was a mystery in Samuel Johnson's day, and he records nine different theories; \"What sort of thing is Ambergrease?\" was a type of a puzzling question beyond conjecture. King Charles II's favorite dish was said to be eggs and ambergris [Macauley, \"History of England\"].Frenchgrisis from Frankish*grisor some other Germanic source (cognates: Dutchgrijs, Old High Germangris; seegray(adj.))."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambidexterity",
    "response": "\"faculty of using both hands with equal facility,\" 1650s, with-ity+ Medieval Latinambidexter, literally \"right-handed on both sides,\" fromambi-\"both, on both sides\" (seeambi-) +dexter\"right-handed\" (from PIE root*deks-\"right; south\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambidextrous",
    "response": "alsoambidexterous, \"able to use both hands equally,\" 1640s, with-ous+ Medieval Latinambidexter, literally \"right-handed on both sides,\" fromambi-\"both, on both sides\" (seeambi-) +dexter\"right-handed\" (from PIE root*deks-\"right; south\"). An earlier English use ofambidexter(adj.) meant \"double-dealer, one who takes both sides in a conflict\" (late 14c.).Its opposite,ambilevous\"left-handed on both sides,\" hence \"clumsy\" (1640s) is rare.Ambidexteras a noun is attested from 1530s (in the sense \"one who takes bribes from both sides\") and is the earliest form of the word in English; its sense of \"one who uses both hands equally well\" appears by 1590s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambience",
    "response": "1797, \"environmental surroundings,\" used as a term in art for the arrangements that support the main effect of the piece, from Frenchambiance\"atmosphere, mood, character, quality, tone,\" from Latinambiens\"a going around,\" present participle ofambire\"to go around,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +ire\"go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\"). The notion of \"going all around\" led to the sense of \"encircling, lying all around.\" Compareambiance."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambient",
    "response": "1590s, \"surrounding, encircling,\" from Latinambientem(nominativeambiens) \"a going around,\" present participle ofambire\"to go around, go about,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +ire\"go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\"). The notion of \"going all around\" led to the sense of \"encircling, lying all around.\""
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambiguity",
    "response": "c. 1400, \"uncertainty, doubt, indecision, hesitation,\" from Old Frenchambiguiteand directly from Latinambiguitatem(nominativeambiguitas) \"double meaning, equivocalness, double sense,\" noun of state fromambiguus\"having double meaning, doubtful\" (seeambiguous). The meaning \"obscurity in description\" is from early 15c."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambiguous",
    "response": "\"of doubtful or uncertain nature, open to various interpretations,\" 1520s, from Latinambiguus\"having double meaning, shifting, changeable, doubtful,\" an adjective derived fromambigere\"to dispute about, contend, debate,\" literally \"to wander, go about, go around,\" figuratively \"hesitate, waver, be in doubt,\" fromambi-\"about\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +agere\"drive, lead, act\" (from PIE root*ag-\"to drive, draw out or forth, move\"). The English word is first attested in Sir Thomas More (1528); relatedambiguitydates to c. 1400. Related:Ambiguously;ambiguousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambit",
    "response": "late 14c., \"space surrounding a building or town; precinct;\" 1590s, \"a circuit;\" from Latinambitus\"a going round, a circuit, circumference,\" noun use of past participle ofambire\"to go around, go about,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +ire\"go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambition",
    "response": "mid-14c.,ambicioun, \"eager or inordinate desire for honor or preferment,\" from Old Frenchambicion(13c.), or directly from Latinambitionem(nominativeambitio) \"a going around,\" especially to solicit votes, hence \"a striving for favor, courting, flattery; a desire for honor, thirst for popularity,\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofambire\"to go around, go about,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +ire\"go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\").Rarely used in English or Latin the literal sense. In early use in English always pejorative, of inordinate or overreaching desire;ambitionwas grouped withprideandvainglory, and sometimes meant little more than \"arrogance.\" The neutral or positive senses are modern. The meaning \"object of strong desire\" is from c. 1600."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambitious",
    "response": "late 14c.,ambicious, \"craving, yearning, overambitious,\" from Latinambitiosus\"eager for public office, eager to win favor, ingratiating,\" fromambitio\"a going around (to solicit votes),\" noun of action from past-participle stem ofambire\"to go around, go about,\" fromamb-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") +ire\"go\" (from PIE root*ei-\"to go\"). The meaning \"springing from ambition\" is by 1751. Related:Ambitiously;ambitiousness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambivalence",
    "response": "\"simultaneous conflicting feelings,\" 1924 (by 1912 asambivalency), from GermanAmbivalenz, coined 1910 by Swiss psychologist Eugen Bleuler on the model of GermanEquivalenz\"equivalence,\" etc. (for which seeequivalence), from Latinambi-\"both, on both sides\" (seeambi-) +valentia\"strength,\" an abstract noun from the present participle ofvalere\"be strong\" (from PIE root*wal-\"to be strong\"). A psychological term that by 1929 had taken on a broader literary and general sense."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambivalent",
    "response": "\"having simultaneous conflicting feelings or contradictory ideas about something,\" 1916, originally a term in psychology; a back-formation fromambivalence. In general use by 1929."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambivert",
    "response": "\"person exhibiting features of an extrovert and an introvert,\" coined by Kimball Young in \"Source Book for Social Psychology\" (1927), fromambi-\"about, around\" +-vert(as in earlierintrovert), which is ultimately from Latinvertere\"to turn\" (seeversus). Related:Ambiversion."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amble",
    "response": "\"to move easily and gently without hard shocks,\" as a horse does when it first lifts the two legs on one side and then the two on the other, early 14c., from Old Frenchambler, in reference to a horse or other quadruped, \"go at a steady, easy pace\" (12c.), from Latinambulare\"to walk, to go about, take a walk,\" perhaps a compound ofambi-\"around\" (from PIE root*ambhi-\"around\") and-ulare, from a Proto-Italic*ala-\"to wander,\" from PIE root*el-\"to go\" (source also of Greekale\"wandering,\"alaomai\"wander about;\" Latvianaluot\"go around or astray\"), as per de Vaan. Until 1590s used only of horses or persons on horseback. Related:Ambled;ambling."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambler",
    "response": "\"a horse which ambles; a person who ambles,\" late 14c., agent noun fromamble(v.)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amblyopia",
    "response": "1706, \"weakening of the eyesight without any apparent defect in the eyes,\" medical Latin, from Greekamblyōpia\"dim-sightedness,\" noun of action fromōps\"eye\" (from PIE root*okw-\"to see\")  +amblys\"dulled, blunt,\" a word of uncertain origin; according to Watkins possibly from a suffixed form of PIE root*mel-(1) \"soft.\" With abstract noun ending-ia. Related:Amblyopic."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ambrose",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from LatinAmbrosius, from Greekambrosios\"immortal, belonging to the immortals\" (seeambrosia). TheAmbrosianLibrary in Milan, founded 1609 by Cardinal Borromeo, is named for Saint Ambrose (obit 397), bishop of Milan."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambrose",
    "response": "masc. proper name, from LatinAmbrosius, from Greekambrosios\"immortal, belonging to the immortals\" (seeambrosia). TheAmbrosianLibrary in Milan, founded 1609 by Cardinal Borromeo, is named for Saint Ambrose (obit 397), bishop of Milan."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambrosia",
    "response": "1560s, \"favored food or drink of the gods,\" from Latinambrosia, from Greekambrosia\"food of the gods,\" noun use of fem. ofambrosios\"divine,\" probably literally \"of the immortals,\" fromambrotos\"immortal, imperishable,\" froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +mbrotos, related tomortos\"mortal,\" from PIE root*mer-\"to rub away, harm\" (also \"to die\" and forming words referring to death and to beings subject to death).The name was applied to certain herbs by Pliny and Dioscorides; it has been used of various foods for mortals since 1680s (originally of fruit drinks); and was used figuratively for \"anything delightful\" by 1731."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambrosial",
    "response": "1590s, \"immortal, divine, of the quality of ambrosia;\" seeambrosia+-al. The sense of \"fragrant, delicious\" is from 1660s. Other adjectives wereambrosiac(c. 1600);ambrosian(1630s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambrotype",
    "response": "type of photograph on glass with lights given by silver and shades by a dark background showing through, 1855, American English, apparently from Greekambrotos\"immortal, imperishable\" (seeambrosia), with second element fromdaguerreotype."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambulance",
    "response": "1798, \"mobile or field hospital,\" from Frenchambulance, formerly(hôpital) ambulant(17c.), literally \"walking (hospital),\" from Latinambulantem(nominativeambulans), present participle ofambulare\"to walk, go about\" (seeamble).The word was not common in English until the meaning transferred from \"field hospital\" to \"vehicle for conveying wounded from the field\" (1854) during the Crimean War. It was extended early 20c. to vehicles to transport the sick or wounded in civilian life. In late 19c. U.S. the same word was used dialectally to mean \"prairie wagon.\"Ambulance-chaseras a contemptuous term for a type of lawyer is by 1897."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambulant",
    "response": "1610s, \"walking, moving from place to place,\" from Latinambulantem(nominativeambulans), present participle ofambulare\"to walk, go about\" (seeamble(v.)). Of diseases, denoting cases in which the patient may be up and around, by 1913."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambulate",
    "response": "\"to walk, move about,\" 1620s, a back-formation fromambulation, or else from Latinambulatus, past participle ofambulare\"to walk, go about\" (seeamble(v.)). Related:Ambulated;ambulating."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambulation",
    "response": "\"act of walking about,\" 1570s, from Latinambulationem(nominativeambulatio), noun of action from past-participle stem ofambulare\"to walk, go about\" (seeamble(v.)). The word was used earlier in reference to the spread of disease (1540s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambulatory",
    "response": "1620s, \"pertaining to walking;\" also \"movable; shifting, not permanent,\" from Latinambulatorius\"pertaining to a walker; movable,\" fromambulator, agent noun from past-participle stem ofambulare\"to walk, go about\" (seeamble(v.)). Middle English hadambulary\"movable\" (mid-15c.). Related:Ambulatorial."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambuscade",
    "response": "1580s, \"act of lying concealed for the purpose of attacking by surprise,\" essentially a variant form ofambush(q.v.), \"now more formal as a military term\" [OED]. It is a reborrowing of that French word after it had been Italianized:Ambuscadeis from Frenchembuscade(16c.), Gallicized from Italianimboscata, literally \"a hiding in the bush,\" compounded from the same elements as Old Frenchembuscher.Sometimes in early use in English it appears asambuscado, with a faux Spanish ending of the sort popular in 17c. As a verb, \"attack from a concealed position,\" by 1590s. Related:Ambuscaded; ambuscading."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ambush",
    "response": "mid-14c.,embushen, enbushen, inbuchen, \"to hide in ambush,\" from Old Frenchembuschier(13c., Modern Frenchembûcher) \"to hide, conceal, lay an ambush,\" fromen-\"in\" (ultimately from PIE root*en\"in\") +busch\"wood,\" which is apparently from Frankish*busk\"bush, woods,\" or a similar Germanic source (seebush(n.)). The notion probably is \"hide in the bush,\" or \"lure into the bush.\" Related:Ambushed;ambushing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amelia",
    "response": "fem. proper name, Latin, but said to be of Germanic origin and mean literally \"laborious\" (cognates: Old Norseama\"to trouble\"); the name was assimilated with Roman gens nameAemilia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amelia",
    "response": "fem. proper name, Latin, but said to be of Germanic origin and mean literally \"laborious\" (cognates: Old Norseama\"to trouble\"); the name was assimilated with Roman gens nameAemilia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ameliorate",
    "response": "1728, \"to make better,\" in some cases perhaps a back-formation fromameliorationon pattern of Frenchaméliorer, or else from Medieval Latinamelioratus, past participle ofameliorare. The intransitive sense of \"grow better\" is by 1789. The simpler formmelioratewas used in Middle English. Related:Ameliorated;ameliorating;ameliorable."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amelioration",
    "response": "1650s, \"a making or becoming better,\" from Frenchamélioration, from Old Frenchameillorer(12c.), froma\"to\" (seead-) +meillior(Modern Frenchmeìlleur) \"to better, repair, improve,\" from Late Latinmeliorare\"improve,\" from Latinmelior\"better,\" perhaps originally \"stronger\" (from PIE root*mel-(2) \"strong, great\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ameliorative",
    "response": "\"tending to make better,\" 1796, fromameliorate+-ive."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amen",
    "response": "Old English, from Late Latinamen, from Ecclesiastical Greekamen, from Hebrewamen\"truth,\" used adverbially as an expression of agreement (as in Deuteronomy xxvii.26, I Kings i.36), from Semitic roota-m-n\"to be trustworthy, confirm, support.\"Compare similar use of Modern Englishcertainly,absolutely. Used in Old English only at the end of Gospels, otherwise translated asSoðlic!orSwa hit ys, orSy!As an expression of concurrence after prayers, it is recorded from early 13c.Amen corneris attested from 1860."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amen",
    "response": "Old English, from Late Latinamen, from Ecclesiastical Greekamen, from Hebrewamen\"truth,\" used adverbially as an expression of agreement (as in Deuteronomy xxvii.26, I Kings i.36), from Semitic roota-m-n\"to be trustworthy, confirm, support.\"Compare similar use of Modern Englishcertainly,absolutely. Used in Old English only at the end of Gospels, otherwise translated asSoðlic!orSwa hit ys, orSy!As an expression of concurrence after prayers, it is recorded from early 13c.Amen corneris attested from 1860."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amenability",
    "response": "\"amenableness, liability to answer, disposition to respond to,\" 1761; seeamenable+-ity."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amenable",
    "response": "1590s, \"liable to make answer or defense, accountable,\" from Anglo-Frenchamenable, from Old Frenchamener\"bring, take, conduct, lead\" (to the law), from \"to\" (seead-) +mener\"to lead,\" from Latinminare\"to drive (cattle) with shouts,\" variant ofminari\"to threaten,\" also \"to jut, project\" (from PIE root*men-(2) \"to project\"). The sense of \"tractable\" is from 1803, on the notion of \"disposed to answer or submit to influence.\" Related:Amenably."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amenableness",
    "response": "\"liability to answer, disposition to respond to,\" 1830, fromamenable+-ness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amend",
    "response": "early 13c.,amenden, \"to free from faults, rectify,\" from Old Frenchamender\"correct, set right, make better, improve\" (12c.), from Latinemendare\"to correct, free from fault,\" fromex\"out\" (seeex-) +menda,mendum\"fault, physical blemish; error,\" from PIE*mend-\"physical defect, fault\" (source also of Sanskritminda\"physical blemish,\" Old Irishmennar\"stain, blemish,\" Welshmann\"sign, mark;\" Hittitemant-\"something harming\").The spelling witha-is unusual but early and also is found in Provençal and Italian. In English, the word has been supplanted in senses of \"repair; cure\" by its shortened offspringmend(v.). The meaning \"to add to legislation\" (ostensibly to correct or improve it) is recorded from 1777. Related:Amended;amending."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amendable",
    "response": "1580s, \"capable of correction or repair;\" seeamend+-able. Related:Amendability."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amendment",
    "response": "early 13c., \"betterment, improvement;\" c. 1300, of persons, \"correction, reformation,\" from Old Frenchamendement\"rectification, correction; advancement, improvement,\" fromamender\"to amend\" (seeamend). The sense expanded 17c. to include \"correction of error in a legal process\" (c. 1600) and \"alteration of a writ or bill\" to remove its faults (1690s)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amends",
    "response": "early 14c., \"recompense, compensation for loss or injury,\" collective singular, from Old Frenchamendes\"fine, penalty, reparation, compensation,\" plural ofamende\"reparation,\" fromamender\"to amend\" (seeamend)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amenity",
    "response": "late 14c., \"quality of being pleasant or agreeable,\" from Latinamoenitatem(nominativeamoenitas) \"delightfulness, pleasantness,\" fromamoenus\"pleasant,\" which is perhaps related toamare\"to love\" (seeAmy)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amenorrhea",
    "response": "\"suppression of menstruation, especially from a cause other than age or pregnancy,\" 1804, Modern Latin, from Greek privative prefixa-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +men\"month\" (seemoon(n.)) +rhein\"to flow\" (from PIE root*sreu-\"to flow\"). Related:amenorrheal."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ament",
    "response": "\"person born an idiot,\" 1894, from Latinamentia\"madness,\" fromamentem\"mad,\" fromaforab\"away from\" (seea-(2)) +mentem\"mind\" (from PIE root*men-(1) \"to think\")."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amentia",
    "response": "\"mental deficiency,\" late 14c., from Latinamentia\"madness,\" fromamentem\"mad,\" fromaforab\"away from\" (seea-(2)) +mentem\"mind\" (from PIE root*men-(1) \"to think\") + abstract noun ending-ia."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amerce",
    "response": "\"punishment by arbitrary or discretionary fine,\" 1215, earlieramercy, Anglo-Frenchamercier\"to fine,\" frommerci\"mercy, grace\" (seemercy). The legal phraseestre a merci\"to be at the mercy of\" (a tribunal, etc.) was corrupted toestre amercié, a good example of how an adverbial phrase in legalese tends to become a verb (compareabandon).Related:Amercement;amerciable/amerceable."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "America",
    "response": "1507, \"the western hemisphere, North and South America,\" in Cartographer Martin Waldseemüller's treatise\"Cosmographiae Introductio,\"from Modern LatinAmericanus, traditionally afterAmerigoVespucci (1454-1512) who made two trips to the New World as a navigator and claimed to have discovered it. His published works put forward the idea that it was a new continent, and he was first to call itNovus Mundus\"New World.\"Amerigois more easily Latinized thanVespucci(LatinVesputius, which might have yielded place-nameVesputia). The sense in English naturally was restricted toward the British colonies, then the United States.The man's nameAmerigois Germanic, said to derive from GothicAmalrich, literally \"work-ruler.\" The Old English form of the name has come down as surnamesEmmerich,Emery, etc. The Italian fem. form merged intoAmelia.Colloquial pronunciation \"Ameri-kay,\" not uncommon 19c., goes back to at least 1643 and a poem that rhymed the word withaway.Amerika\"U.S. society viewed as racist, fascist, oppressive, etc.\" is attested from 1969; the spelling is German but it also might suggest the KKK."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "American",
    "response": "1570s, originally \"one of the aboriginal peoples discovered in the Western Hemisphere by Europeans,\" from Modern LatinAmericanus, fromAmerica(q.v.). The original sense is nowNative Americans; the sense of \"resident of North America of European (originally British) descent\" is from 1765."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Americanism",
    "response": "1781, in reference to words or phrases used in North America and distinct from British use, coined by John Witherspoon, president of Princeton College, fromAmerican+-ism. (American English\"English language as spoken in the United States\" is recorded by  1806, in Webster.)Americanismin the sense \"attachment to or preference for the U.S.\" is attested by 1797 in the writings of Thomas Jefferson."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Americanization",
    "response": "\"the act or process of becoming more American in character or nature,\" 1816, noun of state or action fromAmericanize."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Americanize",
    "response": "\"render American in character,\" 1797, fromAmerican+-ize. Related:Americanized;Americanizing."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "americium",
    "response": "artificial radioactive element, 1946, fromAmerica+ metallic element ending-ium."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amerind",
    "response": "1899, coined by Maj. John Wesley Powell at the Bureau of American Ethnology, where he was director, fromAmerican+Indian."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amerindian",
    "response": "1900; seeAmerind, of which it is the derived adjective."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amethyst",
    "response": "violet-colored quartz, late 13c.,amatist, from Old Frenchametiste(12c., Modern Frenchaméthyste) and directly from Medieval Latinamatistus, from Latinamethystus, from Greekamethystos\"amethyst,\" noun use of an adjective meaning \"not intoxicating; not drunken,\" froma-\"not\" (seea-(3)) +methyskein\"make drunk,\" frommethys\"wine\" (from PIE root*medhu-\"honey; mead;\" seemead(n.1)).The stone had a reputation among the ancients for preventing drunkenness; this was perhaps sympathetic magic suggested by its wine-like color. Beekes writes that the stone \"was named after its color: the red of wine diluted with water such that it is no longer intoxicating.\" When drinking, people wore rings made of it to ward off the effects. The spelling was restored in early Modern English."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Amex",
    "response": "1970, contraction ofAmerican Express, a trademark registered in U.S. 1950 by American Express Co., originally an express mail service. Its credit card dates from 1958."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ami",
    "response": "\"friend, lover,\" c. 1300, from Old Frenchamy,ami\"friend, lover, beloved; kinsman\" (11c.), from Latinamicus\"friend\" (seeAmy)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "ami",
    "response": "\"friend, lover,\" c. 1300, from Old Frenchamy,ami\"friend, lover, beloved; kinsman\" (11c.), from Latinamicus\"friend\" (seeAmy)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amiability",
    "response": "\"quality of being friendly and agreeable,\" 1779, fromamiable+-ity.Amiablenessis recorded from 1530s."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amiable",
    "response": "late 14c., \"kindly, friendly,\" also \"worthy of love or admiration,\" from Old Frenchamiable\"pleasant, kind; worthy to be loved\" (12c.), from Late Latinamicabilis\"friendly,\" from Latinamicus\"friend, loved one,\" noun use of an adjective, \"friendly, loving,\" fromamare\"to love\" (seeAmy).The form and sense were confused in Old French withamable\"lovable\" (from Latinamare\"to love\"), and by 16c. the English word also had a secondary sense of \"exciting love or delight,\" especially by having an agreeable temper and a kind heart. The word was subsequently reborrowed by English in Latin form without the sense contamination asamicable."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amicability",
    "response": "\"friendliness,\" 1650s, fromamicable+-ity."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amicable",
    "response": "early 15c., \"pleasant,\" from Late Latinamicabilis\"friendly,\" a word in Roman law, from Latinamicus\"friend,\" ultimately fromamare\"to love\" (seeAmy). In modern use \"characterized by friendliness, free from hard feelings, peaceable, socially harmonious.\" Compareamiable, which is the same word through French. Related:Amicableness."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amicably",
    "response": "\"in a friendly manner, without controversy,\" 1630s, fromamicable+-ly(2)."
  },
  {
    "prompt": "amid",
    "response": "Middle Englishamidde, from Old Englishon middan\"in the middle,\" from dative singular ofmidde\"mid, middle\" (from PIE root*medhyo-\"middle\"); also seea-(1). The phrase evidently was felt as \"in (the) middle\" and thus followed by a genitive case, and if this had endured we would follow it today withof. (Seeamidstfor further evolution along this line).The same applies to equivalents in Latin (in medio) and Greek (en meso), both originally adjective phrases which evolved to take the genitive case. But in later Old Englishon middanalso was treated as a preposition and followed by dative. Used in compounds from early 13c."
  }
]